<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2063" xml:id="Chevedden_Treaties20" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.BurnsTreaties 2</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Chevedden_Treaties20</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ويتفضّـ</supplied>ـل مقتضاه بالأذان في الصّوامع والصّلاة في المساجد وإقـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـا</supplied>مة <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>لخطبة في الجمع والأ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عـ</supplied>ـيادِ وغير ذ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لك</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="2"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أيّـ</supplied>ـة دوا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بّ</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>لا غير ذلك من <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـكلف إلّا إن حدث فساد في بعض البلاد الّتِي من بلنسية إلى بيار فله حشدهم لذلك وعلى أن يكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـونو</supplied>ا مُأَمّنِين <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نفوسهم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وأموالهم</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">فـ</supplied>ـلا اعتر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>ض عليه في ملـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـكـ</supplied>ِـهِ ومَن كان من خواص النّاس ووجوههم فيخفر في البر والبحر ويوصل إلى مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـقصـ</supplied>ـوده من ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لبلا</supplied>د و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأقاليم</supplied> و 
<lb n="4"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الحصون</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والقصاب</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والمدن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والقرى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والسواحل</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والموانئ</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ويحـ</supplied>ـكم ڤي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">النـ</supplied>ـو<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">از</supplied>ل الحادثة پعد انقضا الامَدِ بينهم وبين النصارى بشهادة شاهدين مرضيين مسلم وپصـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـرا</supplied>ني ولا پو<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>حد فما فوقه من 
<lb n="5"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ولا</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يحكم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بتأديبه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إ</supplied>ن أخـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـفى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>سيرًا من المسلمين وأن يجبر على صاحبه الأسير إن عُثِر عليه وعلى الملك أيّده اللّه قتل من يغير على المسلميـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـن</supplied> فـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـلـ</supplied>ـو قتله مسلم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سقط</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="APD">حقن</rdg></app> 
<lb n="6"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">قتله</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمه</rdg></app> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وأن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يـ</supplied>ـكلّف المسلمين بنآءً في القصبة ويكونون على اختيارهم في بنآءِ سور الجفنةِ <sic n="superfluous">والمدنية</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">والمدينة</supplied> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>لا يجبرون عليه ولا يمنعون منه وعلى أن يبادي للملكِ 
<lb n="7"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ببناء</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">القصبة</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والأسوار</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">من</supplied> قبل ولَه زكاة الماشية على سنّةِ للمسلمين ولا يبقى رسم من رسوم القبالاتِ المحدثة في <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأ</supplied>سواق برسم السّور وغيـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـر</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذلك</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="8"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ولزم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـملك أيّده اللّه هذه المعاهدة على شروطها والملكة المعظّمة دونة إِيأُليش ولزم ذلك أيضا ابنه الإ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">فَـ</supplied>ـا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نـ</supplied>ـت د<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>ن أدفونش وجميع عقيبه 
<lb n="9"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وحلفو</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الوفاء</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بها</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بالجميع</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مـ</supplied>ـن المملكة باللّه العظيم <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>بالصّليب والإنجيل وبكل ما لا يصح الحنث للحالف به في ملّته والتزم الملك أيّده <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>خليفه الإ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">فا</supplied>نت ابنه و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">خلـ</supplied>ـفا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ؤه</supplied> 
<lb n="10"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بالجميع</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ما</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذكر</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ولزم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">القائدين</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أعزّهما</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">هذه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">المعاهدة</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شروطها</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ولزم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذلك</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أيضا</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">من</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كان</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">من</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">خواصّ</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">النّاس</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ووجوه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شـ</supplied>ـاطبة وما <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إليـ</supplied>ـها وألزموها من وراءَهم من طبقاتِ النّاس وحلفوا على الوفاءِ بها باللّه الكَـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـريم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ومحمّد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">رسوله</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">صلّى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عليه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وسلّم</supplied> 
<lb n="11"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وبالقرآن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الّذي</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أنزل</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عليه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والتزم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">القائدان</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أعزّهما</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وجميع</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عقيبهما</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">با</supplied>لجميع ما ذكر <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">با</supplied>للّه سـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـبحا</supplied>نه وكل من حضر وكتب القائدان أعزّهما اللّه وسا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ئـ</supplied>ـر من حضر أسماءهم أسفل <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">استصدر</supplied> في <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يـ</supplied>ـو<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">م</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأحد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الخامـ</supplied>ـس والـ]ـعشر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ين</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لشهر</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذي</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الحجّة</supplied> 
<lb n="12"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عام</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أحد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وأربعين</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وستّمائة</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>ذَلك للـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـملـ</supplied>ـك <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أيّـ</supplied>ـده اللّه وأن يبقى بأيدي المسلمين كل مَا بأيديهم من أسَارى النّصارى في الأمدِ وبعده <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>لا يعترضون في <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأمد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وبعده</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="13"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شهد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذلك</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> ومحمّد بن أحمد بن محمّد بن أحمد بن عيسى الأنصاري ومحمّد بن عبد اللّه بن يعقوب ومحمّد بن طلحة بن يعقوب بن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">طلحة</unclear> وعبد السّلام بن يوسف <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** wa yatafaḍḍalu muqtaḍā hu bi ăl ʾaḏāni fī ăṣ ṣawāmiʿi wa ăṣ ṣalāẗi fī ăl masāǧidi wa ʾiqāmaẗi ăl ḫuṭbaẗi fī ăl ǧumaʿi wa ăl ʾaʿyādi wa ġayri ḏālika *** 
 <lb n="2"/>*** ʾayyaẗa dawābb:in wa lā ġayra ḏālika mina ăl kulafi ʾillā ʾin ḥadaṯa fasād:un fī baʿḍi ăl bilādi ăllatī min balansiyaẗa ʾilà biyāra biyar:in fa la hu ḥašdu hum li ḏālika wa ʿalà ʾan yakūnū muʾammanīna fī 
 <lb n="3"/>nufūsi him wa ʾamwāli him *** fa lā ĭʿtirāḍa ʿalay hi fī milki hi wa man kāna min ḫawāṣṣi ăn nāsi wa wuǧūhi him fa yuḫfaru fī ăl barri wa ăl baḥri wa yūṣalu ʾilà maqṣūdi hi mina ăl bilādi wa ăl ʾaqālīmi wa ăl ḥuṣūni 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ăl qiṣābi wa ăl muduni wa ăl qurà wa ăs sawāḥili wa ăl mawāniʾi *** wa yuḥkamu fī ăn nawāzili ăl ḥādiṯaẗi baʿda ĭnqiḍāʾi ăl ʾamadi bayna hum wa bayna ăn naṣārà bi šahādaẗi šāhidayni marḍiyyayni muslim:in wa naṣrāniyy:in wa lā bi wāḥid:in fa mā fawqa hu mina ăš šuhūdi 
 <lb n="5"/>*** wa lā yuḥkamu bi taʾdībi hi ʾin ʾaḫfà ʾasīr:an mina ăl muslimīna wa ʾan yuǧbara ʿalà ṣāḥibi hi ăl ʾasīru ʾin ʿuṯira ʿalay hi wa ʿalà ăl maliki ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu qatlu man yuġīru ʿalà ăl muslimīna fa law qatala hu muslim:un saqaṭa ḥuqina 
 <lb n="6"/>qatlu damu hu wa ʾan yukallifa ăl muslimīna bināʾ:an fī ăl qaṣbaẗi wa yakūnūna ʿalà ĭḫtiyāri him fī bināʾi sūri ăl ǧafnaẗi wa ăl madīnaẗi wa lā yuǧbarūna ʿalay hi wa lā yumnaʿūna min hu wa ʿalà ʾan yubādiya li l maliki 
 <lb n="7"/>bi bināʾi ăl qaṣbaẗi wa ăl ʾaswāri *** min qabl:in wa la hu zakāẗu ăl māšiyaẗi ʿalà sunnaẗ:in li l muslimīna wa lā yabqà rasm:un min rusūmi ăl qabālāti ăl muḥdaṯaẗi fī ăl ʾaswāqi bi rasmi ăs sūri wa ġayri ḏālika *** 
 <lb n="8"/>*** wa lazima ăl maliku ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu hāḏihi ăl muʿāhadaẗa ʿalà šurūṭi hā wa ăl malikaẗu ăl muʿaẓẓamaẗu dūnaẗu ʾīʾulīšu wa lazima ḏālika ʾayḍ:an ĭbnu hu ăl ʾifāntu dūn ʾadfūnšu wa ǧamīʿu ʿaqībi hi 
 <lb n="9"/>*** wa ḥalafū ʿalà ăl wafāʾi bi hā bi ăl ǧamīʿi mina ăl mamlakaẗi bi ăl lāhi ăl ʿaẓīmi wa bi ăṣ ṣalībi wa ăl ʾinǧīli wa bi kulli mā lā yaṣiḥḥu ăl ḥinṯu li l ḥālifi bi hi fī millati hi wa ĭltazama ăl maliku ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu wa ḫalīfu hu ăl ʾifāntu ĭbnu hu wa ḫulafāʾu hu 
 <lb n="10"/>bi ăl ǧamīʿi mā ḏukira wa lazima ăl qāʾidayni ʾaʿazza humā ăl lāhu hāḏihi ăl muʿāhadaẗa ʿalà šurūṭi hā wa lazima ḏālika ʾayḍ:an man kāna min ḫawāṣṣi ăn nāsi wa wuǧūhi šāṭibaẗa wa mā ʾilay hā wa ʾalzamū hā man warāʾa hum min ṭabaqāti ăn nāsi wa ḥalafū ʿalà ăl wafāʾi bi hā bi ăl lāhi ăl karīmi wa muḥammad:in rasūli hi ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalay hi wa sallama 
 <lb n="11"/>wa bi ăl qurʾāni ăllaḏī ʾanzala ʿalay hi wa ĭltazama ăl qāʾidāni ʾaʿazza humā ăl lāhu wa ǧamīʿu ʿaqībi himā *** bi ăl ǧamīʿi mā ḏukira bi ăl lāhi subḥāna hu wa kullu man ḥaḍara wa kataba ăl qāʾidāni ʾaʿazza humā ăl lāhu wa sāʾiru man ḥaḍara ʾasmāʾa hum ʾasfala ŭstuṣdira fī yawmi ăl ʾaḥadi ăl ḫāmisi wa ăl ʿišrīna li šahri ḏī ăl ḥiǧǧaẗi 
 <lb n="12"/>ʿāma ʾaḥad:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa sitti miʾaẗ:in *** wa ḏālika li l maliki ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu wa ʾan yabqà bi ʾaydī ăl muslimīna kullu mā bi ʾaydī him min ʾasārà ăn naṣārà fī ăl ʾamadi wa baʿda hu wa lā yaʿtariḍūna fī ăl ʾamadi wa baʿda hu *** 
 <lb n="13"/>šahida ʿalà ḏālika *** wa muḥammadu bnu ʾaḥmada bni muḥammadi bni ʾaḥmada bni ʿīsà ăl ʾanṣāriyyu wa muḥammadu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni yaʿqūba wa muḥammadu bnu ṭalḥaẗa bni yaʿqūba bni ṭalḥaẗa wa ʿabdu ăs salāmi bnu yūsufa *** 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		...[?The king shall deign to grant] his demand for the call to prayer from minarets, prayer in the mosques, and the performance of the Friday sermon on Fridays, on feast days, and the like
			<lb n="2"/>
		[?The king shall not demand? an]y pack animals or any other obligations. However, if there is a revolt [fasād] in the territory from Valencia to Biar, he [the king] shall call them [i.e., the townsmen of Játiva] for military service for that purpose. [it is agreed] that they [the Jativans] shall be granted crown protection [?with respect to?]
			<lb n="3"/>
		[?person and chattels.?] ... There shall be no interference with regard to one&#039;s property. Any person from among the people of distinction and theiry leading men shall bei protected [wile traveling] by land and by sea and shall be escorted to his destination, whether [?territory?], [?regions?],
			<lb n="4"/>
		[?castles, citadels, cities, towns, coastlands, or harbors.?]. ... In lawsuits filed after the period [of the agreement] between them [the Muslims] and the Christians, one shall receive a judicial decision on the basis of testimony of two approved male witnesses, one Muslim and one Christian - but not on the basis of one male witness - and if there are more witnesses than that ...
			<lb n="5"/>
		... [?It is also agreed that one shall not be liable to punishment if?] he harbors a Muslim captive, but the captive shall be restored to his master if he is found. It is incumbent upon the king - may God support him! - to execute anyone who makes and attack on the Muslims. And if the attacker should be killed by a Muslim, [?the Muslim may not be killed?].
			<lb n="6"/>
		... The Muslims shall be responsible for construction on the citadel, and they may do as they like with respect to work on the outer wall of the city and on the city &lt;wall&gt;; they may not be compelled to do it, nor are they prohibited from doing so. [It is also agreed] that he [the ruler of Játiva] shall inform the king
			<lb n="7"/>
		[?about construction on the citadel and the walls ... It is also agreed that a tax (or taxes) shall be continued?] as before. He [he king] shall receive the tax on livestock according to the sunnah of the Muslims, [but] a certain qabālah-tax recently imposed on the markets for wall [maintenance] and the like shall not remain [in force] ...
			<lb n="8"/>
		... [The] king - may God support him! - [shall be bound to] this agreement by [all of] its articles, as shall the exalted queen, Dona Yoles. His son, the Infant Don Alfonso, and all of his descendants shall also be bound to it.
			<lb n="9"/>
		... [?and they shall take an oath of fidelity to it in al of?] the kingdom. By God Almighty; by the Cross and the Gospel; by all that by which perjury by the oath-taker is prohibited in his community. The king - may God support him! - and his successor the Infant, his son, and his successors shall undertake
			<lb n="10"/>
		[?all that has been specified. The two qāʾids - may God glorify them! shall be bound to this agreement by all of its articles. The people of distinction and the leading men of? J]átiva and its district [?shall also be bound to it?], and they shall make it binding on men of lower rank. They [i.e., the leadership of Játiva] shall take an oath of fidelity to it [the agreement]. By God, the Gen[erous; ?by Muḥammad his Messenger - may God bless him and grant him salvation!;?]
			<lb n="11"/>
		[?by the Koran which was revealed to him. The two qāyids - may God glorify them! - and all of their descendants ... shall undertake?] all that has been specified. By God, praise Him! The two qāʾids - may God glorify them! - and the rest of those present whose names are below attended [the proceedings] and drew up [this document]. [Issued on Sunday the] twen[ty-fifth of the month of Dhū al-Ḥiǧǧah]
			<lb n="12"/>
		[in the year 641 (5 June 1244) ... and] that belongs to the king - may God support him! The Muslims shall retain possession of their Christian captives during the period [of the agreement] and after it, [and] they [the captives] shall not object [to this] during [the period of the agreement and after it.] ...
			<lb n="13"/>
		[?Witnessed by?] [first name], Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad Ibn ʿìsá al-Anṣārī, Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Yaʿqūb, Muḥammad ibn Ṭalḥah ibn Yaʿqūb ibn Ṭalḥah (?), and ʿAbd al-Salām ibn Yūsuf ...
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
