<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1667" xml:id="Fahmi_060" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 06</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_060</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169418</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى موسيس بن أبيمة اشترى من بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس من سكّان ططون من 
<lb n="3"/>  كورة الفيّوم اشترى منها ثلث الغرفتين الّتي ورثتها من أبيها سرمادة وهو ثمنية أسهم من أربعة 
<lb n="4"/>  وعشرين سهما مع حصّتها من المخرج وصطح الغرفتين اشترى ذلك منها مدخلهم ومخرجهم وسلفهم 
<lb n="5"/>  وعلوهم بدينارين مثاقيل طري عينا ذهبا قد قبضت بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس من موسيس بن أبيمة 
<lb n="6"/>  هذا الثّمن تامّا وافيا وبرئت من هذه الحصّة المعروفة لها مشاع غير مقسوم مع أختها ومرة أخيها 
<lb n="7"/>  وسلّمت ذلك إلى موسيس بن أبيمة فتسلّمها منها وأجازها وقبضها وصار ذلك مالا من ماله وملك 
<lb n="8"/>  من ملكه إن شا باع وإن شا عمر وإن شا عطّل وإن شا وهب باعت بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة هذا المنزل 
<lb n="9"/>  المحدود الموجود في هذا الكتاب على شرط بيع الإسلام وعهدته فمتى ما ادّعت بدعوى أو أحد أسبابها 
<lb n="10"/>  بعد هذا الكتاب أو احتجّوا بحجّة أو اعتلّوا بعلّة فدعوى من يدّعي في ذلك باطل وزور ومتى ما كان من علقة 
<lb n="11"/>  أو بياعة أو طارئ بدين أو مستحق فنفاذ ذلك وخلاصه عليها من خالص مالها بالغا ما بلغ كائنا ما كان 
<lb n="12"/>  وحد حدود هذا المنزل وهي الغرفتين الّتي على خزانتين لموسيس حدّهما القبلي دار موسيس بن أبيمة 
<lb n="13"/>  والبحري منزل موسيس بن أبيمة والشّرقي منزل سرمادة بن سويرس والغربي موسيس بن أبيمة شهد 
<lb n="14"/>  على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب بعد أن قرئ عليها وعرفت ما فيه وترجم لها 
<lb n="15"/>  بالقبطيّة حرفا حرفا فأقرّت بفهمه في صحّة من بدنها وعقلها وجواز أمرها طائعة غير مكرهة طالبة راغبة 
<lb n="16"/>  وذلك في شهر ربيع الأوّل من سنة ثلث وتسعين ومائتين شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="17"/>  شهد إسماعيل بن موسى بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="18"/>  وهرون بن الحسن وكتب شهادته بخطّه على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وذلك في 
<lb n="19"/>  ربيع الأوّل سنة ثلث وتسعين <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>مائتين شهد أحمد بن الحسن بن رزق على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس وكتب بخطّه 
<lb n="20"/>  شهد يوسف بن هرون على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه سنة ثلث وتسعين ومائتين 
<lb n="21"/>  وشهد عبد القاهر بن إسماعيل على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه وذلك في 
<lb n="22"/>  ربيع الأوّل من سنة ثلث وتسعين ومائتين ومحمّد بن بكر وكتب شهادته بخطّه على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بن سويرس بجميع ما 
<lb n="23"/>  في هذا الكتاب وكتب عنه عبد القاهر بن إسماعيل بأمره ومحضره 
<lb n="24"/>  شهد علي بن أحمد على إقرار بلهيوه ابنت سرمادة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه سنة ثلث وتسعين ومائتين 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà mūsīsu bnu ʾabīmaẗa ĭštarà min bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa min sukkāni ṭuṭūna min 
 <lb n="3"/>kūraẗi ăl fayyūmi ĭštarà min hā ṯulṯa ăl ġurfatayni ăllatī waraṯat hā min ʾabī hā sarmādaẗa wa huwa ṯamāniyaẗu ʾashum:in min ʾarbaʿaẗ:in 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ʿišrīna sahm:an maʿa ḥiṣṣati hā mina ăl maḫraǧi wa ṣaṭḥi ăl ġurfatayni ĭštarà ḏālika min hā madḫala hum wa maḫraǧa hum wa sulfa hum 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ʿulwa hum bi dīnārayni maṯāqīla ṭariyy ʿayn:an ḏahab:an qad qabaḍat bilihiyūhu ĭbnatu sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa min mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa 
 <lb n="6"/>hāḏā ăṯ ṯamana tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa bariʾat min hāḏihi ăl ḥiṣṣaẗi ăl maʿrūfaẗi la hā mušāʿ ġayra maqsūm:in maʿa ʾuḫti hā wa maraẗi ʾaḫī hā 
 <lb n="7"/>wa sallamat ḏālika ʾilà mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa fa tasallama hā min hā wa ʾaǧāza hā wa qabaḍa hā wa ṣāra ḏālika māl:an min māli hi wa milk 
 <lb n="8"/>min milki hi ʾin šāʾa bāʿa wa ʾin šāʾa ʿamara wa ʾin šāʾa ʿaṭṭala wa ʾin šāʾa wahaba bāʿat bilihiyūhu ĭbnatu sarmādaẗa hāḏā ăl manzila 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl maḥdūda ăl mawǧūda fī hāḏā ăl kitābi ʿalà šarṭi bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi fa matà mā ĭddaʿat bi daʿw:an ʾaw ʾaḥadi ʾasbābi hā 
 <lb n="10"/>baʿda hāḏā ăl kitābi ʾaw ĭḥtaǧǧū bi ḥuǧǧaẗ:in ʾaw ĭʿtallū bi ʿillaẗ:in fa daʿwà man yaddaʿī fī ḏālika bāṭil:un wa zūr:un wa matà mā kāna min ʿulqaẗ:in 
 <lb n="11"/>ʾaw biyāʿaẗ:in ʾaw ṭāriʾ:in bi dayn:in ʾaw mustaḥiqq:in fa nafāḏu ḏālika wa ḫalāṣu hu ʿalay hā min ḫāliṣi māli hā bāliġ:an mā balaġa kāʾin:an mā kāna 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ḥadda ḥudūd:un hāḏā ăl manzila wa hiya ăl ġurfatayni ăllatī ʿalà ḫizānatayni li mūsīsa ḥaddu humā ăl qibliyyu dāru mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa 
 <lb n="13"/>wa ăl baḥriyyu manzilu mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa wa ăš šarqiyyu manzilu sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa wa ăl ġarbiyyu mūsīsu bnu ʾabīmaẗa šuhida 
 <lb n="14"/>ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay hā wa ʿarafat mā fī hi wa turǧima la hā 
 <lb n="15"/>bi ăl qibṭiyyaẗi ḥarf:an ḥarf:an fa ʾaqarrat bi fahmi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗ:in min badani hā wa ʿaqli hā wa ǧawāzi ʾamri hā ṭāʾiʿaẗ:an ġayra mukrahaẗ:in ṭālibaẗ:an rāġibaẗ:an 
 <lb n="16"/>wa ḏālika fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni šuhida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="17"/>šahida ʾismāʿīlu bnu mūsà bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="18"/>wa hārūnu bnu ăl ḥasani wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ḏālika fī 
 <lb n="19"/>rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida yūsufu bnu hārūna ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="21"/>wa šahida ʿabdu ăl qāhiri bnu ʾismāʿīla ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī 
 <lb n="22"/>rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni wa muḥammadu bnu bakr:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bni sawīrisa bi ǧamīʿi mā 
 <lb n="23"/>fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăl qāhiri bni ʾismāʿīla bi ʾamri hi wa maḥḍari hi 
 <lb n="24"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ʾaḥmada ʿalà ʾiqrāri bilihiyūha ĭbnati sarmādaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		 In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Mūsīs b. Abīme has bought. He bought from Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris of the inhabitants of Ṭuṭūn in
			<lb n="3"/>
		the district of the Fayyūm. He bought from her the third of the two rooms which she inherited from her father Sarmāde, which is eight fraction out of twenty-
			<lb n="4"/>
		four fractions, along with her share of the exit and the roof of the two rooms. He bought that from her, its entry and exit, its lower
			<lb n="5"/>
		and upper part, for two dīnārs of the miṯqāl-weight, freshly coined gold. Biliheu bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris has received this price from Mūsīs b. Abīme
			<lb n="6"/>
		fully and entirely and has released herself of this share, known as belonging to her in shared ownership, not divided, with her sister and the wife of her brother,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and she has handed that over to Mūsīs b. Abīme. So he accepted it from her, took possession of it and received it. And that became a property in his property and an estate
			<lb n="8"/>
		in his estate. If he wants, he may sell it, and if he wants, he may inhabit it, and if he wants, he may leave it empty, and if he wants, he may give it away as a gift. Biliheu bt. Sarmāde has sold this dwelling
			<lb n="9"/>
		delimited and found (?) in this document, according to the islamic sale and its contractual obligation. Whenever she may claim by a claim or one of her reasons
			<lb n="10"/>
		after this document, or they bring forward any argument or excuse, then the claim of him who claims in that will be invalid and void. And whenever there should be an attachment
			<lb n="11"/>
		or ? biyāʿa ? or someone claiming a debt or entitled, then the execution of that and its solution will go to her expense out of her own property, to whatever sum it might amount to and whatever it might be.
			<lb n="12"/>
		Boundaries delimit this dwelling, which is the two rooms which are above two magazines of Mūsīs. Their southern boundary is the house of Mūsīs b. Abīme,
			<lb n="13"/>
		the northern one is the dwelling of Mūsīs b. Abīme, the eastern one is the dwelling of Sarmāde b. Sawīris and the western one is Mūsīs b. Abīme. Witness has been borne
			<lb n="14"/>
		to the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris of everything in this document, after it was read to her, and she took knowledge of what is in it, and it was translated for her
			<lb n="15"/>
		into Coptic, letter by letter, and she acknowledged to have unterstood it, being in good health of her body and mind, and capacle of transacting her affairs, wishing it, not coerced, asking and desiring it.
			<lb n="16"/>
		That (took place) in the month of Rabīʿ I of the year two hundred and ninety-three. That has been witnessed to.
			<lb n="17"/>
		ʾIsmāʿīl b. Mūsā witnessed to everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="18"/>
		And Hārūn b. al-Ḥasan, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting concerning the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris of everything in this document, and that during
			<lb n="19"/>
		Rabīʿ I, in the year two hundred and ninety-three. ʾAḥmad b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris, and he wrote in his handwriting.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Yūsuf b. Hārūn witnessed to the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde of everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting in the year two hundred and ninety-three.
			<lb n="21"/>
		And ʿAbd al-Qāhir b. ʾIsmāʿil witnessed to the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris of everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting. That (took place) during
			<lb n="22"/>
		Rabīʿ I of the year two hundred and ninety-three. And Muḥammad b. Bakr, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting concerning the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde b. Sawīris of everything
			<lb n="23"/>
		in this document, and ʿAbd al-Qāhir b. ʾIsmāʿīl wrote for him on his order and in his presence.
			<lb n="24"/>
		ʿAlī b. ʿAḥmad witnessed to the acknowledgement by Biliheuh bt. Sarmāde of everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting, in the year two hundred and ninety-three.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
