<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1679" xml:id="Fahmi_070" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 07</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_070</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169429</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى موسيس بن أبيمة من شنودة وبقطر ومرقورة وقزمان بني شنودة بن مرقس من 
<lb n="3"/>  سكّان ططون من كورة الفيّوم نخلتين لهما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">مورّفة </lem><rdg resp="APD">مورفة</rdg></app> في بقعة تدعى تهروح مثمرة صفراتين قصبي 
<lb n="4"/>  بدينار واحد مثقال طري قد قبضوا الثّمن تامّا وافيا وبروا من هاتين النّخلتين الموصوفة في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="5"/>  وسلّموا ذلك إلى موسيس بن أبيمة فتسلّمها منهم وصارت مالا من ماله وملك من ملكه إن شا 
<lb n="6"/>  باع وإن شا عمر وإن شا غيّر وإن شا عطّل وإن شا وهب باعوا ذلك لموسيس بن أبيمة على شرط 
<lb n="7"/>  بيع الإسلام وعهدته فمتى ما ادّعى شنودة وبقطر ومرقورة وقزمان بني شنودة بن مرقس بدعوى 
<lb n="8"/>  أو أحد أبنائهم أو احتجّوا بحجّة بعد هذا الكتاب فدعوى من يدّعي في ذلك باطل وزور وعليهما الضّمان والعهدة 
<lb n="9"/>  عن إخوتهم وشي ما كان من علقة أو بياعة أو مستحق أو طارئ بدين فنفاذ ذلك وخلاصه على هولا 
<lb n="10"/>  النّفر المسمّون في هذا الكتاب وهاتين النّخلتين في شرقي نخل موسيس بن أبيمة شهد على إقرار شنودة 
<lb n="11"/>  وبقطر ومرقورة وقزمان بني شنودة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب بعد أن قرئ عليهم وعرفوا ما فيه 
<lb n="12"/>  فأقرّوا بفهمه في صحّة من أبدانهم وعقولهم وجواز أمورهم طائعين غير مكرهين طالبين راغبين وذلك 
<lb n="13"/>  في شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة ثلث وتسعين ومائتين 
<lb n="14"/>  شهد هرون بن موسى <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">الحدّاد</unclear> بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب عنه معاذ بن طاهر بأمره ومحضره 
<lb n="15"/>  وشهد معاذ بن طاهر بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="16"/>  وشهد عبد القاهر بن إسماعيل بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="17"/>  شهد إسماعيل بن موسى بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="18"/>  شهد هبيرة بن هرون بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="19"/>  شهد محمّد بن بكر بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب عنه هبيرة بن هرون بأمره ومحضره 
<lb n="20"/>  شهد يس بن إسماعيل على بقطر وشنودة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà mūsīsu bnu ʾabīmaẗa min šanūdaẗa wa buqṭura wa marqūraẗa wa quzmāna banī šanūdaẗa bni marqusa min 
 <lb n="3"/>sukkāni ṭuṭūna min kūraẗi ăl fayyūmi naḫlatayni la humā mawrifaẗ:un muwarrifaẗ:an fī buqʿaẗ:in tudʿà tahrūḥa muṯmiraẗ:an ṣafrātayni qaṣabiyy 
 <lb n="4"/>bi dīnār:in wāḥid:in miṯqāl:in ṭariyy:in qad qabaḍū ăṯ ṯamana tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa bariʾū min hātayni ăn naḫlatayni ăl mawṣūfaẗi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="5"/>wa sallamū ḏālika ʾilà mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa fa tasallama hā min hum wa ṣārat māl:an min māli hi wa milk min milki hi ʾin šāʾa 
 <lb n="6"/>bāʿa wa ʾin šāʾa ʿamara wa ʾin šāʾa ġayyara wa ʾin šāʾa ʿaṭṭala wa ʾin šāʾa wahaba bāʿū ḏālika li mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa ʿalà šarṭi 
 <lb n="7"/>bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi fa matà mā ĭddaʿà šanūdaẗu wa buqṭuru wa marqūraẗu wa quzmānu banī šanūdaẗa bni marqusa bi daʿw:an 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾaw ʾaḥadu ʾabnāʾi him ʾaw ĭḥtaǧǧū bi ḥuǧǧaẗ:in baʿda hāḏā ăl kitābi fa daʿwà man yaddaʿī fī ḏālika bāṭil:un wa zūr:un wa ʿalay humā ăḍ ḍamānu wa ăl ʿuhdaẗu 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿan ʾiḫwati him wa šayʾ:un mā kāna min ʿulqaẗ:in ʾaw biyāʿaẗ:in ʾaw mustaḥiqq:in ʾaw ṭāriʾ:in bi dayn:in fa nafāḏu ḏālika wa ḫalāṣu hu ʿalà hāʾulāʾi 
 <lb n="10"/>ăn nafari ăl musammawna fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa hātayni ăn naḫlatayni fī šarqiyyi naḫli mūsīsa bni ʾabīmaẗa šuhida ʿalà ʾiqrāri šanūdaẗa 
 <lb n="11"/>wa buqṭura wa marqūraẗa wa quzmāna banī šanūdaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay him wa ʿarafū mā fī hi 
 <lb n="12"/>fa ʾaqarrū bi fahmi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗ:in min ʾabdāni him wa ʿuqūli him wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri him ṭāʾiʿīna ġayra mukrahīna ṭālibīna rāġibīna wa ḏālika 
 <lb n="13"/>fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa tisʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="14"/>šahida hārūnu bnu mūsà ăl ḥaddādu bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba ʿan hu muʿāḏu bnu ṭāhir:in bi ʾamri hi wa maḥḍari hi 
 <lb n="15"/>wa šahida muʿāḏu bnu ṭāhir:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="16"/>wa šahida ʿabdu ăl qāhiri bni ʾismāʿīla bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="17"/>šahida ʾismāʿīlu bnu mūsà bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="18"/>šahida hubayraẗu bnu hārūna bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida muḥammadu bnu bakr:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba ʿan hu hubayraẗu bnu hārūna bi ʾamri hi wa maḥḍari hi 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida ys bnu ʾismāʿīla ʿalà buqṭura wa šanūdaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		 In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Mūsīs b. Abīme has bought from Šanūde, Buqṭur, Marqūre and Quzmān, the sons of Šanūde b. Marqus of
			<lb n="3"/>
		the inhabitants of Ṭuṭūn in the district of the Fayyūm: (he bought) two date-palms belonging to (the two eldest brothers), extending their shade on a lot of land called Tahrūḥ, carrying fruit, yellow, ?qaṣabī?, 
		the inhabitants of Ṭuṭūn in the district of the Fayyūm: (he bought) two date-palms having a ?mawfira? on a lot of land called Tahrūḥ, carrying fruit, yellow, ?qaṣabī? , 
			<lb n="4"/>
		for one dīnār of the miṯqāl-weight, freshly coined. They have received the price fully and entirely, and delivered themselves of these date-palms described in this document,
			<lb n="5"/>
		and they handed that over to Mūsīs b. Abīme, so that he received them [sic], and they became a property in his property and an estate in his estate. If he wants,
			<lb n="6"/>
		he may sell it, inhabit it, change or demolish it or give it as a gift. They sold that according to the condition
			<lb n="7"/>
		the islamic sale and its contractual obligation. Whenever Šanūde, Buqṭur, Marqūre and Quzmān, the sons of Šanūde b. Marqus, should come up with a claim
			<lb n="8"/>
		- or any of their children - or an argument after (the writing of) this document, then the claim of him who claims shall be invalid and void. And the warranty and the contractual obligation lies upon the two of them
			<lb n="9"/>
		towards their brothers (plural!), and anything which might come by way of an impediment or biyāʿa (?), or someone entitled or claiming a debt, then the execution of that and its indemnification will be at the expense of these
			<lb n="10"/>
		people named in this document. These two palms are east of Mūsīs b. Abīme&#039;s palms. Witness has been borne to the acknowledgement by Šanūde
			<lb n="11"/>
		Buqṭur, Marqūre and Quzmān, the sons of Šanūde, of everything in this document, after it was read to them, and they took knowledge of it,
			<lb n="12"/>
		and they acknowledged to have understood it, being in good health of their body and mind and capable of transacting their affairs, voluntarily, not coerced, requesting and desiring it. This (took place)
			<lb n="13"/>
		in the month of Rabīʿ I, in the year two hundred and seventy-three
			<lb n="14"/>
		Hārūn b. Mūsā witnessed to everything in this document, and Muʿāḏ b. Ṭāhir wrote for him on his order and in his presence.
			<lb n="15"/>
		And Muʿāḏ b. Ṭāhir witnessed to everything in this document and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="16"/>
		And ʿAbd al-Qāhir b. Ismāʿīl witnessed to everything in this document and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="17"/>
		ʾIsmāʿīl b. Mūsā witnessed to everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="18"/>
		Hubayra b. Hārūn witnessed to everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="19"/>
		Muḥammad b. Bakr witnessed to everything in this document, and Hubayra b. Hārūn wrote for him on his order and in his presence.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Yāsīn b. ʾIsmāʿīl witnessed to (the acknowledgement by) Buqṭur and Šanūda concerning everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
