<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1704" xml:id="Fahmi_100" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 10 (= P.Vente 08)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_100</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169454</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  وما توفيقي إلّا باللّه عليه توكّلت وإليه أنيب الحمد للّه أسأله رحمة من عنده وتوفيقنا 
<lb n="2"/>  ثبتت 
<lb n="3"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم اشترتي بمصر 
<lb n="4"/>  فاطمة ابنة نصر المبجّج من أحمد بن عمران الطّحّان 
<lb n="5"/>  ساكن بالموقف بالطّحّانين جارية في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بيته </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">يديه</rdg></app> مقرّة له 
<lb n="6"/>  بالملك تدعا توفيق <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">قدمته </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">قرمية</rdg></app> سودا إلى الحمرة معتدلة 
<lb n="7"/>  القامة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">كثيفتـها </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">كشفاء</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نافرة </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">ناتئة</rdg></app> الجبهة بلجا عينا فطسا غليظة 
<lb n="8"/>  الشّفتين مثقوبة السّفلى منهما قصيرة الذّقن منكسر 
<lb n="9"/>  الثّمن خمسة وعشرين دينارا معزّيّة الجعل منها تقابضا 
<lb n="10"/>  وتفرّقا عن تراض منهما بيع الإسلام وعهدته <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وإمرته </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">طهارة</rdg></app> 
<lb n="11"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وسلامه </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">وسلامة</rdg></app> برئ البائع من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">سمادة </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">سماجة</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يديها </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">يديها</rdg></app> ورجليها وشيب 
<lb n="12"/>  رأسها وقلع أضراسها وذلك يوم الخميس لثمان 
<lb n="13"/>  خلون من شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تسع </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">سبع</rdg></app> وستّين وثلثمائة 
<lb n="14"/>  شهد بذلك أحمد بن سعد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">المعبّي </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">المعني </rdg><rdg resp="Rāġib">المعبّي </rdg><rdg resp="Rāġib">المعنّى</rdg></app> وعلي بن الغريب 
<lb n="15"/>  وميمون بن نصر المودپ وموسى بن إسحق الجوهري 
<lb n="16"/>  وحجّاج بن أحمد وخلف بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حلفون </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">حلفون</rdg></app> وعلي بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الجوهري </lem><rdg resp="Rāġib">بشر</rdg></app> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>wa mā tawfīq ī ʾillā bi ăl lāhi ʿalay hi tawakkaltu wa ʾilay hi ʾunību ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ʾasʾalu hu raḥmaẗ:an min ʿinda hu wa tawfīqa nā 
 <lb n="2"/>ṯabatat 
 <lb n="3"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi ĭštaratī bi miṣra 
 <lb n="4"/>fāṭimaẗu ĭbnaẗu naṣr:ini ăl mubaǧǧiǧi min ʾaḥmada bni ʿimrāna ăṭ ṭaḥḥāni 
 <lb n="5"/>sākin:in bi ăl mawqifi bi ăṭ ṭaḥḥānīna ǧāriyaẗ:an fī bayti yaday hi muqarraẗ:an la hu 
 <lb n="6"/>bi ăl milki tudʿā tawfīqa qdmt qaramiyyaẗan h sawdāʾa ʾilà ăl ḥumraẗi muʿtadilaẗa 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl qāmaẗi kaṯīfata kašfāʾa hā nāfiraẗa nātiʾaẗa ăl ǧabhaẗi balǧāʾa ʿaynāʾa faṭsāʾa ġalīẓaẗa 
 <lb n="8"/>ăš šafatayni maṯqūbaẗa ăs suflà min humā qaṣīraẗ:an ăḏ ḏaqnu munkasir:un 
 <lb n="9"/>ăṯ ṯamanu ḫamsaẗ:un wa ʿišrīna dīnār:an muʿizziyyaẗ:an ăl ǧuʿlu min hā taqābaḍā 
 <lb n="10"/>wa tafarraqā ʿan tarāḍ:in min humā bayʿa ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdata hu wa ṭahāraẗun ʾimrata hu 
 <lb n="11"/>wa salāma salāmaẗun hu bariʾa ăl bāʾiʿu min samādaẗi samāǧaẗi badani yaday hā wa riǧlay hā wa šaybi 
 <lb n="12"/>raʾsi hā wa qulaʿi ʾaḍrāsi hā wa ḏālika yawma ăl ḫamīsi li ṯamān:in 
 <lb n="13"/>ḫalawna min šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa tisʿ:in sabʿ:in wa sittīna wa ṯalāṯi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="14"/>šahida bi ḏālika ʾaḥmadu bnu saʿd:in ăl maʿnī muʿabbī muʿannà muġannī wa ʿaliyyu bnu ăl ġarībi 
 <lb n="15"/>wa maymūnu bnu naṣr:in ăl muʾaddibu wa mūsà bnu ʾisḥāqa ăl ǧawhariyyu 
 <lb n="16"/>wa ḥaǧǧāǧu bnu ʾaḥmada wa ḫalafu bnu ḥalfūna ḫalqūna wa ʿaliyyu bnu ăl bišri ǧawhariyyi ø ăṣ ṣafadiyyi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		And my success is &lt;only&gt; with God, in Him do I trust and to Him shall I return. Praise be to God. I ask him for mercy from his side, and our success.
		Mon assistance n’est qu’en Dieu. Sur Lui je m’appuie et vers Lui je reviens repentant. Louange à Dieu! Je Lui demande miséricorde de Sa part et assistance.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Enregistré.
		It has been confirmed.
			<lb n="3"/>
		Au nom de Dieu, clément et miséricordieux!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate and Merciful. She bought in Egypt,
			<lb n="4"/>
		Fāṭima bt. Naṣr, the barber-surgeon (?), from ʾAḥmad b. ʿImrān, the miller,
		Fāṭima ibnat Naṣr al-Munǧiḥ a acheté à Miṣr d’Aḥmad b. ʿImrān le meunieur,
			<lb n="5"/>
		habitant du Mawqif au (quartier des) meuniers, une esclave qui se trouve en sa possession et reconnaît être
		living in the place (?), with the millers, (she bought) a female slave in his house, acknowledged to belong to him
			<lb n="6"/>
		as his property, who is called Tawfīq [...], black to red, straight
		sa propriété, appelée Tawfīq. C’est une Garamente noire tirant sur le rouge et
			<lb n="7"/>
		and heavy of build, having a sloping forehead, bright and large eyes, flat-nosed, with thick
		de taille moyenne. Elle a les cheveux du toupet frisés, un front proéminent, des sourcils écartés, de grands yeux, un nez camard,
			<lb n="8"/>
		des lèvres épaisses, dont l’inférieure est percée, un menton court et brisé.
		lips, the upper of them pierced, short, and (her) chin is cleft.
			<lb n="9"/>
		Le prix est de vingt-cinq dinars d’al-Muʿizz, rémunération forfaitaire comprise. Les parties ont pris possesion réciproquement (l’une du prix, l’autre de l’esclave)
		The price is twenty-five Muʿizzī Dīnārs, the reward for her (?). The received from each other (the money and the slave respectively)
			<lb n="10"/>
		and separated from each other in mutual satisfaction. (They transacted this?) as an islamic sale with its contractual obligation, its authority
		et se sont séparées sur consentement mutuel. Vente (conclue suivant la loi) de l’ilsam et sa garantie. (L’esclave) est en bonne santé
			<lb n="11"/>
		and its security. The seller became free from the swelling of her body and feet, the white-hairedness
		et exemple (de tromperie). Le vendeur a libéré sa responsabilité de la laideur de ses mains et de ses pieds, de ses cheveux blancs
			<lb n="12"/>
		et de ses dents arrachées. Et cela le jour du jeudi huit
		of hear head and the putridity of her molar teeth. And this (took place) on Thursday, eight (nights)
			<lb n="13"/>
		du mois de rabīʿ I l’ammée trois cent soixante-sept.
		having past of the month of Rabīʿ I, in the year nine-and-sixty and three hundred.
			<lb n="14"/>
		Ont témoigné de cela Aḥmad b. Saʿd al-Maʿnī, ʿAlī b. al-Ġarīb,
		Witnessed by ʾAḥmad b. Saʿd the singer, ʿAlī son of the stranger,
			<lb n="15"/>
		Maymūn b. Naṣr le maître d’école, Mūsā b. Isḥāq le joaillier,
		Maymūn b. Naṣr the educator, Mūsā b. ʾIsḥaq, the jewel-trader,
			<lb n="16"/>
		Ḥaǧǧāǧ b. Aḥmad, Ḫalaf b. Ḥalfūn et ʿAlī b. Bišr al-Ṣafadī.
		Ḥaǧǧāǧ b. ʾAḥmad, Ḫalaf b. Ḫalqūn and ʿAlī son of the jewel-trader.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
