<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1635" xml:id="Fahmi_050" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 05</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_050</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169390</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترت برسيوه ابنت يحنّس بن بمون بن بليط من سكّان 
<lb n="3"/>  ططون من كورة الفيّوم اشترت من مطرونة ابنت أبنولة وهي 
<lb n="4"/>  زوجة بمون بن بليط اشترت منها مير<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ا</supplied>ثها من زوجها بمون 
<lb n="5"/>  بن بليط وهو الرّبع من جميع ما يملكه بمون بن بليط من منزل أو دار 
<lb n="6"/>  أو عقار أو دابّة أو ماشية أو ثوب أو حمير أو نحاس أو شي ممّا خلقه 
<lb n="7"/>  اللّه وبرأه ممّا ورثته مطرونة من مال زوجها بمون بن بليط باثنين وعشرين 
<lb n="8"/>  دينرا مثاقيل طريّة وازن بالجديد وقد قبضت مطرونة ابنت أبنولة 
<lb n="9"/>  زوجة بمون بن بليط الثّمن تامّا وافيا وبرئت من كل شي ورثته من مال 
<lb n="10"/>  زوجها بمون بن بليط وسلّمت ذلك إلى برسيوه ابنت يحنّس بن بمون بن بليط 
<lb n="11"/>  وصار ذلك مالا من مالها وملك من ملكها إن شاپ برسيوه باعت وإن 
<lb n="12"/>  شاپ عمرت وإن شاپ عطّلت باعت ذلك كلّه طائعة غير مكرهة على شرط بيع الإسلام 
<lb n="13"/>  وعهدته ولم يبق لمطرونة ابنت أبنولة في هذا الرّبع المنشور في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="14"/>  قليل ولا كثير وكلّما ادّعت مطرونة ابنت أبنولة بعد هذا الكتاب من كل دعوى 
<lb n="15"/>  تدّعي به فهو باطل وزور وقد افترقا عن تراض منهما بعد أن قبضت مطرونة الثّمن 
<lb n="16"/>  تامّا وافيا وهو اثنين وعشرين دينرا من برسيوه ابنت يحنّس بن بمون بن بليط 
<lb n="17"/>  ورضي كل واحد منهما بما صار عليه بعد أن قبضت برسيوه ابنت يحنّس هذا الرّبع 
<lb n="18"/>  وعرفته شي شي ووقفت على المنازل والدّار والنّخل والحمير والثّياب والنّحاس 
<lb n="19"/>  والبقر والنّعم والكباش وكل رأس بقي من البقر وربع الحمارة وخمسة أروس 
<lb n="20"/>  من الغنم والكباش صغار وكبار وربع النّورج الحديد ومن النّحاس طشت وبور وربع 
<lb n="21"/>  المحرث ومن الثّياب سپپپه صوف وپصف الڤطپپه الاررق وسراح احمر وكپپه 
<lb n="22"/>  عسلي وثلثة فرش ووسادتين صوف ووسادتين كتّان ومن المنازل والدّور 
<lb n="23"/>  المنزل الكبير والدّار الّذي بلصق هذا المنزل من القبلي بحدّها وحدودها وأرضها وسمائها 
<lb n="24"/>  وأسوارهم وحيشنهم وحيطانهم ومدخلهم ومخرجهم فصار ربع هذا المنزل والدّار 
<lb n="25"/>  المحدود في هذا الكتاب على جميع ما سمّي ووصف في هذا الكتاب باثنين وعشرين دينرا 
<lb n="26"/>  ملك برسيوه ابنت يحنّس بن بمون بن بليط وحد حدود هذا المنزل والدّار حدّها القبلي 
<lb n="27"/>  الصّحرا والبحري منزل إسحق بن قلمون والشّرقي منزل ورثة بني مينا بن موسى والغربي منزل 
<lb n="28"/>  موسيس بن هميسة شهد على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة زوجة بمون بن بليط بجميع ما 
<lb n="29"/>  في هذا الكتاب من أوّله إلى آخره بعد أن قرئ عليها وعرفته وأقرّت بفهمها في 
<lb n="30"/>  صحّة من بدنها وعقلها وثبات أمرها طائعة غير مكرهة ولا محبرة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">طالبه </lem><rdg resp="LS">طالبة</rdg></app> راغبة 
<lb n="31"/>  وذلك في مستهل شعبان سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="32"/>  شهد داود بن الحسن بن رزق على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="33"/>  شهد الحسن بن رزق على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="34"/>  وكتب عنه أحمد بأمره ومحضره سنة اثنين وسبعين 
<lb n="35"/>  شهد أحمد بن الحسن بن رزق على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="36"/>  وكتب شهادته بخطّه سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين 
<lb n="37"/>  شهد طاهر بن الحسن بن رزق بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="38"/>  وكتب شهادته بخطّه وذلك في مستهل شعبان سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين 
<lb n="39"/>  شهد يعقوب بن الحسن بن رزق على إقرار مطرونة بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="40"/>  شهد إسحق بن سليمن بن رزق على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة بجميع ما في 
<lb n="41"/>  هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه وذلك في مستهل شعبان 
<lb n="42"/>  سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين 
<lb n="43"/>  شهد عيسى بن إسحق بن سليمن على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة 
<lb n="44"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه وذلك في شعبان 
<lb n="45"/>  سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين 
<lb n="46"/>  شهد محمّد بن علي على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة زوجة بمون بن بليط وبرسيوه 
<lb n="47"/>  ابنت يحنّس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وذلك في شعبان سنة اثنين وسبعين ومائتين 
<lb n="48"/>  وشهد مرزوق بن ميمون على إقرار مطرونة ابنت أبنولة وبرسيوه ابنت يحنّس 
<lb n="49"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب عنهما بخطّه بأمرهما ومحضرهما وذلك في شعبان سنة 
<lb n="50"/>  اثنين وسبعين ومائتين شهد سليمن بن يعقوب 
<lb n="51"/>  بـجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarat birsiyūhu ĭbnatu yuḥannisa bni bamūna bni balīṭa min sukkāni 
 <lb n="3"/>ṭuṭūna min kūraẗi ăl fayyūmi ĭštarat min maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa wa hiya 
 <lb n="4"/>zawǧaẗu bamūna bni balīṭa ĭštarat min hā mīrāṯa hā min zawǧi hā bamūna 
 <lb n="5"/>bni balīṭa wa huwa ăr rubʿu min ǧamīʿi mā yamliku hu bamūnu bnu balīṭa min manzil:in ʾaw dār:in 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾaw ʿaqār:in ʾaw dābbaẗ:in ʾaw māšiyaẗ:in ʾaw ṯawb:in ʾaw ḥamīr:in ʾaw nuḥās:in ʾaw šayʾ:in mimmā ḫalaqa hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl lāhu wa baraʾa hu mimmā waraṯat hu maṭrūnaẗu min māli zawǧi hā bamūna bni balīṭa bi ĭṯnayni wa ʿišrīna 
 <lb n="8"/>dīnār:an maṯāqīla ṭariyyaẗ:an wāzin bi ăl ǧadīdi wa qad qabaḍat maṭrūnaẗu ĭbnatu ʾabnūlaẗa 
 <lb n="9"/>zawǧaẗu bamūna bni balīṭa ăṯ ṯamana tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa bariʾat min kulli šayʾ:in waraṯat hu min māli 
 <lb n="10"/>zawǧi hā bamūna bni balīṭa wa sallamat ḏālika ʾilà birsiyūha ĭbnati yuḥannisa bni bamūna bni balīṭa 
 <lb n="11"/>wa ṣāra ḏālika māl:an min māli hā wa milk min milki hā ʾin šāʾat birsiyūhu bāʿat wa ʾin 
 <lb n="12"/>šāʾat ʿamarat wa ʾin šāʾat ʿaṭṭalat bāʿat ḏālika kulla hu ṭāʾiʿaẗ:an ġayra mukrahaẗ:in ʿalà šarṭi bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi 
 <lb n="13"/>wa ʿuhdati hi wa lam yabqa li maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa fī hāḏā ăr rubʿi ăl manšūri fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="14"/>qalīl:un wa lā kaṯīr:un wa kullu mā ĭddaʿat maṭrūnaẗu ĭbnatu ʾabnūlaẗa baʿda hāḏā ăl kitābi min kulli daʿw:an 
 <lb n="15"/>taddaʿī bi hi fa huwa bāṭil:un wa zūr:un wa qad ĭftaraqā ʿan tarāḍ:in min humā baʿda ʾan qabaḍat maṭrūnaẗu ăṯ ṯamana 
 <lb n="16"/>tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa huwa ĭṯnayni wa ʿišrīna dīnār:an min birsiyūha ĭbnati yuḥannisa bni bamūna bni balīṭa 
 <lb n="17"/>wa raḍiya kullu wāḥid:in min humā bi mā ṣāra ʿalay hi baʿda ʾan qabaḍat birsiyūhu ĭbnatu yuḥannisa hāḏā ăr rubʿa 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʿarafat hu šayʾ šayʾ wa waqafat ʿalà ăl manāzili wa ăd dāri wa ăn naḫli wa ăl ḥamīri wa ăṯ ṯiyābi wa ăn nuḥāsi 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ăl baqari wa ăn naʿami wa ăl kibāši wa kulli raʾs:in baqiya min ăl baqari wa rubʿi ăl ḥimāraẗi wa ḫamsaẗi ʾarʾus:in 
 <lb n="20"/>mina ăl ġanami wa ăl kibāši ṣiġār:in wa kibār:in wa rubʿi ăn nawraǧi ăl ḥadīdi wa mina ăn nuḥāsi ṭašt:in wa būr:in wa rubʿi 
 <lb n="21"/>ăl miḥrāṯi wa mina ăṯ ṯiyābi ʿalà sabaniyyaẗi ṣūf:in wa niṣfi ăl quṭniyyaẗi ăl ʾazraqi wa sirāǧ:in ʾaḥmara wa kanabaẗ:in 
 <lb n="22"/>ʿasaliyy:in wa ṯalāṯaẗi furuš:in wa wisādatayni ṣūf:in wa wisādatayni kattān:in wa mina ăl manāzili wa ăd dūri 
 <lb n="23"/>ăl manzili ăl kabīri wa ăd dāri ăllaḏī bi liṣqi hāḏā ăl manzili mina ăl qibliyyi bi ḥaddi hā wa ḥudūdi hā wa ʾarḍi hā wa samāʾi hā 
 <lb n="24"/>wa ʾaswāri him wa ḥīšāni him wa ḥīṭāni him wa madḫali him wa maḫraǧi him fa ṣāra rubʿu hāḏā ăl manzili wa ăd dāri 
 <lb n="25"/>ăl maḥdūdi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi ʿalà ǧamīʿi mā summiya wa wuṣifa fī hāḏā ăl kitābi bi ĭṯnayni wa ʿišrīna dīnār:an 
 <lb n="26"/>milka birsiyūha ĭbnati yuḥannisa bni bamūna bni balīṭa wa ḥadda ḥudūd:un hāḏā ăl manzila wa ăd dāra ḥaddu hā ăl qibliyyu 
 <lb n="27"/>ăṣ ṣaḥrāʾu wa ăl baḥriyyu manzilu ʾisḥāqa bni qalamūna wa ăš šarqiyyu manzilu waraṯaẗi banī mīnā bni mūsà wa ăl ġarbiyyu manzilu 
 <lb n="28"/>mūsīsa bni humīsaẗa šuhida ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa zawǧaẗi bamūna bni balīṭa bi ǧamīʿi mā 
 <lb n="29"/>fī hāḏā ăl kitābi min ʾawwali hi ʾilà ʾāḫiri hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay hā wa ʿarafat hu wa ʾaqarrat bi fahmi hā fī 
 <lb n="30"/>ṣiḥḥaẗ:in min badani hā wa ʿaqli hā wa ṯabāti ʾamri hā ṭāʾiʿaẗ:an ġayra mukrahaẗ:in wa lā muǧbaraẗ:in ăl battaẗ:an ṭālibaẗ:an rāġibaẗ:an 
 <lb n="31"/>wa ḏālika fī mustahalli šaʿbāni sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni šuhida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="32"/>šahida dāwidu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="33"/>šahida ăl ḥasanu bnu rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="34"/>wa kataba ʿan hu ʾaḥmadu bi ʾamri hi wa maḥḍari hi sanaẗa ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna 
 <lb n="35"/>šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="36"/>wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi sanaẗa ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="37"/>šahida ṭāhiru bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="38"/>wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī mustahalli šaʿbāni sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="39"/>šahida yaʿqūbu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="40"/>šahida ʾisḥāqu bnu sulaymāna bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="41"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī mustahalli šaʿbāni 
 <lb n="42"/>sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="43"/>šahida ʿīsà bnu ʾisḥāqa bni sulaymāna ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa 
 <lb n="44"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī šaʿbāni 
 <lb n="45"/>sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="46"/>šahida muḥammadu bnu ʿaliyy:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa zawǧaẗi bamūna bni balīṭa wa birsiyūha 
 <lb n="47"/>ĭbnati yuḥannisa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ḏālika fī šaʿbāni sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="48"/>wa šahida marzūqu bnu maymūn:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa wa birsiyūha ĭbnati yuḥannisa 
 <lb n="49"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba ʿan humā bi ḫaṭṭi hi bi ʾamri himā wa maḥḍari himā wa ḏālika fī šaʿbāni sanaẗi 
 <lb n="50"/>ĭṯnayni wa sabʿīna wa miʾatayni šahida sulaymānu bnu yaʿqūba 
 <lb n="51"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		 In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is, what ? Perseuh ? bt. Yuḥannis b. Bamūn b. Balīṭ, of the inhabitants
			<lb n="3"/>
		of Ṭuṭūn in the district of the Fayyūm. She bought from Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle, who is
			<lb n="4"/>
		the wife of Bamūn b. Balīṭ. She bought from her her inheritance from her husband Bamūn
			<lb n="5"/>
		b. Balīṭ, which is a quarter of everything Bamūn b. Balīṭ owned of a dwelling, a house,
			<lb n="6"/>
		an estate, a riding animal, a piece of cattle, a piece of cloth, donkeys or copper, or anything of what God
			<lb n="7"/>
		created and brought into being of what Maṭrūna inherited from the property of her husband Bamūn b. Balīṭ, for twenty-two
			<lb n="8"/>
		dīnār miṯqāl, new, full-weight according to the new (standard). Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle, wife of Bamūn b. Balīṭ,
			<lb n="9"/>
		has received the price fully and entirely, and has releases herself of everything she inherited of the property
			<lb n="10"/>
		of her husband Bamūn b. Balīṭ, and handed that over to ? Perseu ? bt. Yuḥannis b. Bamūn b. Balīṭ,
			<lb n="11"/>
		and that (the inheritance) became a property in her property and an estate in her estate. If ? Perseuh ? wants, she may sell it, and if
			<lb n="12"/>
		she wants, she may inhabit it, and if she wants, she may leave it empty. She (Maṭrūna) sold all that voluntarily, not coerced, according to the condition of the islamic sale
			<lb n="13"/>
		and its contract. Nothing has remained to Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle in this quarter published in this writing
			<lb n="14"/>
		little or much. Anything which Maṭrūna bt. Abnūla might claim after this writing by way of any claim
			<lb n="15"/>
		she might claim is invalid and void. The two have separated in mutual satisfaction about each other, after Maṭrūna received the price
			<lb n="16"/>
		fully and entirely, it being twenty-two dīnār, from ? Perseuh ? b. Yuḥannis b. Bamūn b. Balīṭ
			<lb n="17"/>
		and each of them was content about what became his obligation, after ? Perseuh ? bt. Yuḥannis received this quarter
			<lb n="18"/>
		and took knowledge of it, one thing after the other, and became instructed about the dwellings and the house and the palm-trees, the donkeys, the clothes, the copper,
			<lb n="19"/>
		the cattle, the grazing livestock, the rams and every head which remains of the cattle, and a quarter of the she-donkey, five heads of the sheep and the rams, the small and the big ones, and a quarter of the iron threshing sledge, and of the copper a kneading bowl, and fallow land (?), and a quarter
			<lb n="21"/>
		of the plow, and of the clothes a wollen sash and half of the blue cotton (items), and a red lamp and ? a honey-coloured
			<lb n="22"/>
		canapé ?, three matresses, two wollen pillows and two linnen pillows, and of the dwellings and the houses
			<lb n="23"/>
		the big dwelling and the house attached south of this dwelling, with their limit and their boundaries, their ground and their skye,
			<lb n="24"/>
		their fences, enclosures and walls, their entry and exit. So the quarter of this dwelling and house
			<lb n="25"/>
		defined in this writing, in addition to everything which was named and described in this writing, became, for twenty-two dīnār,
			<lb n="26"/>
		property of ? Perseuh ? bt. Yuḥanis b. Bamūn b. Balīṭ. Boundaries enclose this dwelling and the house: Their southern boundary
			<lb n="27"/>
		is the desert, the northern one is the dwelling of Isḥāq b. ? Qalamūn ?, the eastern one is the dwelling of the heirs of the sons of the Banī Mīnā b. Mūsà, and the western one is the dwelling
			<lb n="28"/>
		of Mūsīs b. Homīse. The acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle, wife of Bamūn b. Balīṭ, of everything contained
			<lb n="29"/>
		in this writing from its beginning to its end has been witnessed to, after it was read to her, and she took knowledge of it and acknowledged her understanding, being in
			<lb n="30"/>
		good health of her body and mind and ? stability of conducting her affairs ?, voluntarily, not coerced nor under constraint, demanding and desiring it.
			<lb n="31"/>
		That (took place) in the beginning of Šaʿbān of the year two hundred and seventy-two. That has been witnessed to.
			<lb n="32"/>
		Dāwid b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle of everything in this document //
			<lb n="33"/>
		Al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle of everything in this document
			<lb n="34"/>
		and ʾAḥmad wrote for him on his order and in his presence in the year seventy-two.
			<lb n="35"/>
		ʾAḥmad b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle of everything in this document,
			<lb n="36"/>
		and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting in the year two hundred and seventy-two.
			<lb n="37"/>
		Ṭāhir b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to everything in this document,
			<lb n="38"/>
		and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting. That (took place) in the beginning of Šaʿbān of the year two hundred and seventy-two.
			<lb n="39"/>
		Yaʿqūb b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna of everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="40"/>
		ʾIsḥāq b. Sulaymān b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle to everything in
			<lb n="41"/>
		this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting. That (took place) in the beginning of Šaʿbān
			<lb n="42"/>
		of the year two hundred and seventy-two.
			<lb n="43"/>
		ʿIsà b. ʾIsḥāq b. Sulaymān witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle
			<lb n="44"/>
		of everything in this document, and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting. That (took place) in Šaʿbān
			<lb n="45"/>
		of the year two hundred and seventy-two.
			<lb n="46"/>
		Muḥammad b. ʿAlī witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle, wife of Bamūn b. Balīṭ, and by ? Perseuh ?
			<lb n="47"/>
		bt. Yuḥannis, of everything in this document. That (took place) in Šaʿbān of the year two hundred and seventy-two.
			<lb n="48"/>
		Marzūq b. Maymūn witnessed to the acknowledgement by Maṭrūna bt. Abnūle and by ? Perseuh ? bt. Yuḥannis
			<lb n="49"/>
		of everything in this document, and he wrote for them with his handwriting on their order and in their presence. That in Šaʿbān of the year
			<lb n="50"/>
		two hundred and seventy-two. Sulaymān b. Yaʿqūb witnessed
			<lb n="51"/>
		to everything in this document.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
