<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1612" xml:id="Fahmi_010" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 01</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_010</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169368</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى عبد اللّه بن بطرس ولقبه أنتناس بن بطرس الإدفوي من النّضر بن عبد اللّه الزّيّات 
<lb n="3"/>  وهو صحيح العقل والبدن لا علّة به من مرض ولا غيره في ذي القعدة سنة ثمان وثلثين ومائتين اشترى منه 
<lb n="4"/>  جماعة طباق المنزل الّذي فيه معصرة الزّيت في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حارة </lem><rdg resp="LS. The press that the heirs of Bišande will sell in P.FahmīTaʿāqud 2 	">حيازة</rdg></app> بشنده الشّمّاس في شرق إدفوا 
<lb n="5"/>  وما فوقه إلى الهوى وهو علو المعصرة الّتي حدّها القبلي منزل يونس وموسى ابني بقطر الشّمّاس وحدّه البحري 
<lb n="6"/>  الطّريق وحدّه الشّرقي منزل يونة ابنت يحنّس والعرصة المعروفة ببرقس وحدّه الغربي منزل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لبسنسة </lem><rdg resp="Quoted thus in the commentary. One of the two must be a printing mistake.">لبسسنة </rdg><rdg resp="This name is well attested “LS÷ N.B. for males” , but an additional hook is very visible. “Fahmi”">لسسنّة</rdg></app> 
<lb n="7"/>  ابنت شانوده بينهما الطّريق اشترى عبد اللّه بن بطرس المعروف بأنتناس من النّضر بن عبد اللّه 
<lb n="8"/>  الزّيّات جماعة الغرف الّتي هي علوا هذه المعصرة المحدودة في هذا الكتاب وما فوقها إلى الهوى 
<lb n="9"/>  بجميع مرافقها ومرتفعها وكل سطوحها وسقفها وكل قليل وكثير هو لعلوّا هذه المعصرة 
<lb n="10"/>  بستّة دنانير عينا ذهبا وزنا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بالمثاڤيل </lem><rdg resp="LS">بالمثاڤيل</rdg></app> الجديد قد نقد عبد اللّه بن بطرس النّضر بن عبد اللّه الزّيّات 
<lb n="11"/>  هذه السّتّة الدّنانير المثاقيل ثمنا لعلوا هذه المعصرة وما فوقها إلى الهوى ما خلى المسلك 
<lb n="12"/>  إلى هذه الغرف المبيعة في هذا الكتاب فإنّه لا حق لعبد اللّه بن بطرس في المسلك إلى علوا هذه المعصرة <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ولا</supplied> 
<lb n="13"/>  من شي من سفله ولا من باب المعصرة وسلّم النّضر بن عبد اللّه لعبد اللّه بن بطرس جماعة علوا 
<lb n="14"/>  ما أحاطت به حدود هذه المعصرة بالثّمن المسمّا في هذا الكتاب وهو ستّة دنانير مثاقيل 
<lb n="15"/>  وقبض عبد اللّه المعروف بأنتاناس طباق هذه المعصرة إلى الهوى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وجازه </lem><rdg resp="LS">وحازه</rdg></app> وملكه وجرى حكمـه فيه 
<lb n="16"/>  وصار مالا من ماله فلم يبق للنّضر بن عبد اللّه في علوا هذا المنزل الّذي فيه هذه المعصرة ولا في شي منه 
<lb n="17"/>  قليل ولا كثير على الوجوه كلّها والأسباب فما أدرك عبد اللّه بن بطرس فيما اشترى 
<lb n="18"/>  من النّضر بن عبد اللّه من دعوى أو طلبة أو خصومة أو <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بياعة </lem><rdg resp="LS. cf. P.Fay.Monast. 1.21">تباعة</rdg></app> أو درك لأحد من النّاس فعلى النّضر بن عبد اللّه 
<lb n="19"/>  نفاذ ذلك وخلاصه وتصحيحه لعبد اللّه بن بطرس المعروف بأنتاناس على بيع الإسلام وعهدته 
<lb n="20"/>  شهد على ذلك عبد الأعلى بن معوية بن عبد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الآخر </lem><rdg resp="LS">الأعلى</rdg></app> وهو كاتب الكتاب في ذي القعدة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ستّة </lem><rdg resp="LS">سنة</rdg></app> ثمان وثلثين ومائتين 
<lb n="21"/>  وموسى بن عيسى بن عروة وكتب شهادته 
<lb n="22"/>  شهد اليسع بن عبد الوهّاب على النّضر بن عبد اللّه الزّيّات بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب في ذي 
<lb n="23"/>  القعدة من سنة ثما<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ن</supplied> وثلثين ومائتين 
<lb n="24"/>  وعبد الكريم بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="25"/>  وشهد أحمد بن محمّد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الفشني </lem><rdg resp="LS">القيسيّ</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هاذا الكتاب 
<lb n="24 left (wāw)"/>  وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="26"/>  وعبد اللّه بن هعويت وكتب شهادته بخطّه سنة 
<lb n="27"/>  وإبراهيم بن مهدي وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="28"/>  شهد علي بن عبد الجواد بن عبد الأعلى على إقرار النّضر بن عبد اللّه بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="29"/>  وغياث بن محمّد بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نزار </lem><rdg resp="LS">مراد</rdg></app> وكتب شهادته بيده على إقرار النّضر 
<lb n="30"/>  بن عبد اللّه ما ڤى هدا الكپاپ وسهادپه ڤى دى الڤعذه سپه 
<lb n="31"/>  ثمان وثلثين ومائتين <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> شهد هرون بن كامل على إقرار النّضر بن عبد اللّه 
<lb n="32"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وشهادته في ذو القعدة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ستّة </lem><rdg resp="LS">سنة</rdg></app> ثمان وثلثين ومائتين 
<lb n="33"/>  عبد اللّه بن محمّد وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="23 left (ʾalif)"/>  شهد اليسع بن عيسى على إقرار 
<lb n="23 left (bāʾ)"/>  النّضر بن عبد اللّه الزّيّات 
<lb n="24 left (ǧīm)"/>  وعلى إقرار عبد اللّه بن بطرس 
<lb n="24 left (dāl)"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته 
<lb n="24 left (hāʾ)"/>  في ذي القعدة سنة ثمان وثلثين ومائتين 
<lb n="26 left (zāy)"/>  وعبد اللّه بن زيد وكتب شهادته على إقرار 
<lb n="26 left (ḥāʾ)"/>  عبد اللّه بن النّضر بن عبد اللّه بجميع ما في 
<lb n="26 left (ṭāʾ)"/>  هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="27 left (yāʾ)"/>  وعلي بن عبد الأعلى وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu buṭrusa wa laqabu hu ʾantanāsu bnu buṭrusa ăl ʾidfūiyyu mina ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăz zayyāti 
 <lb n="3"/>wa huwa ṣaḥīḥu ăl ʿaqli wa ăl badani lā ʿillaẗa bi hi min maraḍ:in wa lā ġayri hi fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗi ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni ĭštarà min hu 
 <lb n="4"/>ǧamāʿaẗa ṭibāqi ăl manzili ăllaḏī fī hi maʿṣaraẗu ăz zayti fī ḥāraẗi ḥiyāzaẗi bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi fī šarqi ʾidfū 
 <lb n="5"/>wa mā fawqa hu ʾilà ăl hawà wa huwa ʿulwu ăl maʿṣaraẗi ăllatī ḥaddu hā ăl qibliyyu manzilu yūnusa wa mūsà ĭbnay buqṭura ăš šammāsi wa ḥaddu hu ăl baḥriyyu 
 <lb n="6"/>ăṭ ṭarīqu wa ḥaddu hu ăš šarqiyyu manzilu yūnaẗa ĭbnati yuḥannisa wa ăl ʿarṣaẗu ăl maʿrūfaẗu bi brqsa wa ḥaddu hu ăl ġarbiyyu manzil:un li bsnsẗa bssnẗa sisinnaẗa 
 <lb n="7"/>ĭbnati šānūdaẗa bayna humā ăṭ ṭarīqu ĭštarà ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu buṭrusa ăl maʿrūfu bi ʾantanāsa mina ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="8"/>ăz zayyāti ǧamāʿaẗa ăl ġurafi ăllatī hiya ʿulwu hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi ăl maḥdūdaẗi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa mā fawqa hā ʾilà ăl hawà 
 <lb n="9"/>bi ǧamīʿi marāfiqi hā wa murtafaʿi hā wa kulli suṭūḥi hā wa saqfi hā wa kulli qalīl:in wa kaṯīr:in huwa li ʿulwi hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi 
 <lb n="10"/>bi sittaẗi danānīra ʿayn:an ḏahab:an wāzin:an bi ăl maṯāqīli manāqīli ăl ǧadīdi qad naqada ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu buṭrusa ăn naḍra bna ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăz zayyāti 
 <lb n="11"/>hāḏihi ăs sittaẗa ăd danānīri ăl maṯāqīla ṯaman:an li ʿulwi hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi wa mā fawqa hā ʾilà ăl hawà mā ḫalà ăl maslaku 
 <lb n="12"/>ʾilà hāḏihi ăl ġurafi ăl mabīʿaẗi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi fa ʾinna hu lā ḥaqqa li ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa fī ăl maslaki ʾilà ʿulwi hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi wa lā 
 <lb n="13"/>min šayʾ:in min sufli hi wa lā min bābi ăl maʿṣaraẗi wa sallama ăn naḍru bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi li ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa ǧamāʿaẗa ʿulwi 
 <lb n="14"/>mā ʾaḥāṭat bi hi ḥudūdu hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi bi ăṯ ṯamani ăl musammā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa huwa sittaẗu danānīra maṯāqīla 
 <lb n="15"/>wa qabaḍa ʿabdu ăl lāhi ăl maʿrūfu bi ʾantanāsa ṭibāqa hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi ʾilà ăl hawà wa ǧāza ḥāza hu wa malaka hu wa ǧarà ḥukmu hu fī hi 
 <lb n="16"/>wa ṣāra māl:an min māli hi fa lam yabqa li ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi fī ʿulwi hāḏā ăl manzili ăllaḏī fī hi hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗu wa lā fī šayʾ:in min hu 
 <lb n="17"/>qalīl:un wa lā kaṯīr:un ʿalà ăl wuǧūhi kulli hā wa ăl ʾasbābi fa mā ʾadraka ʿabda ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa fī mā ĭštarà 
 <lb n="18"/>mina ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi min daʿw:an ʾaw ṭalibaẗ:in ʾaw ḫuṣūmaẗ:in ʾaw biyāʿaẗ:in tibāʿaẗ:in ʾaw darak:in li ʾaḥad:in mina ăn nāsi fa ʿalà ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="19"/>nafāḏu ḏālika wa ḫalāṣu hu wa taṣḥīḥu hu li ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa ăl maʿrūfi bi ʾantanāsa ʿalà bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida ʿalà ḏālika ʿabdu ăl ʾaʿlà bnu muʿāwiyaẗa bni ʿabdi ăl ʾāḫiri ʾaʿlà wa huwa kātibu ăl kitābi fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗi sittaẗi ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="21"/>wa mūsà bnu ʿīsà bni ʿurwaẗa wa kataba šahādata hu 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida ăl yasaʿu bnu ʿabdi ăl wahhābi ʿalà ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăz zayyāti bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi fī ḏī 
 <lb n="23"/>ăl qaʿdaẗi min sanaẗi ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="24"/>wa ʿabdu ăl karīmi bni mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="25"/>wa šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu muḥammad:in ăl fašniyyu qaysiyyu bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="26"/>wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="27"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu haʿwīta wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi sanaẗi 
 <lb n="28"/>wa ʾibrāhīmu bnu mahdī wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="29"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl ǧawādi bni ʿabdi ăl ʾaʿlà ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="30"/>wa ġiyāṯu bnu muḥammadi bni nizār:in murād:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi yadi hi ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăn naḍri 
 <lb n="31"/>bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗi 
 <lb n="32"/>ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni * šahida hārūnu bnu kāmil:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="33"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ḏū ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗi sittaẗi ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="34"/>ʿabdu ăl lāhi bni muḥammad:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="35"/>šahida ăl yasaʿu bnu ʿīsà ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="36"/>ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăz zayyāti 
 <lb n="37"/>wa ʿalà ʾiqrāri ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa 
 <lb n="38"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu 
 <lb n="39"/>fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗi ṯamān:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="40"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu zayd:in wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="41"/>ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni ăn naḍri bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="42"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="43"/>wa ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl ʾaʿlà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is, what ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus, whose surname is Antanās, b. Buṭrus al-ʾIdfuwī (from Edfou) bought from an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh the oilseller,
			<lb n="3"/>
		while he was healthy in mind and body, no disease being in him from any illness or anything else, in Ḏū l-Qaʿda of the year 238: He bought from him
			<lb n="4"/>
		the entirety of the (upper) floors of the dwelling in which the oil press is, in the quarter of Bišande the deacon (or: the house in which the oil press possessed by Bišande is), in the east of Edfou,
			<lb n="5"/>
		and everything above until the air, this being the upper part of the oil press whose southern boundary is the dwelling of Yūnus and Mūsā, the sons of Buqṭur the deacon, and whose northern boundary
			<lb n="6"/>
		is the lane, whose eastern boundary is the dwelling of of Yūna, daughter of Yuḥannis, and the open area known as Brqs, and whose western boundary is a house of Bsnsa,
			<lb n="7"/>
		daughter of Šānūda, the lane being between them. ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus, known as Antanās, bought from an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh
			<lb n="8"/>
		the oilseller the entirety of the rooms which constitute the upper part of this press defined in this document and everything above until the air
			<lb n="9"/>
		with its appurtenances and its height (high part?) and all its terraces and its roof and everything little or much which belongs to the upper part of this oil press
			<lb n="10"/>
		for six dīnār, gold coins, full weight according to the new miṯqāl. ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus has paid an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh the oilseller
			<lb n="11"/>
		these six dīnār miṯqāl, the price for the upper part of this press and everything above up to the air. The access
			<lb n="12"/>
		to the rooms sold in this document is not free (is not included in the sale?). ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus has no rights in the access to the upper part of this press, &lt;nor&gt;
			<lb n="13"/>
		of anything of its lower part, nor of the the door of the the press. An-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh handed over to ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus the entirety of the upper part
			<lb n="14"/>
		of what the boundaries of this press enclose, for the price named in this document, which is six dīnār miṯqāl,
			<lb n="15"/>
		and ʿAbdallāh, known as Antanās, took over the upper floors of this press up to the air, and he acquired it and took possession of it, and ?his authority became valid in it?,
			<lb n="16"/>
		and it has become his own property, so that nothing little or much has remained for an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh in the upper part of this dwelling in which this press is, nor in anything of it,
			<lb n="17"/>
		in any way, nor by any reason. And whatsoever should ensue to ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus concerning what he bought 
			<lb n="18"/>
		from an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh by way of a claim or pretension or litigation or an article of merchandise / a demand of some person, it is on the expense of an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh
			<lb n="19"/>
		to execute that and to fullfill and correct it for ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus, known as Antanās, as the muslim sale and its contract require it.
			<lb n="20"/>
		This was witnessed by ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà b. Muʿāwiya b. ʿAbd al-ʾĀḫir (or: ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà b. Muʿāwiya b. ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà), he being the writer of the document in Ḏū l-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty eight.
			<lb n="21"/>
		And Mūsà b. ʿIsà b. ʿUrwa (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony.
			<lb n="22"/>
		al-Yasaʿ b. ʿAbd al-Wahhāb witnessed against an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh the oilseller to everything which is in this document in Ḏū
			<lb n="23"/>
		al-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty eight.
			<lb n="24"/>
		And ʿAbd al-Karīm b. Mūsà (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="25"/>
		And ʾAḥmad b. Muḥammad al-Fašnī witnessed to all which is in this document
			<lb n="26"/>
		and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="27"/>
		And ʿAbdallāh b. Haʿwīt? (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting. Year... [aborted datation?]
			<lb n="28"/>
		And ʾIbrāhīm b. Mahdī (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="29"/>
		ʿAlī b. ʿAbd al Ǧawād b. ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà is witness to the acknowledgement of an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh of everything which is in this document.
			<lb n="30"/>
		And Ġiyāṯ b. Muḥammad b. Nizār/Murād (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony by his hand to the acknowledgement of an-Naḍr
			<lb n="31"/>
		b. ʿAbdallāh (of all) which is in this document, and his testimony (was) in Ḏū l-Qaʿda of the year
			<lb n="32"/>
		two hundred and thirty-eight. Hārūn b. Kāmil witnessed to the acknowledgement of an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh
			<lb n="33"/>
		of all which is is in this document, and his testimony (took place) in Ḏū l-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty-eight.
			<lb n="34"/>
		ʿAbdallāh b. Muḥammad (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
			<lb n="35"/>
		al-Yasaʿ b. ʿĪsà witnessed to the acknowledgement
			<lb n="36"/>
		of an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh the oilseller
			<lb n="37"/>
		and to the acknowledgement of ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus
			<lb n="38"/>
		of which is in this document, and he wrote his testimony
			<lb n="39"/>
		in Ḏū l-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty-eight.
			<lb n="40"/>
		And ʿAbdallāh b. Zayd (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony to the acknowledgement
			<lb n="41"/>
		of ʿAbdallāh b. an-Naḍr b. ʿAbdallāh (sic) of all which is in
			<lb n="42"/>
		this document.
			<lb n="43"/>
		And ʿAlī b. ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà (witnessed to this contract), and he wrote his testimony in his handwriting.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
