<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1625" xml:id="Fahmi_040" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 04</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_040</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169381</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترت مطرونة ابنت أبنولة من سكّان ططون اشترت من قفرى بن بليط حصّته 
<lb n="3"/>  من المنزل الّذي يملكه بططون بجميع حدوده ومرافقه ومدخله ومخرجه <sic n="superfluous">وسلڤه</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">وسفله</supplied> وعلوه 
<lb n="4"/>  ونقضه وبنائه وأبوابه وأفنائه وخشبه وكل حق له في هذا المنزل وحصّته من الدّور الّتي 
<lb n="5"/>  للدّواب وحصّته من المنزل الّذي بلصق منزل ورثة أبيمة بن ذكري بجميع ما غلقت عليه باب 
<lb n="6"/>  هذا المنزل والدّار الّذي بلصق هذا المنزل وحصّته من النّخل والسّنط الّذي بينه وبين بمون أخوه 
<lb n="7"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> أبو موسى وحصّته من جميع ما كان بينه وبين 
<lb n="8"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> مشاع غير مقسوم من المنازل والدّور والسّنط والنّخل والجمّيز وغير ذلك 
<lb n="9"/>  ممّا خلقه اللّه وبرأه ممّا كان بينه وبين بمون أخوه مشاع غير مقسوم اشترت مطرونة 
<lb n="10"/>  ابنت أبنولة منه ذلك كلّه بثلثين دينرا عينا ذهبا وقد قبض قفرى بن بليط من مطرونة ابنت 
<lb n="11"/>  أبنولة هذه الثّلثين دينرا وبرئ من هذه المنازل والدّور والنّخل والسّنط وجميع ما سمّي في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="12"/>  حدودها ومرافقها ومصعدها ومدخلها ومخرجها وكل حق لقفرى بن بليط داخل 
<lb n="13"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> لمطرونة ابنت أبنولة وصار ذلك مالا من مالها وملك من 
<lb n="14"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مـ</supplied>ـلكها إن شاپ باعت وإن شاپ عمرت وإن شاپ عطّلت وقد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أحازت </lem><rdg resp="LS">أحازت</rdg></app> مطرونة هذه المنازل 
<lb n="15"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>الدّور والسّنط والنّخل المحدود في هذا الكتاب وافترقا عن تراض منهما طائعين غير مكرهين 
<lb n="16"/>  ولا مجبرين ولم يبق لقفرى بن بليط دعوى ولا طلبة ولا قليل ولا كثير بوجه من الوجوه كلّها والأسباب 
<lb n="17"/>  وحد حدود هذا المنزل الكبير والدّور حدّهم القبلي الصّحرا والبحري باب المنزل والمدخل والمخرج 
<lb n="18"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وا</supplied>لـشّرقي منازل سويرس بن مارمينا والغربي منزل موسيس بن هميسة ودوره وحد حدوده 
<lb n="19"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> أبيمة بن ذكري والدّار حدّهم القبلي الصّحرا والبحري منزل بني هيلانة 
<lb n="20"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والـ</supplied>ـشّرقي منزل ورثة أبيمة بن ذكري والغربي الصّحرا شهد على إقرار قفرى بن بليط بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="21"/>  بعد أن قرئ عليه وعرفه وأقر بفهمه في صحّة من عقله وبدنه وجواز أمره غير مططهد 
<lb n="22"/>  ولا مجبر طالب راغب وذلك في صفر سنة ثمان وستّين ومائتين شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="23"/>  شهد الحسن بن رزق على إقرار قفرى بن بليط بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب عنه داود ولده بأمره ومحضره وذلك في صفر سنة ثمان وستّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـين</supplied> 
<lb n="24"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> رزق على إقرار قفرى بن بليط بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه في صفر سنة ثمان <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="25"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إ</supplied>سحق بن سليمن بن رزق على إقرار قفرى بن بليط بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب في صفر سنة ثمان وستّين ومائتين 
<lb n="26"/>  شهد طاهر بن الحسن بن رزق بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه وذلك في صفر سنة <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="27"/>  شهد هرون بن الحسن بن رزق بجـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـميع</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ما</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه وذلك في 
<lb n="28"/>  صفر سنة ثمان وستّين ومائتين شهد أ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حمد</supplied> بن الحسن بن رزق على إقرار قفرى بن بليط 
<lb n="29"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه وذلك <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">في</supplied> صفر سنة ثمان وستّين ومائتين 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarat maṭrūnaẗu ĭbnatu ʾabnūlaẗa min sukkāni ṭuṭūna ĭštarat min qufrà bni balīṭa ḥiṣṣata hu 
 <lb n="3"/>mina ăl manzili ăllaḏī yamliku hu bi ṭuṭūna bi ǧamīʿi ḥudūdi hi wa marāfiqi hi wa madḫali hi wa maḫraǧi hi wa sufli hi wa ʿulwi hi 
 <lb n="4"/>wa naqḍi hi wa bināʾi hi wa ʾabwābi hi wa ʾafnāʾi hi wa ḫašabi hi wa kulli ḥaqq:in la hu fī hāḏā ăl manzili wa ḥiṣṣata hu mina ăd dūri ăllatī 
 <lb n="5"/>li d dwʾbi wa ḥiṣṣata hu mina ăl manzili ăllaḏī bi liṣqi manzili waraṯaẗi ʾabīmaẗa bni ḏikrī bi ǧamīʿi mā ġalaqat ʿalay hi bābu 
 <lb n="6"/>hāḏā ăl manzili wa ăd dāra ăllaḏī bi liṣqi hāḏā ăl manzili wa ḥiṣṣata hu mina ăn naḫli wa ăs sanṭi ăllaḏī bayna hu wa bayna bamūna ʾaḫū hu 
 <lb n="7"/>*** ʾabū mūsà wa ḥiṣṣata hu min ǧamīʿi mā kāna bayna hu wa bayna 
 <lb n="8"/>*** mušāʿ ġayr maqsūm:in mina ăl manāzili wa ăd dūri wa ăs sanṭi wa ăn naḫli wa ăl ǧummayzi wa ġayri ḏālika 
 <lb n="9"/>mimmā ḫalaqa hu ăl lāhu wa baraʾa hu mimmā kāna bayna hu wa bayna bamūna ʾaḫū hu mušāʿ ġayra maqsūm:in ĭštarat maṭrūnaẗu 
 <lb n="10"/>ĭbnatu ʾabnūlaẗa min hu ḏālika kulla hu bi ṯalāṯīna dīnār:an ʿayn:an ḏahab:an wa qad qabaḍa qufrà bnu balīṭa min maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati 
 <lb n="11"/>ʾabnūlaẗa hāḏihi ăṯ ṯalāṯīna dīnār:an wa bariʾa min hāḏihi ăl manāzili wa ăd dūri wa ăl naḫli wa ăs sanṭi wa ǧamīʿi mā summiya fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="12"/>ḥudūdi hā wa marāfiqi hā wa maṣʿadi hā wa madḫali hā wa maḫraǧi hā wa kulli ḥaqq:in li qufrà bni balīṭa dāḫil 
 <lb n="13"/>*** li maṭrūnaẗa ĭbnati ʾabnūlaẗa wa ṣāra ḏālika māl:an min māli hā wa milk min 
 <lb n="14"/>milki hā ʾin šāʾat bāʿat wa ʾin šāʾat ʿamarat wa ʾin šāʾat ʿaṭṭalat wa qad ʾaǧāzat ʾaḥāzat maṭrūnaẗu hāḏihi ăl manāzila 
 <lb n="15"/>wa ăd dūra wa ăs sanṭa wa ăn naḫla ăl maḥdūda fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ĭftaraqā ʿan tarāḍ:in min humā ṭāʾiʿayni ġayra mukrahayni 
 <lb n="16"/>wa lā muǧbarayni wa lam yabqa li qufrà bni balīṭa daʿw:an wa lā ṭalibaẗ:un wa lā qalīl:un wa lā kaṯīr:un bi waǧh:in mina ăl wuǧūhi kulli hā wa ăl ʾasbābi 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ḥadda ḥudūd:un hāḏā ăl manzila ăl kabīra wa ăd dūra ḥaddu humu ăl qibliyyu ăṣ ṣaḥrāʾu wa ăl baḥriyyu bābu ăl manzili wa ăl madḫalu wa ăl maḫraǧu 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ăš šarqiyyu manāzilu sawīrisa bni mārmīnā wa ăl ġarbiyyu manzilu mūsīsa bni humīsaẗa wa dūru hu wa ḥadda ḥudūdu hu 
 <lb n="19"/>*** ʾabīmaẗ bn ḏikrī wa ăd dār ḥaddu humu ăl qibliyyu ăṣ ṣaḥrāʾu wa ăl baḥriyyu manzilu banī hīlānaẗa 
 <lb n="20"/>wa ăš šarqiyyu manzilu waraṯaẗi ʾabīmaẗa bni ḏikrī wa ăl ġarbiyyu ăṣ ṣaḥrāʾu šuhida ʿalà ʾiqrāri qufrà bni balīṭa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="21"/>baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay hi wa ʿarafa hu wa ʾaqarra bi fahmi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗ:in min ʿaqli hi wa badani hi wa ǧawāzi ʾamri hi ġayra muṭṭahad:in 
 <lb n="22"/>wa lā muǧbar:in ṭālib rāġib wa ḏālika fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in wa sittīna wa miʾatayni šuhida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="23"/>šahida ăl ḥasanu bnu rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri qufrà bni balīṭa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba ʿan hu dāwidu waladu hu bi ʾamri hi wa maḥḍari hi wa ḏālika fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in wa sittīna 
 <lb n="24"/>*** rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri qufrà bni balīṭa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in *** 
 <lb n="25"/>*** ʾisḥāqu bnu sulaymāna bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri qufrà bni balīṭa bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in wa sittīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="26"/>šahida ṭāhiru bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa *** 
 <lb n="27"/>šahida hārūnu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī 
 <lb n="28"/>ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in wa sittīna wa miʾatayni šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri qufrà bni balīṭa 
 <lb n="29"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ḏālika fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯamān:in wa sittīna wa miʾatayni 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		 In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is, what Maṭrūna bt. ʾAbnūla, of the inhabitants of Ṭuṭūn, has bought. She bought from Qufrà b. Balīṭ his share
			<lb n="3"/>
		of the dwelling which he owns in Ṭuṭūn, with all its boundaries and appurtenances, its entry and exit, its lower and upper part,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and its beams and buildings, doors and fore-courts and its wood, and every right belonging to it in this dwelling, and his share of the houses which
			<lb n="5"/>
		belong to the ?dwʾb?, and his share of the dwelling attached to the dwelling of the heirs of ʾAbīme b. Ḏikrī, with everything which the door of this dwelling
			<lb n="6"/>
		enclose, and the building attached to this dwelling, and his share of the date-palms and the acacia (shared) between him and his brother Bamūn
			<lb n="7"/>
		[...] ʾAbū Mūsà, and (she bought?) his share of everything which he owned together with
			<lb n="8"/>
		[...] hold in common, not divided, of the dwellings, the buildings, the acacia, the date-palms, the sycamores and the everything else
			<lb n="9"/>
		of what God created and brought into being of what was between him and his brother, owned in common and not divided. Maṭrūna bt. ʾAbnūle
			<lb n="10"/>
		bought from him all this for thirty dīnārs, cold coin. Qufrà b. Balīṭ has received from Maṭrūna bt.
			<lb n="11"/>
		ʾAbnūle those thirty dīnārs, and he became free of these dwellings, buildings, date-palms, acacia and sycamores and everything named in this document
			<lb n="12"/>
		&lt;with&gt; their boundaries and appurtenances, their stairs (?), entry and exit and every right belonging to Qufrà b. Balīṭ inside
			<lb n="13"/>
		[...] to Maṭrūna bt. ʾAbnūle, so that this became a property in her property and an estate in
			<lb n="14"/>
		her estate. If she wants, she may sell it, and if she wants, she may inhabit it, and if she wants, she may leave it empty. Maṭruna has taken possession of these dwellings 
			<lb n="15"/>
		houses, acacia and date-palms delimited in this document, and they separated in mutual satisfaction, desiring it, not compulsed
			<lb n="16"/>
		nor under coercion. Nothing has remained to Qufrà b. Balīṭ by way of a claim or demand, little or much in any way nor by any reason.
			<lb n="17"/>
		Boundaries delimit this big dwelling and the buildings: Their southern boundary is the desert, the northern one the door of the dwelling, its entry and exit,
			<lb n="18"/>
		the eastern one are the dwellings of Sawīris b. Mārmīnā, and the western one the dwelling of Mūsīs b. Homīse and his buildings. And its boundaries delimit
			<lb n="19"/>
		[? the second object sold, i.e. the dwelling attached to the dwelling of the heirs of ? ] ʾAbīme b. Ḏikrī and the building: Their southern boundary is the desert, the northern one is the dwelling of the sons of Hīlāne,
			<lb n="20"/>
		the eastern one is the dwelling of the heirs of ʾAbīme b. Ḏikrī, and the western one is the desert. The acknowldedgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ of everything in this document has been witnessed to
			<lb n="21"/>
		after it was read to him, and he took notice of it and acknowledged to have understood it, being in good health of his mind and body and capable of transacting his business, without constraint
			<lb n="22"/>
		nor coercion, desiring and wishing it. This (took place) in Ṣafar of the year two hundred and sixty-eight. This has been testified.
			<lb n="23"/>
		al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ of everything in this document, and his child Dāwid wrote for him on his order and in his presence. This (took place) in Ṣafar, in the year ... and six[ty]-eight.
			<lb n="24"/>
		[Dāwid b. al-Ḥasan b.? ] Rizq [witnessed] to the acknowledgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ to everything in this document, and he wrote with his own handwriting in Ṣafar, in ... -eight.
			<lb n="25"/>
		ʾIsḥāq b. Sulaymān b. Rizq [witnessed] to the acknowledgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ to everything in this document, and he wrote in Ṣafar, in two-hundred and sixty-eight.
			<lb n="26"/>
		Ṭāhir b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to everything in this document, and he wrote in his own handwriting. This (took place) in Ṣafar, year...
			<lb n="27"/>
		Hārūn b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ of ev(erything in) this document, and he wrote in his own handwriting. This (took place) in
			<lb n="28"/>
		Ṣafar, in two-hundred and sixty-eight. ʾA(ḥmad) b. a-Ḥasan b. Rizq witnessed to the acknowledgement by Qufrà b. Balīṭ
			<lb n="29"/>
		of everything in this document, and he wrote in his own handwriting. This (took place) in Ṣafar, in two hundred and sixty-eight.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
