<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1617" xml:id="Fahmi_020" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.FahmiTaaqud 02</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Fahmi_020</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169373</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى علي بن عبد اللّه ولقبه أنتناس من مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عيسى </lem><rdg resp="LS">يحنّس</rdg></app> الشّمّاس 
<lb n="3"/>  في شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة ست وأربعين ومائتين اشترا منهم جماعة حقّهم من سفل المنزل الّذي فيه معصرة الزّيت الّتي في 
<lb n="4"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حارة </lem><rdg resp="LS">حيازة</rdg></app> كنيسة بن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">بنتمون</unclear> في شرق إدفوا جميع حقوقهم ممّا هو لها من آلة المعصرة من الحجارة والخشب والنّجب ومرافقها 
<lb n="5"/>  كلّها وذلك ثمانية أسهم من أربعة وعشرين سهما من جماعة سفل هذا المنزل وآلة المعصرة وهي المعصرة الّتي حدّها 
<lb n="6"/>  القبلي منزل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أبو </lem><rdg resp="LS. cf. P.FahmīTaʿāqud 01.5">يونس</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يسى </lem><rdg resp="LS">ø</rdg></app> وموسى ابني بقطر الشّمّاس وحدّها البحري الطّريق وحدّها الشّرقي منزل يونة ابنت يحنّس الشّمّاس 
<lb n="7"/>  وحدّها الغربي منزل لقزمان بن بشندة الشّمّاس وعلوا هذا المنزل لعبد اللّه بن بطرس ولقبه أنتناس اشترى علي بن عبد اللّه 
<lb n="8"/>  من مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة الشّمّاس هذه الثّمانية أسهم من أربعة وعشرين سهما من جماعة هذا المنزل المعروف 
<lb n="9"/>  بالمعصرة الّتي علوها لعبد اللّه بن بطرس وممّا بها من آلة المعصرة بحدّها وحدودها ومداخلها ومخارجها ومرافقها ومرتفعها 
<lb n="10"/>  وسلّمها وفنائها والبهائم النّجب والحجارة ومن كل قليل وكثير هو فيها ومنها ولها بأربعة دنانير وربع دينر عينا ذهبا وزنا بالمثاقيل 
<lb n="11"/>  الجديد قد نقد علي بن عبد اللّه المعروف بأنتناس مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة بن يحنّس الشّمّاس هذه الأربعة دنانير والرّبع دينر 
<lb n="12"/>  ثمنا لهذه الثّمانية أسهم من أربعة وعشرين سهما من سفل جماعة هذا المنزل الّذي فيه المعصرة ومن آلة المعصرة الّتي في هذا المنزل 
<lb n="13"/>  تسلّم إليهم مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة بن يحنّس الشّمّاس هذه الأربعة دنانير والرّبع من علي بن عبد اللّه تامّة وافية وسلّم 
<lb n="14"/>  مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة كبوا ورثة بشندة لعلي بن عبد اللّه جميع حقوقهم من سفل هذا المنزل ومن آلة المعصرة الّتي في هذا المنزل 
<lb n="15"/>  بالثّمن المسمّا في هذا الكتاب وهو أربعة دنانير وربع دينر فلم يبق لمينا ولا لقزمان ولا لهسفرنة ولا لقبوا في جماعة هذا المنزل ولا في جماعة المعصرة 
<lb n="16"/>  وآلتها قليل ولا كثير على الوجوه كلّها والأسباب فما أدرك علي بن عبد اللّه المعروف بأنتناس في حقّه من هذا المنزل الّذي اشتراه 
<lb n="17"/>  من ورثة بشندة الشّمّاس أو في حقّه من هذه المعصرة وهو ثمانية أسهم من أربعة وعشرين سهما من جماعة سفل هذا المنزل 
<lb n="18"/>  بما فيه من دعوى أو طلبة أو علقة أو <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تباعة </lem><rdg resp="LS">تباعة</rdg></app> أو خصومة أو درك لأحد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">قبل </lem><rdg resp="LS">فعلى</rdg></app> مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فنفاذ </lem><rdg resp="LS">إنفاذ</rdg></app> ذلك 
<lb n="19"/>  وخلاصه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وتصميمه </lem><rdg resp="LS">وتصحيحه</rdg></app> لعلي بن عبد اللّه على بيع الإسلام وعهدته شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="20"/>  شهد هرون بن إسحق على إقرار مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة بن يحنّس الشّمّاس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="21"/>  وشهادته في المحرّم سنة سبع وأربعين ومائتين شهد اليسع بن علي على مينا وقزمان ابني بشندة الشّمّاس بما 
<lb n="22"/>  في هذا الكتاب وشهادته في المحرّم سنة سبع وأربعين ومائتين 
<lb n="23"/>  شهد رجب بن عديل على إقرار مينا وقزمان وهسفرنة وقبوا ورثة بشندة الشّمّاس وعلى علي بن عبد اللّه بجميع 
<lb n="24"/>  ما في هذا الكتاب وشهـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـا</supplied>ـدته في المحرّم من سنة سبع وأربعين ومائتين 
<lb n="25"/>  شهد علي بن عبد الأعلى بن معوية على مينا وقزمان ابني بشندة الشّمّاس بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="26"/>  وشهـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـا</supplied>ـدته في المحرّم سنة سبع وأربعين ومائتين 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi wa laqabu hu ʾantanāsu min mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa bni ʿīsà yuḥannisa ăš šammāsi 
 <lb n="3"/>fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗi sitt:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni ĭštarā min hum ǧamāʿaẗa ḥaqqi him min sufli ăl manzili ăllaḏī fī hi maʿṣaraẗu ăz zayti ăllatī fī 
 <lb n="4"/>ḥāraẗi ḥiyāzaẗi kanīsaẗi bni bntmūna fī šarqi ʾidfū ǧamīʿa ḥuqūqi him mimmā huwa la hā min ʾālaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi mina ăl ḥiǧāraẗi wa ăl ḫašabi wa ăn naǧabi wa marāfiqi hā 
 <lb n="5"/>kulla hā wa ḏālika ṯamāniyaẗu ʾashum:in min ʾarbaʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna sahm:an min ǧamāʿaẗi sufli hāḏā ăl manzili wa ʾālaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi wa hiya ăl maʿṣaraẗu ăllatī ḥaddu hā 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl qibliyyu manzilu ʾabū yūnusa yasà ø wa mūsà ĭbnay buqṭura ăš šammāsi wa ḥaddu hā ăl baḥriyyu ăṭ ṭarīqu wa ḥaddu hā ăš šarqiyyu manzilu yūnaẗa ĭbnati yuḥannisa ăš šammāsi 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ḥaddu hā ăl ġarbiyyu manzil:un li quzmāna bni bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi wa ʿulwu hāḏā ăl manzili li ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa wa laqabu hu ʾantanāsu ĭštarà ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="8"/>min mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi hāḏihi ăṯ ṯamāniyaẗa ʾashum:in min ʾarbaʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna sahm:an min ǧamāʿaẗi hāḏā ăl manzili ăl maʿrūfi 
 <lb n="9"/>bi ăl maʿṣaraẗi ăllatī ʿulwu hā li ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni buṭrusa wa mimmā bi hā min ʾālaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi bi ḥaddi hā wa ḥudūdi hā wa madāḫili hā wa maḫāriǧi hā wa marāfiqi hā wa murtafaʿi hā 
 <lb n="10"/>wa sullami hā wa fināʾi hā wa ăl bahāʾimi ăn nuǧubi wa ăl ḥiǧāraẗi wa min kulli qalīl:in wa kaṯīr:in huwa fī hā wa min hā wa la hā bi ʾarbaʿaẗi danānīra wa rubʿi dīnār:in ʿayn:an ḏahab:an wāzin:an bi ăl maṯāqīli 
 <lb n="11"/>ăl ǧadīdi qad naqada ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăl maʿrūfi bi ʾantanāsa mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗa bišandaẗa bni yuḥannisa ăš šammāsi hāḏihi ăl ʾarbaʿaẗa danānīra wa ăr rubʿa dīnār:in 
 <lb n="12"/>ṯaman:an li hāḏihi ăṯ ṯamāniyaẗi ʾashum:in min ʾarbaʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna sahm:an min sufli ǧamāʿaẗi hāḏā ăl manzili ăllaḏī fī hi ăl maʿṣaraẗu wa min ʾālaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi ăllatī fī hāḏā ăl manzili 
 <lb n="13"/>tasallama ʾilay him mīnā wa quzmānu wa hsfrnaẗu wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗu bišandaẗa bni yuḥannisa ăš šammāsi hāḏihi ăl ʾarbaʿaẗa danānīra wa ăr rubʿa min ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi tāmmaẗ:an wāfiyaẗ:an wa sallama 
 <lb n="14"/>mīnā wa quzmānu wa hsfrnaẗu kbwʾ waraṯaẗu bišandaẗa li ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi ǧamīʿa ḥuqūqi him min sufli hāḏā ăl manzili wa min ʾālaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi ăllatī fī hāḏā ăl manzili 
 <lb n="15"/>bi ăṯ ṯamani ăl musammā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa huwa ʾarbaʿaẗu danānīra wa rubʿu dīnār:in fa lam yabqa li mīnā wa lā li quzmāna wa lā li hsfrnaẗa wa lā li qbwʾ fī ǧamāʿaẗi hāḏā ăl manzili wa lā fī ǧamāʿaẗi ăl maʿṣaraẗi 
 <lb n="16"/>wa ʾālati hā qalīl:un wa lā kaṯīr:un ʿalà ăl wuǧūhi kulli hā wa ăl ʾasbābi fa mā ʾadraka ʿaliyya bna ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăl maʿrūfi bi ʾantanāsa fī ḥaqqi hi min hāḏā ăl manzili ăllaḏī ĭštarā hu 
 <lb n="17"/>min waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi ʾaw fī ḥaqqi hi min hāḏihi ăl maʿṣaraẗi wa huwa ṯamāniyaẗu ʾashum:in min ʾarbaʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna sahm:an min ǧamāʿaẗi sufli hāḏā ăl manzili 
 <lb n="18"/>bi mā fī hi min daʿwà ʾaw ṭalibaẗ:in ʾaw ʿulqaẗ:in ʾaw biyāʿaẗ:in tibāʿaẗ:in ʾaw ḫuṣūmaẗ:in ʾaw darak:in li ʾaḥad:in ø fa qabla ʿalà mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa fa ø nafāḏu ʾinfāḏu ḏālika 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ḫalāṣu hu wa taṣmīmu taṣḥīḥu hu li ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi ʿalà bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi šuhida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida hārūnu bnu ʾisḥāqa ʿalà ʾiqrāri mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa bni yuḥannisa ăš šammāsi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="21"/>wa šahādatu hu fī ăl muḥarrami sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni šahida ăl yasaʿu bnu ʿaliyy:in ʿalà mīnā wa quzmāna ĭbnay bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi bi mā 
 <lb n="22"/>fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ăl muḥarrami sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="23"/>šahida raǧabu bnu ʿadīl:in ʿudayl:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri mīnā wa quzmāna wa hsfrnaẗa wa qbwʾ waraṯaẗi bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi wa ʿalà ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi bi ǧamīʿi 
 <lb n="24"/>mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ăl muḥarrami min sanaẗi sabʿ:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="25"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl ʾaʿlà bni muʿāwiyaẗa ʿalà mīnā wa quzmāna ĭbnay bišandaẗa ăš šammāsi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="26"/>wa šahādatu hu fī ăl muḥarrami sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		 In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate. 
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is, what ʿAlī, son of ʿAbdallāh, whose surname is Antanās, bought from Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande b. ʿĪsà (Yuḥannis) the deacon,
			<lb n="3"/>
		in the month of Rabīʿ I of the year 246. He bought from them the entirety of their right of the lower part of the the dwelling in which stands the press which is in
			<lb n="4"/>
		the quarter of the church of b. Bntmūn? (the possession of x son of y), in the east of Edfou. (He bought) all their rights of what belongs to it (i.e. the press-building) of the press-machine, of the stones and the wood and the bark [?] and all of its
			<lb n="5"/>
		appurtenances, and that corresponds to eight shares of twenty-four shares for the entirety of the lower part and of this dwelling and the press-machine, and it is the press(-building) whose southern
			<lb n="6"/>
		border is the dwelling of ʾAbū Yasà (Yūnus) and Mūsà, the sons of Buqṭur the deacon, whose northern boundary is the lane, whose eastern boundary is the dwelling of Yūna, daughter of Youḥannis the deacon,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and whose western boundary is a dwelling of Quzmān b. Bišande, the deacon. The upper part of this dwelling belongs to ʿAbdallāh b. Buṭrus, whose surname is Antanās. ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh bought
			<lb n="8"/>
		from Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwā, the heirs of Bišande the deacon, these eight shares of twenty-four shares of the entirety of this dwelling known
			<lb n="9"/>
		as the press, whose upper part belongs to ʿAbdallāh b. Butrus, and (the shares) of what belongs to it of the press-machine, with its border and its boundaries, its entries and exits, its appurtenances and its height [?], 
			<lb n="10"/>
		its stair and its fore-court, and its ?noble animals? and the stones, and of everything little or much which is in it and comes from it and belongs to it, for four dīnār and a quarter-dīnār, cold coins, full weight according to the new
			<lb n="11"/>
		miṯqāl. ʿAlī, son of ʿAbdallāh known as Antanās, has paid Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande b. Yuḥannis the deacon, these four dīnār and quarter-dīnār
			<lb n="12"/>
		as a price for these eight shares out of twenty-four shares of the lower part of the entirety of this dwelling in which there is the press and of the press-machine which is in this dwelling.
			<lb n="13"/>
		Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande b. Yuḥannis the deacon, received for themselves these four dīnār and the quarter from ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh fully and entirely, and Mīnā,
			<lb n="14"/>
		Quzmān, Hsfrna &lt;and&gt; Kbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande, handed over to ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh all of their rights of the lower part of this dwelling and of the press-machine which is in this dwelling,
			<lb n="15"/>
		for the price named in this document, which is four dīnār and a quarter-dīnār. Nothing has remained to Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna nor Qbwʾ in the entirety of this dwelling, nor in the entirety of the press(-building)
			<lb n="16"/>
		and its machine, little or much, in any way nor by any reason. And whatsoever should ensue to ʿAlī, son of ʿAbdallāh known as Antanās, in his right on this dwelling which he bought
			<lb n="17"/>
		from the heirs of Bišande, the deacon, or in his right on this press(-machine?) - this being eight shares out of twenty-four shares of the entirety of the lower part of this dwelling
			<lb n="18"/>
		with what is in it - , by way of a claim, pretension, impediment, article of merchandise (?) / demand, litigation or vindication by anyone before Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande (i.e., a previous owner?), then the execution of that
		with what is in it - , by way of a claim, pretension, impediment, demand, litigation or vindication by anyone, then it will be on the expense of Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande, to execute that
			<lb n="19"/>
		and its fulfillment and blocking (?) will be in favor of ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh, as the muslim sale and its contract require it. This has been testified.
		and to fulfill and correct it in favor of ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh, as the muslim sale and its contract require it. This has been testified.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Hārūn b. ʾIṣḥāq witnessed to the acknowledgement of Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande b. Yuḥannis the deacon, of all which is in this document,
			<lb n="21"/>
		and his testimony (took place) in al-muḥarram of the year two hundred and fourty-seven. al-Yasaʿ b. ʿAlī witnessed against Mīnā and Quzmān, the sons of Bišande the deacon, to what
			<lb n="22"/>
		is in this document, and his testimony (took place) in al-muḥarram of the year two hundred and fourty-seven.
			<lb n="23"/>
		Raǧab b. ʿAdīl witnessed to the acknowledgement of Mīnā, Quzmān, Hsfrna and Qbwʾ, the heirs of Bišande the deacon, and to (the acknowledgement of) ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh of all
			<lb n="24"/>
		which is in this document, and his testimony (took place) in al-muḥarram of the year two hundred and fourty-seven.
			<lb n="25"/>
		ʿAlī b. ʿAbd al-ʾAʿlà b. Muʿāwiya witnessed against Mīnā and Quzmān, the sons of Bišande the deacon, to all which is in this document
			<lb n="26"/>
		and his testimony (took place) in al-muḥarram of the year two hundred and fourty-seven.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
