<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1350" xml:id="FrantzMurphy_Comparison_2" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Frantz-MurphyComparison I 2</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">FrantzMurphy_Comparison_2</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169151</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">سراح </lem><rdg resp="APD">سراج </rdg><rdg resp="APD">شراج</rdg></app> بن دنيل من بقام بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دميني </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> من سكّان ططون من كورة الفيّوم 
<lb n="3"/>  اشترى منه الدّار الّذي له شرقي منزل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">شراج </lem><rdg resp="APD">سراج </rdg><rdg resp="APD">شراج</rdg></app> بن دنيل بحدّه وحدوده وسفله وعلوه 
<lb n="4"/>  داخل فيه وخارج منه حدّه القبلي منزل ورثة بن مونة الأصم وحدّه البحري الدّار الّذي 
<lb n="5"/>  لبقام بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دميني </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> وحدّه الشّرقي منزل ورثة كيل بن أبمالة وحدّه الغربي منزل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">سراج </lem><rdg resp="APD">سراج </rdg><rdg resp="APD">شراج</rdg></app> بن 
<lb n="6"/>  دنيل اشترى ذلك منه بدينارين وسدس عينا ذهبا وازن بالجديد قد قبض بقام 
<lb n="7"/>  بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دمينى </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> الثّمن تامّا وافيا وبرئ من هذا الدّار الموصوف في هذا الكتاب وسلّم 
<lb n="8"/>  ذلك إلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">سراح </lem><rdg resp="APD">سراج </rdg><rdg resp="APD">شراج</rdg></app> بن دنيل وقبضه وحازه وملكه وصار ذلك مال من ماله 
<lb n="9"/>  وملك من ملكه إن شا باع وإن شا <sic n="superfluous">بناى</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">بنا</supplied> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>إن شا سكن ليس لبقام بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دميني </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> في 
<lb n="10"/>  هذا الدّار بعد هذا الكتاب دعوى ولا طلبة بوجه من الوجوه ولا سبب من 
<lb n="11"/>  الأسباب باع ذلك على شرط بيع الإسلام وعهدته فما كان من علقة أو 
<lb n="12"/>  تباعة أو طارئ بدين فإنفاذ ذلك وخلاصه على بقام بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دميني </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> بالغ ما بلغ من 
<lb n="13"/>  خالص ماله شهد على إقرار بقام بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دمينى </lem><rdg resp="APD">دمينى</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب بعد أن قرئ 
<lb n="14"/>  عليه بالعربيّة وفسّر له بالعجميّة في صحّة عقله وبدنه وجواز أموره طائع 
<lb n="15"/>  غير مكره ولا مجبر ولا مضطهد طالب راغب وذلك في المحرّم من سنة 
<lb n="16"/>  اپپپى وخمسين وثلثمائة أقر بقام بما في هذا الكتاب <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بشراج </lem><rdg resp="APD">بسراج </rdg><rdg resp="APD">بشراج</rdg></app> بن دنيل فكتب عنه <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">عمر</unclear> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">بن</unclear> موسى بحطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="17"/>  ‮شهد علي بن جبريل بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه ودتوز بن أحمد وكتب عليه ‪Τιτιυ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="18"/>  شهد إسمعيل بن عبد القاهر على إقرار هولا النّفر المسمّون في هذا الكتاب وكتب في تأريخه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà sarāḥu sirāǧu širāǧu bnu danīla daniyala min baqāma bni damiyanà damiyanī min sukkāni ṭuṭūna min kūraẗi ăl fayyūmi 
 <lb n="3"/>ĭštarà min hu ăd dāra ăllaḏī la hu šarqiyyu manzili sarāḥa sirāǧa širāǧa bni danīla daniyala bi ḥaddi hi wa ḥudūdi hi wa sufli hi wa ʿulwi hi 
 <lb n="4"/>dāḫil fī hi wa ḫāriǧ min hu ḥaddu hu ăl qibliyyu manzilu waraṯaẗi bni mūnaẗa ăl ʾaṣammi wa ḥaddu hu ăl baḥriyyu ăd dāru ăllaḏī 
 <lb n="5"/>li baqāma bni damiyanà damiyanī wa ḥaddu hu ăš šarqiyyu manzilu waraṯaẗi kayli bni ʾabamālaẗa wa ḥaddu hu ăl ġarbiyyu manzilu sarāḥa sirāǧa širāǧa bni 
 <lb n="6"/>danīla daniyala ĭštarà ḏālika min hu bi dīnārayni wa suds:in ʿayn:an ḏahab:an wāzin:in bi ăl ǧadīdi qad qabaḍa baqāmu 
 <lb n="7"/>bnu damiyanà damiyanī ăṯ ṯamana tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa bariʾa min hāḏā ăd dāri ăl mawṣūfi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa sallama 
 <lb n="8"/>ḏālika ʾilà sarāḥa sirāǧa širāǧa bni danīla daniyala wa qabaḍa hu wa ḥāza hu wa malaka hu wa ṣāra ḏālika māl min māli hi 
 <lb n="9"/>wa milk min milki hi ʾin šāʾa bāʿa wa ʾin šāʾa banā wa ʾin šāʾa sakana laysa li baqāma bni damiyanà damiyanī fī 
 <lb n="10"/>hāḏā ăd dāri baʿda hāḏā ăl kitābi daʿw:an wa lā ṭalibaẗ:un bi waǧh:in mina ăl wuǧūhi wa lā sabab:in mina 
 <lb n="11"/>ăl ʾasbābi bāʿa ḏālika ʿalà šarṭi bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi fa mā kāna min ʿulqaẗ:in ʾaw 
 <lb n="12"/>tabāʿaẗ:in ʾaw ṭāriʾ:in bi dayn:in fa ʾinfāḏu ḏālika wa ḫalāṣu hu ʿalà baqāma bni damiyanà damiyanī bāliġ:un mā balaġa min 
 <lb n="13"/>ḫāliṣi māli hi šuhida ʿalà ʾiqrāri baqāma bni damiyanà damiyanī bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi baʿda ʾan quriʾa 
 <lb n="14"/>ʿalay hi bi ăl ʿarabiyyaẗi wa fussira la hu bi ăl ʿaǧamiyyaẗi fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿaqli hi wa badani hi wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri hi ṭāʾiʿ 
 <lb n="15"/>ġayra mukrah:in wa lā muǧbar:in wa lā muḍṭahad:in ṭālib rāġib wa ḏālika fī ăl muḥarrami min sanaẗi 
 <lb n="16"/>ĭṯnatay wa ḫamsīna wa ṯalāṯi miʾaẗ:in ʾaqarra baqāmu bi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi bi sarāḥa sirāǧa širāǧa bni danīla daniyala fa kataba ʿan hu ʿumaru bnu mūsà bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="18"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ǧabrayala ǧabrayla ǧabrīla ǧibrīla bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi wa ditūzu bnu ʾaḥmada wa kataba ʿalay hi Τιτιυ**  
 <lb n="19"/>šahida ʾismāʿīlu bnu ʿabdi ăl qāhiri ʿalà ʾiqrāri hāʾulāʾi ăn nafari ăl musammawna fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the Merciful the Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Sarāḥ son of Daniyal bought from Baqām son of Damiyani, from among the residents of Ṭuṭūn in the District of the Fayyūm.
			<lb n="3"/>
		He bought from him the house which belongs to him, east of the residence of Sarāḥ son of Daniyal, with its boundary and its boundaries, and below it and above it,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and inside and outside of it. The southern boundary is the residence of the heirs of Mūnah the Deaf. Its northern boundary is the house which
			<lb n="5"/>
		belongs to  Baqām son of Damiyani. Its eastern boundary is the residence of the heirs of Kayl son of Abamālah. Its western boundary is the residence of Sarāḥ son of
			<lb n="6"/>
		Daniyal. He bought that from him for two dinars and a sixth, minted gold of full, new weight. Baqām
			<lb n="7"/>
		son of Damiyani has taken (lit. &#034;with the hands&#034;) the price without any remainder and in full. And he has removed himself from the house described in this document. And he delivered
			<lb n="8"/>
		that to Sarāḥ son of Daniyal. He took it, and he took possession of it, and he took ownership of it, and that has become part if his property,
			<lb n="9"/>
		possessed out of his right of possession. If he wishes he may sell, and if he wishes he may build, and if he wishes he may reside. There is not belonging to Baqām son of Damiyani in
			<lb n="10"/>
		this house, after this recording, any claim and no demand, not for any cause
			<lb n="11"/>
		and not for any reason. He sold that according to the stipulation of the sale of Islam and its contract. And whatever there may be by way of a claim for an attachment, or
			<lb n="12"/>
		a right, or should someone come adventitiously because of a loan, the execution of that and its clearance will be the obligation of Baqām son of Damiyani for the worth to which it amounts, out of
			<lb n="13"/>
		his clear property. Testimony was given to the affirmation of Baqām son of Damiyani to all that is in this document, after it was read
			<lb n="14"/>
		to him in Arabic and explained to him in the foreign language, being of sound mind and body and his actions legal, being willing,
			<lb n="15"/>
		without being averse, not being compelled, not being treated injustly, being the petitioner and the one desiring. And that is in Muḥarram of the year
			<lb n="16"/>
		two and fifty and three hundred. [vacat] (2d hand) Baqām agreed with Sarāḥ son of Daniyal to that which is in this document. ʿU(mar son of) Mūsā wrote on his behalf with his hand on its date.
			<lb n="18"/>
		(3d hand) ʿAlī son of Jabrayal bore witness to all that which is in this document and he wrote with his hand. (4th hand) And Ditūz son of Aḥmad and he wrote on his behalf Titiu....
			<lb n="19"/>
		(5th hand) Ismaʿīl son of ʿAbd al-Qāhir testified respecting the affirmation of these persons named in this document and he wrote wiht his hand on its date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
