<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1006" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_38" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 038</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_38</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168903</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لرّحمن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحيم</supplied> 
<lb n="2"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">هـ</supplied>ـذا ما أصدق إسـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمعپل</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مولى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أحمد</supplied> بن مروان القر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شـ</supplied>ـي بمدينة أشمون عايشة 
<lb n="3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ابـ</supplied>ـنت يوسف السّا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كنة</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عند</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ما</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">خطبهـ</supplied>ـا إلى نفسها وهـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـي</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>مرأة أيّم بالغ بعد أن فوّ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ضت</supplied> 
<lb n="4"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أمـ</supplied>ـرها إلى جدّهـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـا</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يعقوب</supplied> بن إسحق الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>أشهـ<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـدت</unclear> له شهود 
<lb n="5"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بتـ</supplied>ـوكيلها إيّاه فقبل و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كالتهـ</supplied>ـا وأنفـ<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـذ</unclear> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نكاحها</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وأصـ</supplied>ـدقها إسمعپل مولى 
<lb n="6"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>حمد بن مروان القرشي أربعة دنانير مثاقيل طرا جياد وازنة يعجّل لها 
<lb n="7"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إ</supplied>سمعپل دينرين مثقالين نقدا حالّا معجّلا ويبقى لعا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يشـ</supplied>ـة ابنت يوسف 
<lb n="8"/>  على زوجها إسمعپل مولى أحمد بن مروان دينرين موحرپن إلى خـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمسة</supplied> سنين 
<lb n="9"/>  أوّلهم شهر ربيع الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـأوّل</supplied> سنة تسع وخمسين ومائتن وشرط إسمعپل مولى 
<lb n="10"/>  أحمد بن مروان لامرأته عائشة تقوى اللّه العظيم بحسن الصّحبة والمعاشرة 
<lb n="11"/>  كما أمر اللّه عز وجل وسنّة محمّد صلّى اللّه عليه وسلّم على 
<lb n="12"/>  الإمساك بالمعروف أو التّسريح بالإحسان وشرط إسمعپل 
<lb n="13"/>  مولى أحمد أن كل امرأة يتزوّجها على امرأته عائشة ابنت يوسف 
<lb n="14"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">تقـ</supplied>ـام تلك المرأة بيد عائشة تطلّق كيف <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شـ</supplied>ـاپ من الطّلاق 
<lb n="15"/>  وولي عقدة هذا النّكاح يعقوب بن إسحق فقبل الوكالة وأنفذ 
<lb n="16"/>  النّكاح ورضي إسمعپل بالمهر المعجّل والموحر والشّروط المسمّات 
<lb n="17"/>  في هذا الكتاب وألزم ذلك نفسه في صحّة عقله وبدنه وجواز 
<lb n="18"/>  أمره لا علّة به من مرض ولا عرّة في شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة تسع 
<lb n="19"/>  وخمسين ومائتن وشهـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> ذلك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ʾaṣdaqa ʾismāʿīlu mawlà ʾaḥmada bni marwāna ăl qurašiyyi bi madīnaẗi ʾušmūna ʿāyišaẗa 
 <lb n="3"/>ĭbnata yūsufa ăs sākinaẗa **** ʿinda mā ḫaṭaba hā ʾilà nafsi hā wa hiya ĭmraʾaẗ:un ʾayyim:un bāliġ:un baʿda ʾan fawwaḍat 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾamra hā ʾilà ǧaddi hā yaʿqūba bni ʾisḥāqa ăl **** wa ʾašhadat la hu šuhūd 
 <lb n="5"/>bi tawkīli hā ʾiyyā hu fa qabila wakālata hā wa ʾanfaḏa nikāḥa hā wa ʾaṣdaqa hā ʾismāʿīlu mawlà 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾaḥmada bni marwāna ăl qurašiyyi ʾarbaʿaẗa danānīra maṯāqīla ṭirāʾ:in ǧiyād:in wāzinaẗ:in yuʿaǧǧilu la hā 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾismāʿīlu dīnārayni miṯqālayni naqd:an ḥāll:an muʿaǧǧal:an wa yabqà li ĭbnati yūsufa 
 <lb n="8"/>ʿalà zawǧi hā ʾismāʿīla mawlà ʾaḥmada bni marwāna dīnārayni muʾaḫḫarayni ʾilà ḫamsaẗi sinīna 
 <lb n="9"/>ʾawwalu hum šahru rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa tisʿ:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni wa šaraṭa ʾismāʿīlu mawlà 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾaḥmada bni marwāna li ĭmraʾati hi ʿāʾišaẗa taqwà ăl lāhi ăl ʿaẓīmi bi ḥusni ăṣ ṣuḥbaẗi wa ăl muʿāšaraẗi 
 <lb n="11"/>kamā ʾamara ăl lāhu ʿazza wa ǧalla wa sunnaẗu muḥammad:in ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalay hi wa sallama ʿalà 
 <lb n="12"/>ăl ʾimsāki bi ăl maʿrūfi ʾawi ăt tasrīḥi bi ăl ʾiḥsāni wa šaraṭa ʾismāʿīlu 
 <lb n="13"/>mawlà ʾaḥmada ʾanna kulla ĭmraʾaẗ:in yatazawwaǧa hā ʿalà ĭmraʾati hi ʿāʾišaẗa ĭbnati yūsufa 
 <lb n="14"/>tuqāmu tilka ăl marʾaẗu bi yadi ʿāʾišaẗa tuṭalliqu kayfa šāʾat mina ăṭ ṭalāqi 
 <lb n="15"/>wa waliya ʿuqdaẗa hāḏā ăn nikāḥi yaʿqūbu bnu ʾisḥāqa fa qabila ăl wakālaẗa wa ʾanfaḏa 
 <lb n="16"/>ăn nikāḥa wa raḍiya ʾismāʿīlu bi ăl mahri ăl muʿaǧǧali wa ăl muʾaḫḫari wa ăš šurūṭi ăl musammāti 
 <lb n="17"/>fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ʾalzama ḏālika nafsa hu fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿaqli hi wa badani hi wa ǧawāzi 
 <lb n="18"/>ʾamri hi lā ʿillaẗa bi hi min maraḍ:in wa lā ʿurraẗ:un fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa tisʿ:in 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni wa šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes des Barmherzigen, Gütigen!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Dies ist das, was Ismāʿīl, der Schutzbefohlene des Aḥmad b. Marwān al-Quraši in der Stadt Ašmūn festgelegt hat als Brautgabe für ʿĀīša
		[Th]is is what Is[smaʿîl, freedman of Aḥmad] b. Marwân, the Qor[aiš]ite, in the town of Ašmûn, has stipulated as a nuptial gift to ʿÂʾiša,
			<lb n="3"/>
		[dau]ghter of Yûsuf, re[siding in the town of ... after that he had asked her personnally for her] hand in marriage, sh[e being an] unmarried adult woman, (and) after that she had transferred
		ibnat Yūsuf, wohnhaft in der Stadt Ašmūn, als er sie personlich um ihre Hand bat, und sie war eine unverheiratete, erwachsene Frau, (und) nachdem sie
			<lb n="4"/>
		her [aff]air to her paternal gandfather [Yaʿqûb] b. Isḥâq, the [.................. and] she had called witnesses for him
		ihre Angelegenheit ihrem Großvater (väterlicherseits) Yaʿqūb b. Isḥāq übertragen hatte. Uns sie liess Zeugen (ihre Bevollmächtigung) für ihn aussagen
			<lb n="5"/>
		in Hinblick darauf, dass sie ihn beauftragt hatte, (für sie zu handeln) und er stimmte zu, sie zu vertreten und hat ihre Heirat für gültig erklärt. Und Ismāʿīl
		[with respect to her having en]trusted him to act for her. He has, therefore, consented to represent her and has declared [her marriage] to be valable. And Ismaʿîl, freedman of
			<lb n="6"/>
		[A]ḥmad b. Marwân, the Qoraišite, has [stipu]lated as the nuptial gift to her four dînârs miṯqâlî, newly minted, good pieces, full weight, of which [I]smaʿîl is paying to her
		hat als Brautgabe für sie vier miṯqāl-Dīnār festgelegt, neu geschlagen, gute Stücke, volles Gewicht, von denen Ismāʿīl ihr
			<lb n="7"/>
		immediately two dînârs miṯqâlî as an immediate payment cash down, and there remain for ʿÂʾiša, daughter of Yûsuf,
		sofort zwei miṯqāl-Dīnār zahlt als sofortige Zahlung in bar, und damit bleiben für ʿĀīša ibnat Yūsuf
			<lb n="8"/>
		two dînârs to be paid to her by her husband Ismaʿîl, freedman of Aḥmad b. Marwân, ere the termination of fi[ve] years,
		zwei Dīnār von ihrem Ehemann Ismāʿīl, dem Schutzbefohlenen des Aḥmad b. Marwān, die bis auf fünf Jahre vertagt werden,
			<lb n="9"/>
		beginnend mit dem Monat Rabīʿ al-awwal des Jahres zweihundertsiebenundfünfzig. Und Ismāʿīl, der Schutzbefohlene des Aḥmad b. Marwān
		reckoning from the month of Rabîʿ [I] of the year two hundred and fifty seven. Ismaʿîl, freedman
			<lb n="10"/>
		of Aḥmad b. Marwân, undertakes in respect to his wife ʿÂʾiša to fear God, the most high, by making his relationship to and life with her pleasing,
		verspricht seiner Frau ʿĀīša, Gott den Erhabenen zu fürchten, indem er seine Beziehung zu ihr und das Leben mit ihr angenehm gestaltet
			<lb n="11"/>
		according to the ordinance of God - He is mighty and sublime - and to the rule of Muḥammad - may the blessing of God be upon him and may He preserve him, that
		wie Gott – er ist mächtig und erhaben – es befohlen hat und gemäß dem Brauch Muḥammads – Gott segne ihn und schenke ihm Heil – wobei er
			<lb n="12"/>
		she shall be kept in amenity or dismissed in kindness. Ismaʿîl,
		sie in rechtlicher Weise zurückhält oder in ordentlicher Weise freilässt. Und Ismāʿīl,
			<lb n="13"/>
		der Schutzbefohlene des Aḥmad, versprach, dass jede Frau, die er zu seiner Frau ʿĀīša (durch Heirat) hinzunimmt,
		freedman of Aḥmad, undertakes, that any woman besides his wife ʿÂʾiša, daughter of Yûsuf, whom he may marry,
			<lb n="14"/>
		[shall] be under the hand of ʿÂʾiša, (so that) she may dismiss her in whatever way she will.
		unter der Hand von ʿĀīša sein soll, so dass sie sie, wie auch immer sie will, verstossen kann.
			<lb n="15"/>
		Und Yaʿqūb b. Isḥāq wurde mit der Ausführung dieses Ehevertrages beauftragt, und er nahm den Auftrag an, und er erklärte für gültig
		Yaʿqûb b. Isḥâq has been entrusted with the carrying out of this contract of marriage and has consented to represent (the bride) and has declared
			<lb n="16"/>
		die Ehe. Und Ismāʿīl hat der Brautgabe zugestimmt, sowohl dem sofort fälligen Teil als auch dem ausstehenden und den genannten Bedingungen
		the marriage to be valable, and Ismaʿîl has agreed to the nuptial gift (both in respect to the part) immediately payable and (to the part) due at a later date and to the conditions named
			<lb n="17"/>
		in diesem Vertrag, und er verpflichtete sich dadurch bei gesundem Verstand und Körper und der Fähigkeit,
		in this contract, and he binds himself by it, he being in a state of sound mind and body and capable of transacting
			<lb n="18"/>
		his business, suffering from no bodily disease and no physical defect, in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred
		seine Angelegenheiten auszuführen; wobei er keine körperliche Krankheit und keinen physischen Mangel hat, im Monat Rabīʿ al-awwal des Jahres zweihundert-
			<lb n="19"/>
		and fifty nine. (The following witnesses) have testified to it.
		neunundfünfzig. (Die folgenden Zeugen) haben dies bezeugt.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
