<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="965" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_48" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 048 (= P.World p. 191 = Chrest.Khoury I 14)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_48</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113712</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1 recto"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2 recto"/>  ذكر حق <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يونة </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”">يونة</rdg></app> ابنت حليصى على زوجها يزيد بن قاسم 
<lb n="3 recto"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> عليه عشرة الدّنانير وزن المثاقيل الجديد عينا 
<lb n="4 recto"/>  ذهبا نقد جيّد وهذا العشرة الدّنانير حالّة 
<lb n="5 recto"/>  ليونة ابنت حليصى على زوجها يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخراز</rdg></app> 
<lb n="6 recto"/>  والعشرة الدّنانير بقيّة صداقها ومن قام بالذّكر الحق 
<lb n="7 recto"/>  اقتضاه ومن أحالت عليه أقر لها بحقّها شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="8 recto"/>  اليسع بن عيسى وهو كاتب الصّك وشهادته في انسلاخ 
<lb n="9 recto"/>  صفر سنة ثلث وثلثين ومائتن <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="10 recto"/>  وموسى بن هرون بن أبي هرون وكتب شهادته على يزيد <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في 
<lb n="11 recto"/>  هذا الصّك وشهادته في شهر ربيع الأوّل من سنة اثنين وثلثين ومائتين <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="12 recto"/>  شهد داود بن سليمن على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في 
<lb n="13 recto"/>  هذا الكتاب في شهر ربيع الأوّل من سنة ثلثة وثلثين ومائتن 
<lb n="14 recto"/>  شهد لقمان بن سليمن على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا 
<lb n="15 recto"/>  الكتاب وشهادته في انسلاخ صفر سنة ثلثة وثلثين <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”"><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">وماپپپن</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">ومائتين</rdg></app> 
<lb n="16 recto"/>  شهد اليسع بن عبد الوهّاب على إقرار يزيد <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="17 recto"/>  ‮في شهر ربيع الأوّل من سنة ثلثة وثلثين ومائتن ‪σλγ‬‬ 
<lb n="18 recto"/>  شهد عبد الكريم بن موسى على إقرار يزيد <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="19 recto"/>  ‮وعبد اللّه بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه سپه ‪σλγ‬‬ 
<lb n="20 recto"/>  وعبد الصّمد بن عبد الرّحمن بن إسمعيل وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="21 recto"/>  شهد رفاعة بن إسحق على يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في 
<lb n="22 recto"/>  هذا الكتاب وشهادته في شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة ثلثة وثلثين ومائتن 
<lb n="23 recto"/>  شهد يحيى بن صفوان المرادي على يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الجرّار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا 
<lb n="24 recto"/>  الصّك وشهادته في شهر ربيع الأوّل من سنة ثلثة وثلثين ومائتن 
<lb n="25 recto"/>  شهد مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـحمّـ</supplied>ـد بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">جزى </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">جزىّ </rdg><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">جزى </rdg><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">حرّىّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الـ<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـإبريّ</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الأزدى</rdg></app> على يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا الصّك وشهادته في صفر سنة ثلثة 
<lb n="26 recto"/>  وثلثين ومائتن 
<lb n="27 recto"/>  شهد عبد الرّحمن بن عبّاس بن عبد الرّحن بن سلام القرشي على إقرار يزيد بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="28 recto"/>  وعبد اللّه بن زكري وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="29 recto"/>  شهد عبد الـ<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـلّه</unclear> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">بن</unclear> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">الحجّاج</unclear> على إقرار يزيد الدّبّاغ بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="30 recto"/>  في ذي الحجّة سنة خمس وأربعين ومائتين <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> وأحمد بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطه 
<lb n="31 recto"/>  وعبد الصّمد بن هرون وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="32 recto"/>  وحميد بن عبيد وكتب شهادته بيده بجميع ما في هاذا 
<lb n="33 recto"/>  الكتاب وعمر بن محمّد بن عمران وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> في شوّال سنة خمس 
<lb n="34 recto"/>  <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">وأربعين</supplied> ومائتن 
<lb n="35 recto right margin"/>  وحسين بن علي الخراساني وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">الخرّاز</rdg></app> بجميع ما في هذا الصّك وعيسى بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="36 verso"/>  وعلي بن مومل وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم الدّبّاغ 
<lb n="37 verso"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الصّك ومحمّد بن مومل وكتب 
<lb n="38 verso"/>  شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> ومحمّد بن أحمد وكتب 
<lb n="39 verso"/>  شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> وحاتم بن المسيّب وكتب 
<lb n="40 verso"/>  شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> وعبد اللّه بن محمّد 
<lb n="41 verso"/>  بن علي وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="42 verso"/>  ومسرور بن ميمون وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="43 verso"/>  وعلي بن حسين بن عـ<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـليّ</unclear> الخراساني وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="44 verso top"/>  كتاب 
<lb n="45 verso top"/>  فيه صداق يونه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ḏikru ḥaqqi yūnaẗa yūnaha ĭbnati ḥilīṣà ʿalà zawǧi hā yazīda bni qāsim:ini 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi ʿalay hi ʿašaraẗu ăd danānīri wazna ăl maṯāqīli ăl ǧadīda ʿayn:an 
 <lb n="4"/>ḏahab:an naqd ǧayyid wa hāḏā ăl ʿašaraẗu ăd danānīri ḥāllaẗ:un 
 <lb n="5"/>li yūnaha ĭbnati ḥilīṣà ʿalà zawǧi hā yazīda bni ăl qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi 
 <lb n="6"/>wa ăl ʿašaraẗu ăd danānīri baqiyyaẗu ṣadāqi hā wa man qāma bi ăḏ ḏikri ăl ḥaqqa 
 <lb n="7"/>ĭqtaḍā hu wa man ʾaḥālat ʿalay hi ʾaqarra la hā bi ḥaqqi hā šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl yasaʿu bnu ʿīsà wa huwa kātibu ăṣ ṣakki wa šahādatu hu fī ĭnsilāḫi 
 <lb n="9"/>ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni * 
 <lb n="10"/>wa mūsà bnu hārūna bni ʾabī hārūna wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà yazīda ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="11"/>hāḏā ăṣ ṣakki wa šahādatu hu fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ĭṯnayni wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni * 
 <lb n="12"/>šahida dāwūdu bnu sulaymāna ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="13"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatay 
 <lb n="14"/>šahida luqmānu bnu sulaymāna ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā 
 <lb n="15"/>ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ĭnsilāḫi ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ṯalāṯīna ø wa ø miʾatayni 
 <lb n="16"/>šahida ăl yasaʿu bnu ʿabdi ăl wahhābi ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="17"/>fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 233 
 <lb n="18"/>šahida ʿabdu ăl karīmi bnu mūsà ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * sanaẗa 233 
 <lb n="20"/>wa ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi bnu ʿabdi ăr raḥmāni bni ʾismāʿīla wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="21"/>šahida rifāʿaẗu bnu ʾisḥāqa ʿalà yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="22"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗi ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="23"/>šahida yaḥyà bnu ṣafwāna ăl murādiyyu ʿalà yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā 
 <lb n="24"/>ăṣ ṣakki wa šahādatu hu fī šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="25"/>šahida muḥammadu bnu ḥarriyy:ini ǧazī ǧurayy:ini ǧuzayy:ini ăl ʾibriyyu ʾazdiyyu ʿalà yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăṣ ṣakki wa šahādatu hu fī ṣafar:in sanaẗa ṯalāṯaẗ:in 
 <lb n="26"/>wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="27"/>šahida ʿabdu ăr raḥmāni bnu ʿabbāsa bni ʿabdi ăr raḥmāni bni salāma ăl qurašiyyu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="28"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu zakariya zikrī wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi * 
 <lb n="29"/>šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu ăl ḥaǧǧāǧi ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda ăd dabbāġi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi * 
 <lb n="30"/>fī ḏī ăl ḥiǧǧaẗi sanaẗa ḫams:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni * wa ʾaḥmadu bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="31"/>wa ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi bnu hārūna wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="32"/>ḥamīdu ḥumaydu bnu ʿubayd:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi yadi hi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā 
 <lb n="33"/>ăl kitābi wa ʿumaru bnu muḥammadi bni ʿimrāna wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi fī šawwāl:in sanaẗa ḫams:in 
 <lb n="34"/>wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="35"/>wa ḥusaynu bnu ʿaliyy:ini ăl ḫurāsāniyyu wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăṣ ṣakki wa ʿīsà bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="36"/>wa ʿaliyyu bnu muʾammal:in wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini ăd dabbāġi 
 <lb n="37"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăṣ ṣakki wa muḥammadu bnu muʾammal:in wa kataba 
 <lb n="38"/>šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * wa muḥammadu bnu ʾaḥmada wa kataba 
 <lb n="39"/>šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * wa ḥātimu bnu ăl musayyabi wa kataba 
 <lb n="40"/>šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu muḥammadi 
 <lb n="41"/>bni ʿaliyy:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="42"/>wa masrūru bnu maymūn:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="43"/>wa ʿaliyyu bnu ḥusayni bni ʿaliyy:ini ăl ḫurāsāniyyu wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="44"/>kitāb:un 
 <lb n="45"/>fī hi ṣadāqu yūnaha 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Au nom de Dieu clément et miséricordieux !
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!
			<lb n="2"/>
		Lettre d&#039;obligation établissant le droit de Yūna fille de Ḥelīṣa sur son mari Yazīd Ibn Qāsim,
		Record of what is due to Yûna, daughter of Helîṣâ, from her husband Yazîd b. Qâsim,
			<lb n="3"/>
		fabricant de seaux en cuir; il lui doit dix dīnārs pesés nouvellement en miṯqāl-s, en pièces
		the leather-bottle merchant; he owes ten dînârs of new standard-weight gold-
			<lb n="4"/>
		coins, good pieces and these ten dînârs fall due
		d&#039;or, en bons étalons monétaires; et ces dix dīnārs sont payables
			<lb n="5"/>
		à Yūna fille de Ḥelīṣā, à la charge de son mari Yazīd Ibn Qāsim, fabricant de seaux en cuir;
		to the credit of Yûna, daughter of Helîṣâ, to the debit of her husband Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant;
			<lb n="6"/>
		and the ten dînârs are the remainder of her nuptial gift, and whoever presents himself with (this) written obligation
		et les dix dīnārs sont le reste de sa dot; quiconque apparaît avec la lettre d&#039;obligation,
			<lb n="7"/>
		en reçoit (le montant); et celui à qui elle renvoie, lui reconnaît sa revendication. Ont témoigné de cela
		shall receive (its amount), and he to whom she cedes (the bill) thereby recognizes her right (to obtain payment). (The following witnesses) have testified to it:
			<lb n="8"/>
		Al-Yasaʿ b. ʿÎsâ, who is the writer of the bill, and his testimony has been given on the last of
		Al-Yasaʿ Ibn ʿĪsā, qui est le scribe de ce titre d&#039;obligation et dont le témoignage eut lieu à la fin
			<lb n="9"/>
		Ṣafar of the year two hundred and thirty three. (Paragraph sign).
		de ṣafar de l&#039;année deux cent trente-trois,
			<lb n="10"/>
		And Mûsâ b. Hârûn b. Abî Hârûn, who has written his testimony to the obligation of Yazîd, the leather-bottle merchant, with regard to all that (is contained) in
		et Mūsā Ibn Hārūn Ibn Abī Hārūn, qui écrivit son témoignage concernant Yazīd le fabricant de seaux en cuir, par rapport à tout le contenu de
			<lb n="11"/>
		ce titre d&#039;obligation, son témoignage eut lieu au mois de rabīʿ I de l&#039;année deux sent trente-deux.
		this bill, and his testimony has been given in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred and thirty two. (Handmark).
			<lb n="12"/>
		A témoigné Dāwūd Ibn Sulaymān de la reconnaissance de Yazīd Ibn Qāsim, le fabricant de seaux en cuir, de tout de qui est dans
		Dâwûd b. Sulaimân is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in
			<lb n="13"/>
		ce document, au mois de rabīʿ I de l&#039;année deux cent trente-trois.
		this act in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred and thirty three.
			<lb n="14"/>
		Luqmân b. Sulaimân is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in this
			<lb n="15"/>
		act, and his testimony has been given on the last of Ṣafar of the year (two hundred) and thirty three.
			<lb n="16"/>
		Al-Yasaʿ b. ʿAbd al-Wahhâb is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in this act,
			<lb n="17"/>
		in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred and thirty three 233.
			<lb n="18"/>
		ʿAbd al-Karîm b. Mûsâ is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in this act.
			<lb n="19"/>
		And ʿAbdallâh b. Mûsâ, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting (in the) year 233.
			<lb n="20"/>
		And ʿAbd aṣ-Ṣamad b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. Ismaʿîl, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting. (Pentagramm).
		And ʿAbd aṣ-Ṣamad b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. Ismâʿîl, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting. (Pentagramm).
			<lb n="21"/>
		Rifâʿa b. Isḥâq is witness to the obligation of Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in
			<lb n="22"/>
		this act, and his testimony has been given in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred and thirty three.
			<lb n="23"/>
		Yaḥyâ b. Ṣafwân, the Murâdite, is witness to the obligation of Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all that (is contained) in this
			<lb n="24"/>
		bill and his testimony has been given in the month of Rabîʿ I of the year two hundred and thirty three.
			<lb n="25"/>
		Mu[ḥamm]ad b. Gurayy, the needle-maker, is witness to the obligation of Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting (all) that (is contained) in this bill, and his testimony has been given on Ṣafar of the year
		Mu[ḥamm]ad b. Ǧurayy, the needle-maker, is witness to the obligation of Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting (all) that (is contained) in this bill, and his testimony has been given on Ṣafar of the year
			<lb n="26"/>
		two hundred and thirty three.
			<lb n="27"/>
		ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. ʿAbbâs b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. Salâm, the Qorashit, is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd respecting all that (is contained) in this act. 
		ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. ʿAbbâs b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. Salâm, the Qorašite, is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd respecting all that (is contained) in this act.
			<lb n="28"/>
		And ʿAbdallâh b. Zakariya, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd respecting all that (is contained) in this act. (Handmark).
			<lb n="29"/>
		ʿAbdallâh b. al-Ḥaǧǧāǧ is witness to the acknowledgment by Yazîd, the tanner, respecting all that (is contained) in this act (Handmark),
			<lb n="30"/>
		in Dhuʾl-Ḥigga of the year two hundred and forty five. And Aḥmad b. Mûsâ and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
		in Ḏuʾl-Ḥiǧǧa of the year two hundred and forty five. And Aḥmad b. Mûsâ and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="31"/>
		And ʿAbd aṣ-Ṣamad b. Harûn, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting
		And ʿAbd aṣ-Ṣamad b. Hârûn, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting
			<lb n="32"/>
		And Ḥumaid b. ʿUbaid - and he has written his testimony with his (own) hand - concerning all that (is contained) in this
		And Ḥumaid b. ʿUbaid - and he has written his testimony with his (own) hand - respecting all that (is contained) in this
			<lb n="33"/>
		act. And ʿUmar b. Muḥammad b. ʿImrân, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, in Shawwâl of the year two
		act. And ʿUmar b. Muḥammad b. ʿImrân is witness, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, in Šawwâl of the year two
			<lb n="34"/>
		hundred and &lt;forty&gt; five.
		hundred and forty five.
			<lb n="35"/>
		And Ḥusain b. ʿAlî, originating from Khurâsân, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all, that (is contained) in this bill. And ʿÎsâ b. Mûsâ, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
		And Ḥusain b. ʿAlî, originating from Ḫurâsân, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the leather-bottle merchant, respecting all, that (is contained) in this bill. And ʿÎsâ b. Mûsâ, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="36"/>
		And ʿAlî b. Muʾammal, and he has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim, the tanner,
			<lb n="37"/>
		respecting all that (is contained) in this bill. And Muḥammad b. Muʾammal, and he has written
			<lb n="38"/>
		his testimony in his (own) handwriting. And Muḥammad b. Aḥmad, and he has written
			<lb n="39"/>
		his testimony in his (own) handwriting. And Ḥâtim b. al-Musayyab, and he has written
			<lb n="40"/>
		his testimony in his (own) handwriting. And ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad
			<lb n="41"/>
		b. ʿAlî, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="42"/>
		And Masrûr b. Maimûn, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="43"/>
		And ʿAlî b. Ḥusain b. ʿAlî, originating from Khurâsân, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting. (Hexagram).
		And ʿAlî b. Ḥusain b. ʿAlî, originating from Ḫurâsân, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting. (Hexagram).
			<lb n="44"/>
		Document
			<lb n="45"/>
		containing the nuptial gift of Yûna.
		contenant la dot de Yūna.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
