<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1037" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_56" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 056</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_56</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168920</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="recto 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="recto 2"/>  هذا ما اشترت يونه ابنت حليصا اشترت من زوجها يزيد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الخرّاز </lem><rdg resp="APD">الخرّاز</rdg></app> منزل له في علا 
<lb n="recto 3"/>  مدينة إدفوا بما غلق عليه بابه وأحاطت به جدرانه داخل فيه وخارج منه بجميع حقوقه وحدوده 
<lb n="recto 4"/>  وأرضه وسمائه وأركانه الأربع جماعة هذا المنزل حدّه القبلي منزل سواد بن بقونس الدّبّاغ ومعصرة النّضر الزّيّات 
<lb n="recto 5"/>  وأشراكه حدّه الغربي منزل بلتوس الطّبيب والممر بينهما وحدّه البحري يلي منزل قيس 
<lb n="recto 6"/>  بن هرون النّجّار والممر بينهما وحدّه الشّرقي يلي منزل سواد الحرّاث وباب هذا 
<lb n="recto 7"/>  المنزل مفتوح إلى البحري اشترت يونه ابنت حليصا من زوجها يزيد الدّبّاغ هذا 
<lb n="recto 8"/>  المنزل المحدود الموصوف في هذا الكتاب بجميع حقوقه وحدوده بدينر وزن 
<lb n="recto 9"/>  <del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">الڤاسم</del> <del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">حدوده</del> <del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">وحده</del> المثاقيل الجديد قد نقدت يونه ابنت حليصا زوجها يزيد الدّبّاغ 
<lb n="recto 10"/>  الدّينر ثمن المنزل وسلّم يزيد الدّبّاغ إلى زوجته يونه ابنت حليصا المنزل كلّه 
<lb n="recto 11"/>  بجميع حقوقه وحدوده ومرافقه وأبرته يونه ابنت حليصا من الدّينر وقبضت 
<lb n="recto 12"/>  يونه المنزل وصار مال من مالها وفي <sic n="superfluous">ملپكپها</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ملكها</supplied> بالثّمن المسمّا في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="recto 13"/>  وهو دينر مثقال بعد تعرّف من يونه ابنت حليصا بما اشترت قبل الاشترا 
<lb n="recto 14"/>  ومعرفة من يزيد الدّبّاغ بما باع قبل البيع وتعرّفهما جميعا بما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="recto 15"/>  بعد البيع عن تراض فإن لحق يونه ابنت حليصا درك من أحد من النّاس فعلى يزيد 
<lb n="recto 16"/>  الدّبّاغ <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">إ</supplied>نقاذ </lem><rdg resp="“Frantz-Murphy; Diem”">نفاذ</rdg></app> بيعه وخلاصه على بيع الإسلم <sic n="superfluous">وعهدپة</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">وعهده</supplied> الإسلم شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="recto 17"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إلپشع </lem><rdg resp="“Littmann”">إلپشع</rdg></app> بن عيسى وهو كاتب الكتاب وشهادته في ذي القعدة سنة تسع وثلثين ومائتن 
<lb n="recto 18"/>  وعلي بن عبد الأعلى بن معوية وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 19"/>  وعبد اللّه بن زكري وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 20"/>  شهد أحمد بن محمّد القيسي بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="recto 21"/>  وعبد الأعلى بن معوية بن عبد الأعلى وكتب شهادته على يزيد الدّبّاغ وعلى إقرار يونه بالقبض والدّفع 
<lb n="recto 22"/>  وشهدته في ذي القعدة سنة تسع وثلثين ومائتين 
<lb n="recto 23"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وعبّاب </lem><rdg resp="APD">وغيّاث </rdg><rdg resp="APD">وعباب </rdg><rdg resp="APD">وعبّاب </rdg><rdg resp="APD">وعتّاب </rdg><rdg resp="APD">وعنّاب</rdg></app> بن محمّد بن مراد وكتب شهادته بيده على إقرار 
<lb n="recto 24"/>  يزيد بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="recto 25"/>  شهد على <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ذلك</unclear> عبد اللّه بن الحجّاج بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وشهادته في ذي القعدة 
<lb n="recto 26"/>  سنة تسع وثلثين ومائتن // وعبد الأوّل بن عبد العزيز وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 27"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="recto 28"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="recto 29"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="recto 30"/>  وهرون بن إسحق وكتب شهادته بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="recto 31"/>  وعبد الصّمد بن هرون وكتب شهادته بخطّه // 
<lb n="recto 32"/>  وحميد بن <sic n="superfluous">پن</sic> عبيد وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 33"/>  وأحمد بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 34"/>  وعيسى بن موسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="recto 35"/>  وحسين بن علي الخراساني وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد بن قاسم 
<lb n="recto 36"/>  الدّبّاغ بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب شهادته بخطّه // 
<lb n="recto 37"/>  علي بن مومل وكتب شهادته على إقرار يزيد 
<lb n="recto 38"/>  بن قاسم الدّبّاغ بجميع ما في 
<lb n="recto 39"/>  هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="recto 40"/>  بخطّه 
<lb n="verso 1"/>  فيه كتاب منزل يونه ابنت حليصا 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarat yūnahu ĭbnatu ḥalīṣā ĭštarat min zawǧi hā yazīda ăl ǧarrāri ḫarrāzi manzil la hu fī ʿulā 
 <lb n="3"/>madīnaẗi ʾidfū bi mā ġalaqa ʿalay hi bābu hu wa ʾaḥāṭat bi hi ǧudrānu hu dāḫil fī hi wa ḫāriǧ min hu bi ǧamīʿi ḥuqūqi hi wa ḥudūdi hi 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ʾarḍi hi wa samāʾi hi wa ʾarkāni hi ăl ʾarbaʿi ǧamāʿaẗu hāḏā ăl manzili ḥaddu hu ăl qibliyyu manzilu sawādi bni baqawnisa ăd dabbāġi wa miʿṣaraẗu ăn naḍri ăz zayyāti 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ʾašrāki hi ḥaddu hu ăl ġarbiyyu manzilu bilatūsa ăṭ ṭabībi wa ăl mamarru bayna humā wa ḥaddu hu ăl baḥriyyu yalī manzila qaysi 
 <lb n="6"/>bni hārūna ăn naǧǧāri wa ăl mamarru bayna humā wa ḥaddu hu ăš šarqiyyu yalī manzila sawādi ăl ḥarrāṯi wa bābu hāḏā 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl manzili maftūḥ:un ʾilà ăl baḥriyyi ĭštarat yūnahu ĭbnatu ḥalīṣā min zawǧi hā yazīda ăd dabbāġi hāḏā 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl manzila ăl maḥdūda ăl mawṣūfa fī hāḏā ăl kitābi bi ǧamīʿi ḥuqūqi hi wa ḥudūdi hi bi dīnār:in wazni 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl maṯāqīli ăl ǧadīdi qad naqadat yūnahu ĭbnatu ḥalīṣā zawǧa hā yazīda ăd dabbāġa 
 <lb n="10"/>ăd dīnāra ṯamana ăl manzili wa sallama yazīdu ăd dabbāġu ʾilà zawǧati hi yūnaha ĭbnati ḥalīṣā ăl manzila kulla hu 
 <lb n="11"/>bi ǧamīʿi ḥuqūqi hi wa ḥudūdi hi wa marāfiqi hi wa ʾabrat hu yūnahu ĭbnatu ḥalīṣā mina ăd dīnāri wa qabaḍat 
 <lb n="12"/>yūnahu ăl manzila wa ṣāra māl min māli hā wa fī milki hā bi ăṯ ṯamani ăl musammā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="13"/>wa huwa dīnār:un miṯqāl:un baʿda taʿarruf:in min yūnaha ĭbnati ḥalīṣā bi mā ĭštarat qabla ăli ĭštirāʾi 
 <lb n="14"/>wa maʿrifaẗ:in min yazīda ăd dabbāġi bi mā bāʿa qabla ăl bayʿi wa taʿarrufi himā ǧamīʿ:an bi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="15"/>baʿda ăl bayʿi ʿan tarāḍ:in fa ʾin laḥiqa yūnaha ĭbnata ḥalīṣā darak:un min ʾaḥad:in mina ăn nāsi fa ʿalà yazīda 
 <lb n="16"/>ăd dabbāġi ʾinqāḏu nafāḏu bayʿi hi wa ḫalāṣi hi ʿalà bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdaẗi ăl ʾislāmi šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="17"/>ăl ø ʾilīšaʿu yasaʿu bnu ʿīsà wa huwa kātibu ăl kitābi wa šahādati hi fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗa tisʿ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl ʾaʿlà bni muʿāwiyaẗa wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu zakariya zikrī wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu muḥammad:ini ăl qaysiyyu bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba * 
 <lb n="21"/>wa ʿabdu ăl ʾaʿlà bnu muʿāwiyaẗa bni ʿabdi ăl ʾaʿlà wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà yazīda ăd dabbāġi wa ʿalà ʾiqrāri yūnaha bi ăl qabḍi wa ăd dafʿi 
 <lb n="22"/>wa šahādata hu fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗa tisʿ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="23"/>wa ʿabābu ʿabbābu ʿannābu ʿattābu ġayyāṯu ġiyāṯu bnu muḥammadi bni murād:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi yadi hi ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="24"/>yazīda bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi * 
 <lb n="25"/>šahida ʿalà ḏālika ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu ăl ḥaǧǧāǧi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šahādatu hu fī ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi 
 <lb n="26"/>sanaẗa tisʿ:in wa ṯalāṯīna wa miʾatayni // wa ʿabdu ăl ʾawwali bnu ʿabdi ăl ʿazīzi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="27"/>*** 
 <lb n="28"/>*** 
 <lb n="29"/>*** 
 <lb n="30"/>wa hārūnu bnu ʾisḥāqa wa kataba šahādata hu bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi * 
 <lb n="31"/>wa ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi bnu hārūna wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭa hi // 
 <lb n="32"/>wa ḥamīdu bnu ʿubayd:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="33"/>wa ʾaḥmadu bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="34"/>wa ʿīsà bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="35"/>wa ḥusaynu bnu ʿaliyy:ini ăl ḫurāsāniyyu wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda bni qāsim:ini 
 <lb n="36"/>ăd dabbāġi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi // 
 <lb n="37"/>ʿaliyyu bnu muʾammal:in wa kataba šahādata hu ʿalà ʾiqrāri yazīda 
 <lb n="38"/>bni qāsim:ini ăd dabbāġi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī 
 <lb n="39"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="40"/>bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="41"/>fī hi kitābu manzili yūnaha ĭbnati ḥalīṣā 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, has bought: she has bought from her husband Yazîd, the leather-bottle merchant, a dwelling house belonging to him, in the upper part of
			<lb n="3"/>
		the town of Edfû, with what its door encloses and its wall(s) encompass (both) within and without, with all the rights and boundaries thereof,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and its land and its sky and its four corners. The southern boundary of this dwelling house is (formed) in its entirety (by) the dewlling house of Sawâd b. Baqaunis, the tanner, and the press of an-Naḍr, the oilseller,
			<lb n="5"/>
		and his fellow holders; its western boundary is (formed by) the dwelling house of Pilatos, the physician, and the passage between them both; and its northern boundary borders on the dwelling house of Qais
			<lb n="6"/>
		b. Harûn, the carpenter, and the passage between them both; and the eastern boundary borders on the dwelling house of Sawâd, the ploughman, and the door of this
			<lb n="7"/>
		dwelling house opens to the north. Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, has bought from her husband Yazîd, the tanner, this
			<lb n="8"/>
		dwelling house, defined and described in this contract, with all its rights and boundaries, for one dînâr, according to
			<lb n="9"/>
		the new (standard) weight of the miṯqâls. Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, has paid to her husband Yazîd, the tanner,
			<lb n="10"/>
		the dînâr as the price for the dwelling house, and Yazîd, the tanner, has handed over to his wife Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, the dwelling house in its entirety,
			<lb n="11"/>
		with all its rights and boundaries and appurtenances, and Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, has given him a quittance for the dînâr, and Yûna
			<lb n="12"/>
		has taken over the dwelling house and it has become her own property and (has come) into her possession for the price named in this contract,
			<lb n="13"/>
		and this is one dînâr miṯqâlî, after that Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, had taken cognizance of that which she has bought before the purchase,
			<lb n="14"/>
		and (after) the cognizance of Yazîd, the tanner, in respect to that which he has sold before the sale; and (after) they both have taken cognizance of all that (is contained) in this act
			<lb n="15"/>
		after the sale, on the ground of their (mutual) consent. But if any evil consequence (therefrom, vindicatio) should befall Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ, from any other person, then the
			<lb n="16"/>
		recuperation for its sale and its indemnification are incumbent upon Yazîd, the tanner, according to Islamic law of sale and Islamic deed of sale. There have testified to it:
			<lb n="17"/>
		Al-Yasaʿ b. ʿÎsâ, who is the writer of the document, and his testimony has been given in Ḏu ʾl-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty nine.
			<lb n="18"/>
		And ʿAlî b. ʿAbd al-Aʿlâ b. Muʿâwiya, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="19"/>
		And ʿAbdallâh b. Zakariya, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
		And ʿAbdallâh b. Zikrî, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Aḥmad b. Muḥammad al-Qaisî, is witness respecting all that (is contained) in this act, and he has written. (Paragraph sign).
			<lb n="21"/>
		And ʿAbd al-Aʿlâ b. Muʿâwiya b. ʿAbd al-Aʿlâ, who has written his testimony with regard to Yazîd, the tanner, and to  the acknowledgment by Yûna respecting the receipt and the delivery,
			<lb n="22"/>
		and his testimony (has been given) in Ḏu ʾl-Qaʿda of the year two hundred and thirty nine.
			<lb n="23"/>
		And Ġiyâṯ b. Muḥammad b. Murâd, who has written his testimony with his (own) hand to the acknowledgment
			<lb n="24"/>
		by Yazîd of all that (is contained) in this act. (Paragraph sign).
			<lb n="25"/>
		ʿAbdallâh b. al-Ḥaǧǧâǧ has been witness to it respecting all that (is contained) in this act, and his testimony (has been given) in Ḏu ʾl-Qaʿda
			<lb n="26"/>
		of the year two hundred and thirty nine. And ʿAbd al-Awwal b. ʿAbd al-ʿAzîz, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="27"/>
		(In Coptic) I Moses Aron am witness to ...
			<lb n="28"/>
			<lb n="29"/>
			<lb n="30"/>
		And Hârûn b. Isḥâq, who has written his testimony in respect of all that (is contained) in this act. (Handmark).
			<lb n="31"/>
		And ʿAbd aṣ-Ṣamad b. Hârûn, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="32"/>
		And Ḥamîd b. ʿUbaid, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="33"/>
		And Aḥmad b. Mûsâ, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="34"/>
		And ʿÎsâ b. Mûsâ, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="35"/>
		And Ḥusain b. ʿAlî, the Ḫurâsânî, who has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd b. Qâsim,
			<lb n="36"/>
		the tanner, respecting all that (is contained) in this act, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="37"/>
		ʿAlî b. Muʾammal, who has written his testimony to the acknowledgment by Yazîd
			<lb n="38"/>
		b. Qâsim, the tanner, respecting all that (is contained) in
			<lb n="39"/>
		this act
			<lb n="40"/>
		in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="41"/>
		Herein is the act concerning the dwelling house of Yûna, daughter of Ḥelîṣâ.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
