<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="355" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_140" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 140</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_140</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106585</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  شهد من أثبت اسمه آخره أنّهم يعرفون كفيّة البكر البالغ ابنة خلبوص بن سليم 
<lb n="3"/>  المقيم ببيهمول معرفة صحيحة شرعية ويشهدون أنّها بكر بالغ صحيحة <sic n="superfluous">صحپحه</sic> العقل والبدن 
<lb n="4"/>  خالية من موانع النّكاح وأن والدها المذكور مستحق الولاية عليها أهلا لتلك وأن الرّاغب 
<lb n="5"/>  في تزويجها مُحَسِّن بن أبي الزّهر بن شمخ كفوا لها وضمن بذلك على فور وذلك 
<lb n="6"/>  تأريخ الخامس عشر من جمادى الآخرة سنة إحدى وأربعين وستّمائة 
<lb n="7 right"/>  شهد بذلك 
<lb n="8 right"/>  عمر بن عبد العزيز بن معز 
<lb n="9 right"/>  حال 
<lb n="10 right"/>  عشرين دينارا 
<lb n="7 middle"/>  شهد بذلك 
<lb n="8 middle"/>  علي بن عبد اللّه بن محمّد 
<lb n="9 middle"/>  موحر 
<lb n="10 middle"/>  ستّين دينارا 
<lb n="9 left"/>  في سلخ كل سنة 
<lb n="10 left"/>  ستّة دنانير 
<lb n="11"/>  عقد بولاية أبيها المذكور الزّوج المذكور على الصّداق المذكور في التّأريخ المذكور 
<lb n="12 right"/>  حضرت ذلك 
<lb n="13 right"/>  وكتب أحمد بن الحسن بن <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="14 right"/>  تم 
<lb n="12 middle"/>  حضرت ذلك 
<lb n="13 middle"/>  كتبه علب بن طاهر بن أحمد 
<lb n="14 middle"/>  تم 
<lb n="12 left"/>  حضرت ذلك 
<lb n="13 left"/>  وكتب محمّد بن عبد الوهّاب <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">النّوبيّ</unclear> 
<lb n="14 left"/>  تم 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>šahida man ʾaṯbata ʾuṯbita ĭsma ĭsmu hu ʾāḫira hu ʾanna hum yaʿrifūna kafiyyaẗa ăl bikra ăl bāliġa ĭbnaẗa ḫulbūṣa bni salīm:in sulaym:ini 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl muqīmi bi biyahmūla maʿrifaẗ:an ṣaḥīḥaẗ:an šarʿiyyaẗ:an wa yašhadūna ʾanna hā bikr:un bāliġ:un ṣaḥīḥaẗu ăl ʿaqli wa ăl badani 
 <lb n="4"/>ḫāliyaẗ:un min mawāniʿi ăn nikāḥi wa ʾanna wālida hā ăl maḏkūra mustaḥiqqu ăl walāyaẗi ʿalay hā ʾahl:an li tilka wa ʾanna ăr rāġiba 
 <lb n="5"/>fī tazwīǧi hā muḥassina bna ʾabī ăz zahri bni šamḫ:in kufuʾ:an la hā wa ḍamina bi ḏālika ʿalà fawr:in wa ḏālika 
 <lb n="6"/>taʾrīḫu ăl ḫāmisa ʿašara min ǧumādà ăl ʾāḫiraẗi sanaẗa ʾiḥdà wa ʾarbaʿīna wa sitti miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="7"/>šahida bi ḏālika 
 <lb n="8"/>ʿumaru bnu ʿabdi ăl ʿazīzi bni muʿizz:in 
 <lb n="9"/>ḥāll:un 
 <lb n="10"/>ʿišrīna dīnār:an 
 <lb n="11"/>šahida bi ḏālika 
 <lb n="12"/>ʿaliyyu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni muḥammad:in 
 <lb n="13"/>muʾaḫḫar:un 
 <lb n="14"/>sittīna dīnār:an 
 <lb n="15"/>fī salḫi kulli sanaẗ:in 
 <lb n="16"/>sittaẗu danānīra 
 <lb n="17"/>ʿaqada bi walāyaẗi ʾabī hā ăl maḏkūri ăz zawǧu ăl maḏkūru ʿalà ăṣ ṣadāqi ăl maḏkūri fī ăt taʾrīḫi ăl maḏkūri 
 <lb n="18"/>ḥaḍartu ḏālika 
 <lb n="19"/>wa kataba ʾaḥmadu bnu ăl ḥasani bni *** 
 <lb n="20"/>tamma 
 <lb n="21"/>ḥaḍartu ḏālika 
 <lb n="22"/>kataba hu ʿalabu bnu ṭāhiri bni ʾaḥmada 
 <lb n="23"/>tamma 
 <lb n="24"/>ḥaḍartu ḏālika 
 <lb n="25"/>wa kataba muḥammadu bnu ʿabdi ăl wahhābi ăn nūbiyyu 
 <lb n="26"/>tamma 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes, des Barmherzigen, des Gütigen!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Diese, welche ihre Namen an das Ende von diesem hier setzen, haben Zeugnis abgelegt, dass sie Kafīya kennen, die erwachsene Jungfrau, die Tochter des Ḫulbūs b. Sulaim,
		Those who have set their names at the end hereof have born witness that they know Kafîya, the adult virgin, the daughter of Ḫulbûṣ b. Sulaim,
			<lb n="3"/>
		residing in Biyahmûl, in form of a right, lawful cognizance; and they testify that she is an adult virgin, sound in mind and body,
		wohnhaft in Biyahmūl, in der Gestalt eines Rechts, voll rechtliche Anerkennung, und sie bezeugen, dass sie eine erwachsene Jungfrau ist, gesund im Geiste und Körper,
			<lb n="4"/>
		free from (legal) impediments to marriage; and that her (above) mentioned father possesses the right of wilâya over her, he being capable thereof; and that he who solicited
		frei von (rechtlichen) Hindernissen zur Heirat; und dass ihr (oben) erwähnter Vater das Recht der Brautvaterschaft über sie besitzt, er dazu befähigt ist, und dass er, der geworben hat
			<lb n="5"/>
		her in marriage, Muḥassin b. Abiʾ z-Zahr b. Šamḫ, is her equal in respect of his social rank, and he guaranteed therefor immediately, viz.
		sie zur Heirat, Muḥassin b. Abi az-Ẓahr b. Šamḫ, ihr ebenbürtig ist hinsichtlich sozialen Ranges, und er sicherte dazu unverzüglich, nämlich
			<lb n="6"/>
		am fünfzehnten des Ǧumāḍa II des Jahres sechshunderteinundvierzig.
		on the fifteenth of Ǧumâdâ II of the year six hundred and forty one.
			<lb n="7"/>
		Witness to it is
		Zeuge dafür ist:
			<lb n="8"/>
		ʿUmar b. ʿAbd al-ʿAzîz b. Muʿizz
		ʿUmar b. ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz b. Muʿizz.
			<lb n="9"/>
		anfallend:
		falling due:
			<lb n="10"/>
		twenty dînârs.
		zwanzig Dīnār
			<lb n="11"/>
		Witness to it is:
		Zeuge hierfür ist:
			<lb n="12"/>
		ʿAlî b. ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad
		ʿAlī b. ʿAbdallāh b. Muḥammad
			<lb n="13"/>
		ausstehend:
		outstanding:
			<lb n="14"/>
		sechzig Dīnār
		sixty dînârs.
			<lb n="15"/>
		am Ende eines jeden Jahres:
		at the end of each year:
			<lb n="16"/>
		sechs Dīnār
		six dînârs.
			<lb n="17"/>
		Der Ehevertrag wurde abgeschlossen unter der Brautvaterschaft ihres (oben) erwähnten Vaters durch den (oben) erwähnten Ehegatten zu der (oben) erwähnten Brautgabe am (oben) erwähnten Datum.
		The marriage-contract was concluded under the wilâya of her (above) mentioned father by the (above) mentioned husband for the (above) mentioned nuptial gift on the (above) mentioned date.
			<lb n="18"/>
		Ich war dabei zugegen,
		I was present at it,
			<lb n="19"/>
		and Aḥmad b. al-Ḥasan b. ..... has written (it).
		und Aḥmad b. al-Ḥasan b. ..... hat (es) geschrieben.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Complete.
		Vollständig.
			<lb n="21"/>
		Ich war dabei zugegen
		I was present at it
			<lb n="22"/>
		ʿAlab b. Ṭâhir b. Aḥmad has written it.
		ʿAlab b. Ṭāhir b. Aḥmad hat es geschrieben.
			<lb n="23"/>
		Complete.
		Vollständig
			<lb n="24"/>
		Ich war dabei zugegen
		I was present at it
			<lb n="25"/>
		and Muḥammad b. ʿAbd al-Wahhâb, the Nubian, has written (it).
		und Muḥammad b. ʿAbd al-Wahhāb, der Nubier, hat (es) geschrieben.
			<lb n="26"/>
		Complete.
		Vollständig.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
