<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="905" xml:id="Grohmann_World_p_161" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.World p. 161</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_World_p_161</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113666</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="recto 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="recto 2"/>  عافانا اللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأبقاكم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وإيّاكم</rdg></app> فإنّي قد 
<lb n="recto 3"/>  كنت كتبت إليكم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">آمركم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">آمركم</rdg></app> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>    
<lb n="recto 4"/>  ستّة مائة كبش <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فليكن </lem><rdg resp="Dietrich; Diem">بستّة </rdg></app>  كبش فليكن 
<lb n="recto 5"/>  إلى يومين <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ولا </lem><rdg resp="Dietrich; Diem">شىء</rdg></app> تدع أن تشتري حوائج رمضان 
<lb n="recto 6"/>  على سلامتك الّتي في عافية فلا يكون 
<lb n="recto 7"/>  وبعد غم وأبو كريم يقريكم سلام كثيرا وأنا 
<lb n="recto 8"/>  ولا توحروه ساعة إن شا اللّه  
<lb n="verso 1"/>  على الاجران فتنقلوا البر إلى المنزل وتصيروه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʿāfā nā ăl lāhu wa ʾabqā ʾiyyā kum fa ʾin nī qad 
 <lb n="3"/>kuntu katabtu ʾilay kum ʾamra ʾāmuru kum ʾan taqdamū tuqaddimū min ḍaʾni 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾibrāhīma bni maymūn:in ø bi sittaẗa sittaẗi miʾaẗi kabš:in fa l yakun 
 <lb n="5"/>ḥaqqu hu ʾakbaru min šayʾ:in nī ø fī hā li tanfuqa tunfaqa min nā wa l yakun qudūmu kum 
 <lb n="6"/>bi hā ăl yawma laʿalla nā nabīʿu hā ġad:an yawma ăs sabti 
 <lb n="7"/>wa baʿda ġad:an yawma ăl ʾaḥadi ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu fa ʿaǧǧilū 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾilay hi wa lā tuʾaḫḫirū hu sāʿaẗ:an ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="9"/>min ǧunādaẗa bni ʿīsà ʾilà zabāna wa ʾaṣḥābi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes des Allbarmherzigen! 
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!
			<lb n="2"/>
		Gott erhalte und und Euch gesund und wohl! Und dann, ich  
		May God keep us in health and may He preserve you. Verily I
			<lb n="3"/>
		habe Euch ja doch schon den schriftlichen Auftrag geschickt, daß Ihr von den Hammel 
		had already written to you ordering you that you let come of the sheep
			<lb n="4"/>
		des Ibrahîm ibn Maimûn 600 Widder sollt kommen lassen; denn wahrhaftig, 
		of Ibrahîm ibn Maimûn sixhundred rams; for
			<lb n="5"/>
		his obligation respecting them is greater than mine so that they be cleared off hastily by us. And your arrival
		seine Verpflichtung (gegen uns) in Betreff derselben wird ja um so größer sein, da seine Waare durch uns rasch abgesetzt wird. Eure Ankunft 
		seine Verpflichtung ist, was sie betrifft, die Hauptsache, damit sie von uns aus rasch abgesetzt werden
			<lb n="6"/>
		mit den Widdern möge also noch heute erfolgen; vielleicht, daß wir sie morgen, Samstag, 
		with them should be to-day. Perhaps we may sell them to-morrow Saturday
			<lb n="7"/>
		and the day after to-morrow, Sunday, if God wills. So hurry
		und übermorgen, Sonntag, verkaufen können, so Gott will! Also eilet! 
			<lb n="8"/>
		to him and do not be behind therewith one hour, please God.
		Zögert keine Stunde! So Gott will! 
			<lb n="9"/>
		From Gunâda ibn ʿÎsâ to Zabân and his mates.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
