<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1749" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_293" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 293</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_293</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169490</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  كتابنا أطال اللّه بقا مولانا و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أد</supplied>ام عزّ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ه</supplied> وتأييده وعلوّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ومكنته </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وتمكينه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكبت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وكبت</rdg></app> 
<lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عـ</supplied>ـبده </lem><rdg resp="Diem">عدوّه</rdg></app> عن سلامة والحـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمـ</supplied>ـد <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> رب العلمين ومولانا أيّده اللّه يعلم 
<lb n="4"/>  أنّا زرعنا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عند</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مع</rdg></app> عبده وصيف فدّانين قمح <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ورفع </lem><rdg resp="APD">ووقّع</rdg></app> إلى الكاتب وتقدّم 
<lb n="5"/>  إليه أن يحطّنا من الخراج ثلثة دنانير والتّوقيع عنده و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مـ</supplied>ـولانا 
<lb n="6"/>  أيّده اللّه في النّاحية ونحن نسئله أيّده اللّه أن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ينقل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">يتقدّم</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إلى </lem><rdg resp="Diem">إلى</rdg></app> من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذ</supplied>لك </lem><rdg resp="Diem"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/></rdg></app> 
<lb n="7"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بالغاية </lem><rdg resp="APD">بالعناية</rdg></app> بحـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـصـ</supplied>ـول الغلّة وقبضها من وصيف فإ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ن</supplied> أحصلت 
<lb n="8"/>  الغلّة عنده يرسل كتب إلينا بذلك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وقد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فقد</rdg></app> عملنا على أن مولانا 
<lb n="9"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="9" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>kitābu nā ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa mawlā nā wa ʾadāma ʿizza hu wa taʾyīda hu wa ʿuluwwa hu wa muknata tamkīna hu wa kabata kataba 
 <lb n="3"/>ʿabdu ʿaduwwa hu ʿan salāmaẗ:in wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi rabbi ăl ʿālamīna wa mawlā nā ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu yaʿlamu 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾan nā zaraʿnā ʿinda maʿa ʿabdi hi waṣīf:in faddānayni qamḥ:in wa waqqaʿa rafaʿa ʾilà ăl kātibi wa taqaddama 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾilay hi ʾan yaḥuṭṭa nā mina ăl ḫarāǧi ṯalāṯaẗa danānīra wa ăt tawqīʿu ʿinda hu wa mawlā nā 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu fī ăn nāḥiyaẗi wa naḥnu nasʾalu hu ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu ʾan yanqula yataqaddama ʾilà ʾilay ø ya man min ḏālika *** 
 <lb n="7"/>bi ăl ġāyaẗi ʿināyaẗi bi ḥuṣūli ăl ġallaẗi wa qabḍi hā min waṣīf:in fa ʾin ʾaḥṣalati 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl ġallaẗu ʿinda hu yursal kutub:un ʾilay nā bi ḏālika wa fa qad ʿamilnā ʿalà ʾanna mawlā nā 
 <lb n="9"/>********* *** 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		We are writing - may God prolong the life of our lord and may He cause his might, strength, high rank and power to continue - and
			<lb n="3"/>
		his [ser]vant writes in a state of safety, and pr[ai]se be [to God,] the Lord of all created beings. Our lord - may God strengthen him - knows
		... . Unser Patron - Gott stütze ihn - weiß,
			<lb n="4"/>
		daß wir [zusammen] mit seinem Sklaven Waṣīf zwei Faddān (Land) mit Getreide bestellt haben und er (sc. der Patron) an den Sekretär (des Finanzamts) einen Erlaß gerichtet und ihn angewiesen hat,
		that we have sown [at] his servant Waṣîf&#039;s two faddâns with wheat. He petitioned the clerk and requested
			<lb n="5"/>
		him, to make us a reduction of three dînârs from the land-tax, and the decree is with him. Now our [l]ord,
		uns drei Dinar von der Grundsteuer abzuziehen; der Erlaß ist bei ihm (sc. dem Sekretär). ...
			<lb n="6"/>
		whom may God strengthen, is in the district, and we shall ask him - may God strengthen him - to transmit to me [the]reof
			<lb n="7"/>
		kümmert, die Ernte einzubringen und von Waṣīf in Empfang zu nehmen.
		to the utmost at (the time) the har[ve]st is brought in and taken over from Waṣīf. But whe[n] the harvest is (finally) brought
			<lb n="8"/>
		in at his place, letters should be sent to us concerning this. We have already worked so that our master
			<lb n="9"/>
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
