<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="287" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_91" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 091</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_91</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106533</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  لفاطمة ابنت محمّد بن عيسى بن إسحق القبلي مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـنزل</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>حمد الدبّاغ و البحري الشارع <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="2"/>  لفاطمة ابنت محمّد بن عيسى في الرّكن الغربي من <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">هـ</supplied>ـذ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ه</supplied> الدّار والشّرقي منظـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـرة</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بن</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="3"/>  والغربي طريق المارّة اكترت ملك السّودا منزل من هذه الدار <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="4"/>  ومن ذلك نصف منزل في الوجه القبلي من حمّام نيله حدّه القبلي <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>li fāṭimaẗa ĭbnati muḥammadi bni ʿīsà bni ʾisḥāqa ăl qibliyyu manzilu *** bni ʾaḥmada ăd dabbāġi wa ăl baḥriyyu ăš šāriʿu *** 
 <lb n="2"/>li fāṭimaẗa ĭbnati muḥammadi bni ʿīsà fī ăr rukni ăl ġarbiyyi min hāḏihi ăd dāri wa ăš šarqiyyu manẓaraẗu *** bni *** 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ăl ġarbiyyu ṭarīqu ăl mārraẗi ĭktarat malaku ăs sawdāʾu manzil min hāḏihi ăd dāri **** 
 <lb n="4"/>wa min ḏālika niṣfu manzil:in fī ăl waǧhi ăl qibliyyi min ḥammāmi nīlahi ḥaddu hu ăl qibliyyu **** 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Belonging to Fâṭima, daughter of Muḥammad b. ʿÎsâ b. Isḥâq, the southern (boundary is formed by) the dw[ellinghouse of So and So, son of A]ḥmad, the tanner; and the northern is (formed by) the street [......  
			<lb n="2"/>
		belonging to Fâṭima, daughter of Muḥammad b. ʿÎsâ, in the western corner of [th]i[s] house; and the eastern is (formed by) the manẓa[ra of So and So, son of So and So,]
			<lb n="3"/>
		and the western is (formed by) the main thoroughfare. Malak, the black, has hired a dwelling (house) appertaining to this house [ .........
			<lb n="4"/>
		and thereto appertains the half of a dwelling (house) lying in the southern part of Nile&#039;s baths, the southern boundary thereof [ ........
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
