<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="295" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_96" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 096 (= P.World p. 208 = Chrest.Khoury I 61)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_96</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106538</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">هـ</supplied>ـذا ما استأجر سعيد بن عيسى استأجر هارون بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بفام </lem><rdg resp="APD">بفام</rdg></app> استأجره 
 <lb n="3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سـ</supplied>ـعيد بن عيسى شهرين كاملين على أن يعمل له عمل الفول وعلى أن 
 <lb n="4"/>  يعطيه في هذين الشّهرين سدس دينر لكل شهر درهمين 
 <lb n="5"/>  وأوّل يوم من الشّهر أوّل يوم من <sic n="superfluous">كهيك</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">كيهك</supplied> من شهور العجم 
 <lb n="6"/>  من سنة مپپن وسبعة وعشرين شهد على ذلك 
 <lb n="7"/>  وأيّوب بن موسى وكتب شهادته σκζ <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> </lem><rdg resp="APD">ἀρχῆς</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">: </lem><rdg resp="APD">ε</rdg></app> 
 <lb n="8"/>  ومحمّد بن أتوث <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكتببخطّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـه</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World">وكتب</rdg></app> 
 <lb n="9"/>  وليد بن مسلم القرشي وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭstaʾǧara saʿīdu bnu ʿīsà ĭstaʾǧara hārūna bna bifāma buqāma ĭstaʾǧara hu 
 <lb n="3"/>saʿīdu bnu ʿīsà šahrayni kāmilayni ʿalà ʾan yaʿmila la hu ʿamala ăl fūli wa ʿalà ʾan 
 <lb n="4"/>yuʿṭiya hu fī hāḏayni ăš šahrayni sudsa dīnār:in li kulli šahr:in dirhamayni 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ʾawwalu yawm:in mina ăš šahri ʾawwalu yawm:in min kiyahk:in min šuhūri ăl ʿaǧami 
 <lb n="6"/>min sanaẗi miʾatayni wa sabʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ʾayyūbu bnu mūsà wa kataba šahādaẗa hu 227 ** archēs * 5 * indikt : 
 <lb n="8"/>wa muḥammadu bnu ʾaṯwaba wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="9"/>walīdu bnu muslim:ini ăl qurašiyyi wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  Au nom de Dieu clément et miséricordieux!
 	  In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  [Ce]ci est ce qu’a pris en louage Saʿīd Ibn ʿĪsā: Il a pris en louage Hārūn ibn Bqām,
 	  [Th]is is what Saʿîd b. ʿÎsâ has hired for wages: he has hired Hârûn b. Bqâm;
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  [Sa]ʿîd b. ʿÎsâ has hired him for two full months that he might do the work connected with the (broad) beans on condition that he would
 	  [Sa]ʿīd Ibn ʿĪsā l’a pris en louage pour deux mois entiers, afin qu’il acconplisse pour lui le travail des fèves et à condition que (Saʿīd)
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  give him (as his hire) for these two months the sixth of a dînâr, for each month two dirhams,
 	  give him (as his wages) for these two months the sixth of a dînâr, for each month two dirhams,
 	  lui donne pour ces deux mois un sixième de dīnār, chaque mois deux drachmes.
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  and the first day of the month is (reckoned from) the first day of Choiak of the months of the Copts
 	  Et le premier jour du mois est le premier jour de khoiak, (l’un) des mois des non arabes
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  de l’année deux cent vingt-sept. Ont témoigné de cela
 	  of the year two hundred and twenty six. (The following witnesses) have testified to it:
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  And Ayyûb b. Mûsâ,  who has written his testimony in the beginning of the 5th indiction of the year 227.
 	  And Ayyûb b. Mûsâ, who has written his testimony in the year 227.
 	  {et} Ayyūb Ibn Mūsā, et il écrivit son témoignage en l’an 227,
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  And Muḥammad b. Aṯwab, who has written (it) in[his]own handwriting.
 	  et Muḥammad Ibn Aṯwab, et il écrivit de [sa] main
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  et Walīd Ibn Muslim alQuraši, et il écrivit son témoignage de sa main.
 	  Walîd b. Muslim, the Qorašite, who has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
