<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="931" xml:id="Grohmann_World_p_175_a" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.World p. 175 a (= CPR XVI 16)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_World_p_175_a</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113689</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="recto 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="recto 2"/>  أبقاك آللّه وحفظك وأتم نعمه عليك وزاد في 
<lb n="recto 3"/>  قد توجّه إلينا <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ما</supplied> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">قبلك </lem><rdg resp="“Diem”">ألى</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ما</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="“Diem”">ما</rdg></app> قبلك 
<lb n="recto 4"/>  وقد إليه <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann; Diem”">قارب </lem><rdg resp="“Diem”">النوبى</rdg></app>  سلّم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إليه </lem><rdg resp="“Diem”">اللّه</rdg></app> قارب 
<lb n="recto 5"/>  يوسف <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">پن </lem><rdg resp="“Diem”">بن</rdg></app> القلفاط وقد وجّهت الى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نفسك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">بيتك</rdg></app> 
<lb n="recto 6"/>  بالّذي وجّهت به معه إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="recto 7"/>  أبقاك اللّه وحفظك 
<lb n="verso 1"/>  لأبي الحسن أبقاه اللّه من جميع أصحابه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu wa ḥafiẓa ka wa ʾatamma niʿama hu ʿalay ka wa zāda fī 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾiḥsāni hi ʾilay ka qad tawaǧǧaha ʾilay ʾilà nā ø ø mā qibala ka 
 <lb n="4"/>qāribu bakr:ini ăn nūbiyyi nūtiyyi wa qad sallama sullima ʾilay ăl hi lāhu qāriba qāribu 
 <lb n="5"/>yūsufa ø ĭbni ăl qalfāṭi wa qad waǧǧahtu ʾilà nafsi bayti ka 
 <lb n="6"/>bi ăllaḏī waǧǧahtu bi hi maʿa hu ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu wa ḥafiẓa ka 
 <lb n="8"/>li ʾabī ăl ḥasani ʾabqā hu ăl lāhu min ǧamīʿi ʾaṣḥābi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes, des Barmherzigen und Gnädigen!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!
			<lb n="2"/>
		Gott erhalte und beschütze Dich, vollende seine Gnadenerweise an Dir und erweise Dir noch mehr
		May God preserve thee and protect thee and may He fulfil His loving kindness unto thee and may He increase
			<lb n="3"/>
		His bounty unto thee! The boat of Bakr, the sailor,
		sein Wohlwollen! Die Barke von 
			<lb n="4"/>
		Bakr dem Seemann ist auf dem Weg zu Dir. Die Barke von
		has just been sent to us from thy part, and the boat of
			<lb n="5"/>
		Yūsuf, dem Sohn des Kalfaterers, hat Gott wohlbehalten ankommen lassen, und ich habe zu Deinem Haus
		Yûsuf, the caulker, has already been handed over to him. And I have just sent to thee personally
			<lb n="6"/>
		das gesandt, was Du durch ihn hattest überbringen lassen, so Gott will.
		that which I have sent with him (i.e. Bakr), please God.
			<lb n="7"/>
		Gott erhalte und beschütze Dich!
		May God preserve thee and protect thee.
			<lb n="8"/>
		An Abū l-Ḥasan - Gott erhalte ihn - von allen seinen Partnern.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
