<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="964" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_37" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 037 (= P.World p. 189 = Chrest.Khoury I 21)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_37</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113711</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  هذا الكتاب صحيح وكتب إبرهيم بن علي 
<lb n="2"/>  وكتب بخطّه 
<lb n="3"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم توكّلت على اللّه 
<lb n="4"/>  يقول إسطورهيوه ابنت سرجه بن أبليدة في صحّة عقلها و 
<lb n="5"/>  بدنها وجواز أمرها طايعة غير مكره ولا مجبرة طيّبة 
<lb n="6"/>  بذلك نفسها صحيحة البدن كاملة العقل أنّها أعتقت 
<lb n="7"/>  صفراه بالعربيّة واسمها بالقبطيّة دجاشه ابنت 
<lb n="8"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أرينه </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”">أرينة</rdg></app> جارية إسطورهيوه أعتقت هذه الصّبيّة 
<lb n="9"/>  عتاقة العبيد من مواليهم وملكت نفسها <sic n="superfluous">فتما</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ڤمتا</supplied> ادّعا 
<lb n="10"/>  ولد لإسطورهيوه أو أحد من تركتها على هذه الصّبيّة 
<lb n="11"/>  دجاشه بشي بعد هذا الكتاب بشي من الخدمة أو شي 
<lb n="12"/>  من المملكة فدعواه باطل وزور وافك وعدوان 
<lb n="13"/>  وكتب ذلك في سلخ رمضان سنة تلات وتسعين وتلتمائة 
<lb n="14"/>  شهد اللّه وملائكته وكفا باللّه شهيد<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied> 
<lb n="15"/>  شهد الحسن بن إبرهيم بن علي بن جبريل بن الحسن بن رزق 
<lb n="16"/>  بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بخطّه 
<lb n="17"/>  شهد عبد الرّحمن بن الشّارك بجميع ما في هذا الكتا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ب</supplied> 
<lb n="18"/>  وكتب بخطّه 
<lb n="19"/>  شهد فضالة بن علي بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب 
<lb n="20"/>  بخطّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>hāḏā ăl kitābu ṣaḥīḥ:un wa kataba ʾibrāhīmu bnu ʿaliyy:in 
 <lb n="2"/>wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="3"/>* bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi tawakkaltu ʿalà ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="4"/>yaqūlu ʾisṭūrhiyūhu ĭbnatu sirǧaha bni ʾablīdaẗa fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿaqli hā wa 
 <lb n="5"/>badani hā wa ǧawāzi ʾamri hā ṭāyiʿaẗ:an ġayra mukrah:in wa lā muǧbaraẗ:in ṭayyibaẗ:an 
 <lb n="6"/>bi ḏālika nafsa hā ṣaḥīḥaẗa ăl badani kāmilaẗa ăl ʿaqli ʾanna hā ʾaʿtaqat 
 <lb n="7"/>ṣafrāha bi ăl ʿarabiyyaẗi wa ĭsmu hā bi ăl qibṭiyyaẗi daǧāšahu ĭbnata 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾaryanaha ʾaryanaẗa ǧāriyaẗa ʾisṭūrhiyūha ʾaʿtaqat hāḏihi ăṣ ṣabiyyaẗa 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿitāqaẗa ăl ʿabīdi min mawālī him wa malakat nafsa hā fa matā ĭddaʿā 
 <lb n="10"/>walad:un li ʾisṭūrhiyūha ʾaw ʾaḥadu man tarakat hā ʿalà hāḏihi ăṣ ṣabiyyaẗi 
 <lb n="11"/>daǧāšaha bi šayʾ:in baʿda hāḏā ăl kitābi bi šayʾ:in mina ăl ḫidmaẗi ʾaw šayʾ:in 
 <lb n="12"/>mina ăl mamlakaẗi fa daʿwā hu bāṭil:un wa zūr:un wa ʾifk:un wa ʿudwān:un 
 <lb n="13"/>wa kutiba ḏālika fī salḫi ramaḍāna sanaẗa talāt:in wa tisʿīna wa talāti miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="14"/>šahida ăl lāhu wa malāʾikatu hu wa kafā bi ăl lāhi šahīd:an 
 <lb n="15"/>šahida ăl ḥasanu bnu ʾibrāhīma bni ʿaliyyi bni ǧibrīla bni ăl ḥasani bni rizq:in 
 <lb n="16"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="17"/>šahida ʿabdu ăr raḥmāni bnu ăš šāriki bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="18"/>wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida faḍālaẗu bnu ʿaliyy:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba 
 <lb n="20"/>bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Ce document est valide, et Ibrāhīm Ibn ʿAlī (l&#039;)a écrit,
		This document is valid and Ibrahîm b. ʿAlî has written it
			<lb n="2"/>
		and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting.
		et il a écrit de sa main.
			<lb n="3"/>
		Au nom de Dieu clément et miséricordieux! Je fais confiance à Dieu !
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful! I trust in God.
			<lb n="4"/>
		Isṭurheu, daughter of Serge ibn Ablîde, declares - she being in sound mind and
		Isṭūrheu, fille de Serge Ibn Ablīde, a déclaré, étant dans la plénitude de ses facultés mentale et
			<lb n="5"/>
		body and capable of transacting her business, voluntarily without compulsion and not against her will, of her own
		physique et sa capacité juridique, de bon gré, non contrainte ou forcée, de
			<lb n="6"/>
		bon coeur, étant en bonne santé corporelle et mentale, qu&#039;elle a affranchi
		good pleasure, healthy in body, fully in possession of her reason - that she has emancipated
			<lb n="7"/>
		Ṣafra, as her name is in Arabic, and in Coptic Daǧâsha, daughter of
		Ṣafrā (comme et son nom) en arabe et en copte Daǧāša, fille
			<lb n="8"/>
		Aryana, the female slave of Isṭurheu. She has emancipated this slave girl
		d&#039;Aryana esclave d&#039;Isṭūrheu. Elle a affranchi cette esclave
			<lb n="9"/>
		de la manière avec laquelle sont affranchis les esclaves par leurs seigneurs, de la sorte qu&#039;elle est entrée en possession d&#039;elle-même. Ainsi si
		in the manner in which slaves are emancipated by their masters, so she becomes her own mistress. But if
			<lb n="10"/>
		a son of Isṭurheu or one of her (relatives) left behind (after her death) should make any claim with regard to this slave-girl
		a son of Isṭurheu or one of her relicts should make any claim with regard to this slave-girl
		un fils d&#039;Isṭūrheu ou l&#039;un de ses descendants revendiquait de cette esclave
			<lb n="11"/>
		Daǧāša quelque chose, après (l&#039;exécution de) ce document, concernant quelque service ou
		Daǧâsha after (the completion) of this act, be it any service or any
			<lb n="12"/>
		proprietory rights (over her) then his claim is vain and false, a fiction and an unjust proceeding.
		titre de possession, alors son action en justice est de nulle valeur et fausse, mensonge et action illégitime.
			<lb n="13"/>
		And this has been written at the end of Ramaḍân of the year three hundred and ninety three.
		Et l&#039;on écrivit cela à la fin de ramaḍān, trois cent quatre-vingt-treize.
			<lb n="14"/>
		God and his angels know it and God suffices as witness.
		Témoins sont Dieu et ses anges, et Dieu est suffisant comme témoin.
			<lb n="15"/>
		Al-Ḥasan b. Ibrahîm b. ʿAlî b. Ǧibrîl b. al-Ḥasan b. Rizq is witness
		A témoigné al-Ḥasan Ibn Ibrāhīm Ibn ʿAlī Ibn Ǧibrīl Ibn al-Ḥasan Ibn Rizq
			<lb n="16"/>
		de tout ce qui est dans ce document, et il écrivit de sa main.
		to all that (is contained) in this act, and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="17"/>
		ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. ash-Shârik is witness to all that (is contained) in this ac[t]
		A témoigné ʿAbd al-Raḥmān Ibn al-Šārik de tout ce qui est dans ce documen[t],
			<lb n="18"/>
		and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting.
		et il écrivit de sa main.
			<lb n="19"/>
		A témoigné Faḍāla Ibn ʿAlī de tout le contenu de ce document, et il écrivit
		Faḍâla b. ʿAlî is witness to all that (is contained) in this act and he has written (it)
			<lb n="20"/>
		de sa main.
		in his (own) handwriting.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
