<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="308" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_107" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 107</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_107</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106549</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أقر أبيمه بن بجوش المزارع ببلجسوق <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أقر </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 71">إقرار</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">له </lem><rdg resp="APD">ø</rdg></app> 
<lb n="3"/>  طوع راغب <expan><abbr>و</abbr><ex>طا</ex><abbr>لب</abbr></expan> وأشهد على نفسه في صحّته وجواز 
<lb n="4"/>  أمر طائعا غير مكره ولا مجبر ولا مضطهد ولا جاهلا 
<lb n="5"/>  بما أقر به فيه أن عليه وعنده وقبله وفي ذمّته وخالص 
<lb n="6"/>  ماله دينا ثابتا وحقّا لازما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">له </lem><rdg resp="Thung p. 38">لزمه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">من </lem><rdg resp="Thung">ø</rdg></app> الإقرار به لزمزوم 
<lb n="7"/>  بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نصر </lem><rdg resp="APD">نضر</rdg></app> من القمح الطّيّب <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الصّل </lem><rdg resp="Levi della Vida, confirmed by Thung p. 100 and 104 and Diem p. 71 and 112">النّصيل</rdg></app> السّالم من العلث 
<lb n="8"/>  أربعة <expan><abbr>أ</abbr><ex>ر</ex><abbr>ا</abbr><ex>د</ex><abbr>ب</abbr></expan> وأن يقوم بذلك في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">صفر </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 71/77">صيفة</rdg></app> سنة ستّة <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>عشرين 
<lb n="9"/>  بغير مدافعة ولا ممانعة ولا احتجاج بحجّة دون الخروج 
<lb n="10"/>  من المبلغ المذكور على تمامه وكماله و<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـذلك أقر وأشهد على 
<lb n="11"/>  نفسه في العشر الثّاني من محرّم سنة سبع وعشرين وخمسمائة 
<lb n="12"/>  شهدت عليه بذلك وكتب 
<lb n="13"/>  إسمعيل بن زيد بن أحمد بن عبد اللّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaqarra ʾabīmahu bnu biǧūša ăl muzāriʿu bi bulǧusūqa ʾaqarra ʾiqrār la ø hu ø 
 <lb n="3"/>ṭawʿ rāġib wa ṭālib wa ʾašhada ʿalà nafsi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗi hi wa ǧawāzi 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾamr:in ṭāʾiʿ:an ġayra mukrah:in wa lā muǧbar:in wa lā muḍṭahad:in wa lā ǧāhil:an 
 <lb n="5"/>bi mā ʾaqarra bi hi fī hi ʾanna ʿalay hi wa ʿinda hu wa qibala hu wa fī ḏimmaẗi hi wa ḫāliṣi 
 <lb n="6"/>māli hi dayn:an ṯābit:an wa ḥaqq:an lāzim:an la lazima hu mina ø ăl ʾiqrāru ʾiqrāri bi hi li zamzūma 
 <lb n="7"/>bni naṣar:in naḍr:in naṣr:in mina ăl qamḥi ăṭ ṭayyibi ăṣ ăn ṣalli naṣīli ăs sālimi min ăl ʿalaṯi 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾarbaʿaẗa ʾarādiba wa ʾan yaqūma bi ḏālika fī ṣafar:in ṣayfaẗi sanaẗa sanaẗi sittaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna 
 <lb n="9"/>bi ġayri mudāfaʿaẗ:in wa lā mumānaʿaẗ:in wa lā ĭḥtiǧāǧ:in bi ḥuǧǧaẗ:in dūna ăl ḫurūǧi 
 <lb n="10"/>mina ăl mablaġi ăl maḏkūri ʿalà tamāmi hi wa kamāli hi wa bi ḏālika ʾaqarra wa ʾašhada ʿalà 
 <lb n="11"/>nafsi hi fī ăl ʿašri ăṯ ṯānī min muḥarram:in sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa ʿišrīna wa ḫamsi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="12"/>šahidtu ʿalay hi bi ḏālika wa kataba 
 <lb n="13"/>ʾismāʿīlu bnu zaydi bni ʾaḥmada bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Abîme b. Beǧôš, the farmer in Bulǧusûq, has acknowledged, (viz.) he has acknowledged for himself
			<lb n="3"/>
		voluntarily, desiring and demanding it and has called witnesses to testify to his obligation, he being sound and capable of transacting
			<lb n="4"/>
		business, voluntarily, wihtout compulsion and not against his will and not under constraint, and not ignorant
			<lb n="5"/>
		of what he has acknowledged herein, viz. that he owes, has in his possession, is in debt and under obligation for, with his undiminished
			<lb n="6"/>
		property, as an obligatory debt and an obligation incumbent upon him on the  basis of the acknowledgment thereto, to Zamzûm
			<lb n="7"/>
		b. Naṣr of good, cleansed wheat, free from any admixture
			<lb n="8"/>
		eight artabas, and that he will present himself with it in Ṣafar of the year (five hundred and) twenty six
		four artabas, and that he will present himself with it in Ṣafar of the year (five hundred and) twenty six
			<lb n="9"/>
		without any delay, or pretext for refusal, or by bringing forward any argument beyond the paying
			<lb n="10"/>
		of the afore-mentioned amount completely and fully. And thereto he has acknowledged and has called witnesses to testify to his obligation
			<lb n="11"/>
		in the second decade of Muḥarram of the year five hundred and twenty seven.
			<lb n="12"/>
		I have testified thereto for him and
			<lb n="13"/>
		Ismaʿîl b. Zaid b. Aḥmad b. ʿAbdallâh has written (it).
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
