<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="298" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_98" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 098 (= P.World p. 209 = Chrest.Khoury I 31)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_98</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106540</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـم</supplied> اللّه الرّحمن الرّ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حـ</supplied>ـيم 
<lb n="2"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شهد</supplied> شهود هذا الكتاب أن موسى بن عبد اللّه لقبه 
<lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بجوش </lem><rdg resp="APD">نخوس</rdg></app> أقر <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عنـ</supplied>ـدهم وأشـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـهدهـ</supplied>ـم على نفسه أن لسليم 
<lb n="4"/>  مولى أبرك عليه سدس دينر مثقال دينا لازما 
<lb n="5"/>  له يدفع إليه في إبيبـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـه</supplied> قيراطين وفي مسرى 
<lb n="6"/>  قيراطين يشهد عبد اللّه بن محمّد على ما في هذا الصّك 
<lb n="7"/>  ‮و <expan><abbr>كـ</abbr><ex>ـبپـ</ex><abbr>ـسهدپه</abbr></expan> پحطه ڤى دى الححه سپه 
<lb n="8"/>  شهد إسمعيل بن قادم يكنّا أبا الحسن على مثل ما شهد به عبد اللّه 
<lb n="9"/>  بن محمّد حرف بحرف وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="10"/>  وشهد وليد بن عبد اللّه وكتب عنه عبد اللّه بن محمّد 
<lb n="11"/>  بأمره وبمخطره وعبد الجبّار بن سهل على ما في هذا الكتا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ب</supplied> 
<lb n="12"/>  ‮ويعقوب بن إبرهيم على ما فـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـي</supplied> هذا الكتاب ‪σλϝ‬ 
<lb n="13"/>  وكفا باللّه شهيدا ومحمّد بن يعقوب 
<lb n="14"/>  على ما في هذا الكتاب وكفا باللّه شهيدا 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>šahida šuhūdu hāḏā ăl kitābi ʾanna mūsà bna ʿabdi ăl lāhi laqabu hu 
 <lb n="3"/>biǧūšu naḫūsu ʾaqarra ʿinda hum wa ʾašhada hum ʿalà nafsi hi ʾanna li salīm:in 
 <lb n="4"/>mawlà ʾabraka ʿalay hi sudsa dīnār:in miṯqāl:in dayn:an lāzim:an 
 <lb n="5"/>la hu yadfaʿu ʾilay hi fī ʾabībha qīrāṭayni wa fī misrà 
 <lb n="6"/>qīrāṭayni yašhadu ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu muḥammad:in ʿalà mā fī hāḏā ăṣ ṣakki 
 <lb n="7"/>wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī ḏī ăl ḥiǧǧaẗi sanaẗa 236 
 <lb n="8"/>šahida ʾismāʿīlu bnu qādim:in yukannā ʾabā ăl ḥasani ʿalà miṯli mā šahida bi hi ʿabdu ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="9"/>bnu muḥammad:in ḥarf bi ḥarf:in wa kataba šahādata hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="10"/>wa šahida walīdu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu muḥammad:in 
 <lb n="11"/>bi ʾamri hi wa bi maḫṭari hi wa ʿabdu ăl ǧabbāri bnu sahl:in ʿalà mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="12"/>wa yaʿqūbu bnu ʾibrāhīma ʿalà mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 236 
 <lb n="13"/>wa kafā bi ăl lāhi šahīd:an wa muḥammadu bnu yaʿqūba 
 <lb n="14"/>ʿalà mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kafā bi ăl lāhi šahīd:an 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Au no[m] de Dieu clément et mi[sé]ricordieux!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Les témoins de ce document [ont témoigné] que Mūsā Ibn ʿAbd Allāh, surnommé
		The witnesses of this deed have testified, that Mûsâ b. ʿAbdallâh, bynamed
			<lb n="3"/>
		Beǧōš, a reconnu[e]n leur présence et l[es] a pris à té[moins] qu’il doit à Salīm,
		Beǧôs, has acknowledged in their presence and has called them to witness as to his obligation, that he owes to Salîm,
			<lb n="4"/>
		freedman of Abrak, a sixth of a dînâr miṯqâlî, in form of an obligatory debt
		l’affranchi d’Abrak, un sixième de dīnār pesé en miṯqāl, et ceci comme dette obligatoire
			<lb n="5"/>
		envers lui; il lui paiera au mois d’épiph[i] deux carats, et au mois de mésori
		to his (the creditors) credit, (so that) he shall pay to him in Epiphi two carats and in Mesori
			<lb n="6"/>
		deux carats. ʿAbd Allāh Ibn Muḥammad Ibn ʿAlī est témoin de ce qui est dans cette obligation,
		two carats. ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad is witness to the tenor of this bill,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting in Ḏu&#039;l-Ḥiǧǧa of the year 236.
		et il écrivit son témoignage de sa main en ḏū l-ḥiǧǧa de l’an 236.
			<lb n="8"/>
		A témoigné Ismāʿīl Ibn Qādim, surnommé Abū l-Ḥasan, de la même chose de lquelle a témoigné ʿAbd Allāh
		Ismaʿîl b. Qâdim, surnamed Abuʾl-Ḥasan, is witness to the same that ʿAbdallâh
			<lb n="9"/>
		b. Muḥammad has testified word by word, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
		Ibn Muḥammad mot à mot, et il écrivit son témoignage de sa main.
			<lb n="10"/>
		And Walîd b. ʿAbdallâh is witness, and ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad has written for him
		Ont témoigné aussi Walīd Ibn ʿAbd Allāh, et ʿAbd Allāh Ibn Muḥammad écrivit à sa place
			<lb n="11"/>
		at his order and in his presence. And ʿAbd al-Ǧabbâr b. Sahl (has testified) to the tenor of this dee[d] 236.
		sur son ordre et en sa présence, et ʿAbd al-Ǧabbār Ibn Sahl de tout le contenu de ce documen[t],
			<lb n="12"/>
		And Yaʿqûb b. Ibrahîm is witness to the tenor of this deed,
		et Yaʿqūb Ibn Ibrāhīm de tout le contenu de ce document, 236,
			<lb n="13"/>
		and God suffices as witness. And Muḥammad b. Yaʿqûb
		et Dieu suffit comme témoin, et Muḥammad Ibn Yaʿqūb
			<lb n="14"/>
		de tout le contenu de ce document, et Dieu suffit comme témoin.
		(has testified) to the tenor of this deed, and God suffices as witness.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
