<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="309" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_108" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 108</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_108</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106550</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أقر عبد المسيح بن بول الشّمسي المزارع ببلجسوق 
<lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أقر </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 71">إقرار</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">له </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> طوع راغب <expan><abbr>و</abbr><ex>طا</ex><abbr>لب</abbr></expan> وأشهد على نفسه في 
<lb n="4"/>  صحّته وجواز طائعا غير مكره ولا مجبر ولا مضطهد 
<lb n="5"/>  ولا جاهل بما أقر به فيه أن عليه وعنده 
<lb n="6"/>  وقبله وفي ذمّته وخالص ماله دينا ثابتا وحقّا 
<lb n="7"/>  لازما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">له </lem><rdg resp="Thung p. 38">لزمه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">من </lem><rdg resp="Thung">ø</rdg></app> الإقرار به لزمزم بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نصر </lem><rdg resp="APD">نضر</rdg></app> 
<lb n="8"/>  من القمح الطّيّب <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الصّل </lem><rdg resp="Levi della Vida, confirmed by Thung p. 100 and 104 and Diem p. 71 and 112">النّصيل</rdg></app> السّالم من العلث بالكيل 
<lb n="9"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الـ<gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 90">الدّوّار</rdg></app> أربعة <expan><abbr>أ</abbr><ex>ر</ex><abbr>ا</abbr><ex>د</ex><abbr>ب</abbr></expan> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>ثلث النّصف من ذلك 
<lb n="10"/>  إردبّين <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>سدس يقوم بذلك في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">صفر </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 71/77">صيفة</rdg></app> سنة 
<lb n="11"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> المذكورة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ولذلك </lem><rdg resp="Diem p. 71">وبذلك</rdg></app> أقر وأشهد على 
<lb n="12"/>  نفسه في العشر الثّاني من محرّم سنة سبع وعشرين وخمسمائة 
<lb n="13"/>  وحضر سربام بولس وأشهد على نفسه بينهما 
<lb n="14"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="11" unit="character" /> و<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـذلك أقر وأشهد على نفوسهم 
<lb n="15"/>  في التّأريخ المذكور شهدت عليهم بذلك وكتب 
<lb n="16"/>  إسمعيل بن زيد بن أحمد بن عبد اللّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaqarra ʿabdu ăl masīḥi bnu būla ăš šamsiyyi šumsiyyi ăl muzāriʿu bi bulǧusūqa 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾaqarra ʾiqrār la ø hu ø ṭawʿ rāġib wa ṭālib wa ʾašhada ʿalà nafsi hi fī 
 <lb n="4"/>ṣiḥḥaẗi hi wa ǧawāz:in ṭāʾiʿ:an ġayra mukrah:in wa lā muǧbar:in wa lā muḍṭahad:in 
 <lb n="5"/>wa lā ǧāhil:in bi mā ʾaqarra bi hi fī hi ʾanna ʿalay hi wa ʿinda hu 
 <lb n="6"/>wa qibala hu wa fī ḏimmaẗi hi wa ḫāliṣi māli hi dayn:an ṯābit:an wa ḥaqq:an 
 <lb n="7"/>lāzim:an la lazima hu mina ø ăl ʾiqrāri ʾiqrāru bi hi li zamzama bni naṣar:in naḍr:in naṣr:in 
 <lb n="8"/>mina ăl qamḥi ăṭ ṭayyibi ăṣ ăn ṣalli naṣīli ăs sālimi mina ăl ʿalaṯi bi ăl kayli 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl ăd **** dawwāri ʾarbaʿaẗa ʾarādiba wa ṯulṯ:uni ăn niṣfu min ḏālika 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾirdabbayni wa suds:un yaqūmu bi ḏālika fī ṣafar:in ṣayfaẗi sanaẗa sanaẗi 
 <lb n="11"/>**** ăl maḏkūraẗi wa li bi ḏālika ʾaqarra wa ʾašhada ʿalà 
 <lb n="12"/>nafsi hi fī ăl ʿašri ăṯ ṯānī min muḥarram:in sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa ʿišrīna wa ḫamsi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="13"/>wa ḥaḍara sarabāmu būlusa būlusu wa ʾašhada ʿalà nafsi hi bayna humā 
 <lb n="14"/>*********** wa bi ḏālika ʾaqarra wa ʾašhada ʿalà nufūsi him 
 <lb n="15"/>fī ăt taʾrīḫi ăl maḏkūri šahidtu ʿalay him bi ḏālika wa kataba 
 <lb n="16"/>ʾismāʿīlu bnu zaydi bni ʾaḥmada bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		ʿAbd al-Masīḥ b. Bûl aš-Šamsī, the farmer in Bulǧusûq, has acknowledged, (viz.)
			<lb n="3"/>
		he has acknowledged for him(self) voluntarily, desiring and demanding (it) and has called witnesses to testify to his obligation, he being
			<lb n="4"/>
		sound and capable of transacting, voluntarily, without compulsion and not against his will and not under constraint,
			<lb n="5"/>
		and not ignorant of what he has acknowledged herein, viz. that he owes, has in his possession,
			<lb n="6"/>
		is in debt and under obligation for, with his undiminished property, as an obligatory debt and an obligation
			<lb n="7"/>
		incumbent upon him on the basis of the acknowledgment thereto, to Zamzam b. Naṣr
			<lb n="8"/>
		of good, cleansed wheat, free from any admixture, according to the .................. measure
			<lb n="9"/>
		four artabas and the third (of an artaba) - the half thereof being
			<lb n="10"/>
		two artabas and a sixth (of an artaba) - with which he will present himself in Ṣafar of the ...............
			<lb n="11"/>
		afore-mentioned year. And thereto he has acknowledged and has called witnesses to testify to his obligation
			<lb n="12"/>
		in the second decade of Muḥarram of the year five hundred and twenty seven.
			<lb n="13"/>
		Sarabâm Bûlus has been present and has called witnesses to testify to his obligation before them
			<lb n="14"/>
		.................. and there(to) they have acknowledged and have called witnesses to testify to their obligation
			<lb n="15"/>
		on the above mentioned date. I have testified thereto for them and
			<lb n="16"/>
		Ismaʿîl b. Zaid b. Aḥmad b. ʿAbdallâh has written (it).
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
