<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1759" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_302" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 302</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_302</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169500</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أخي وسيّدي أطال اللّه بقاك وأدام عزّك وكرامتك وتأييدك 
<lb n="3"/>  وجمع لك خير الدّنيا والآخرة برحمته قد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">كتبت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">كنت</rdg></app> يا سيّدي 
<lb n="4"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأعرفتك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وافقتك</rdg></app> في أمر الخل على ما قد علمته من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أين </lem><rdg resp="Diem “with a superfluous tooth”">أن</rdg></app> يدفعه 
<lb n="5"/>  الشّيخ أيّده اللّه إلي وانتظرت جوابك فلم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><sic n="superfluous">يأتني</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">پاپپى</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">يأتني</rdg></app> خبرا 
<lb n="6"/>  والآن أيّدك اللّه فقد قيل لي أنّه تجدّد خل <sic n="superfluous">باصر</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ماضر</supplied> فبعثه 
<lb n="7"/>  إلى قيرا فتنظر أيّدك اللّه كم جملته فتحسب 
<lb n="8"/>  ما كان لي وما يبقا منه واحتسب له به 
<lb n="9"/>  كما يبيع للخلق وأزن له دنانيره ولا 
<lb n="10"/>  تخلطه بغيره فأنت تعلم قديمي من الخل وتتفضّل 
<lb n="11"/>  بالجواب فقلبي معلّق به وإن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">احدر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أحدر</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> ـ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فتفضّل</rdg></app> 
<lb n="12"/>  وتعلمه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">كن </lem><rdg resp="APD">كم</rdg></app> لا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تحظر </lem><rdg resp="APD">تحظره</rdg></app> والسّلم عليك ورحمة اللّه وبركاته 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaḫ ī wa sayyid ī ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾadāma ʿizza ka wa karāmata ka wa taʾyīda ka 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ǧamaʿa la ka ḫayra ăd dunyā wa ăl ʾāḫiraẗi bi raḥmati hi qad katabtu kuntu yā sayyid ī 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ø ʾaʿraftu wāfaqtu ka fī ʾamri ăl ḫalli ʿalà mā qad ʿalimtu hu min ʾayna ʾan yadfaʿa yadfaʿu hu 
 <lb n="5"/>ăš šayḫu ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu ʾilay ya wa ĭntaẓartu ǧawāba ka fa lam taʾti yaʾti nī ḫabar:an ḫubr:an 
 <lb n="6"/>wa ăl ʾāna ʾayyada ka ăl lāhu fa qad qīla l ī ʾanna hu taǧaddada ḫall:un māḍir:un fa baʿaṯa hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾilà qīrā fa tanẓuru ʾayyada ka ăl lāhu kam ǧumlatu hu fa taḥsubu 
 <lb n="8"/>mā kāna l ī wa mā yabqā min hu wa ĭḥtasib la hu bi hi 
 <lb n="9"/>kamā yabīʿu li l ḫalqi wa ʾazinu la hu danānīra hu wa lā 
 <lb n="10"/>taḫliṭ hu bi ġayri hi fa ʾanta taʿlamu qadīm ī mina ăl ḫalli wa tatafaḍḍalu 
 <lb n="11"/>bi ăl ǧawābi fa qalb ī muʿallaq:un bi hi wa ʾin ʾaḥdara ʾḥdr **** m*** ø fa *** tafaḍḍal 
 <lb n="12"/>wa taʿlamu tuʿlima hu kun kam lā taḥẓur tuḥẓir ø hu wa ăs salāmu ʿalay ka wa raḥmaẗu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		My brother and lord - may God prolong your life and may He cause your might, honour and strength to continue,
			<lb n="3"/>
		and may He unite for you the best of the present world and of the world to come in His mercy -  I have already written, O my lord,
		Ich hatte mich, o mein Herr,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and informed you concerning the matter of vinegar according to that which I had already learned, whence the master handed it over to me
		mit Dir in der Angelegenheit des Essigs auf das Dir Bekannte geeinigt, nämlich daß
			<lb n="5"/>
		der Scheich - Gott stütze ihn - ihn mir aushändigen solle. Ich habe auf Deine Antwort gewartet, aber ich habe (von Dir) keine Nachricht erhalten.
		- may God strengthen him -, and I expected your reply, but you did not let me have any information.
			<lb n="6"/>
		Now - may God strengthen you - I have already been told that sour vinegar was newly made, and so he sent it
			<lb n="7"/>
		to Qîrâ. Now look and see - may God strengthen you - how much the total thereof is, then calculate
			<lb n="8"/>
		what belongs to me and what remains thereof, and put it  to his account
			<lb n="9"/>
		as he sells (it) to the people, and I will weigh him his dînârs; and do not
			<lb n="10"/>
		mix it with anything else. You well  know my old (stock) of vinegar, so favour me
			<lb n="11"/>
		... Wenn M....... das Niltal herabkommt, dann sei so gut
		with the reply, for my heart is attached to it, and in case ... ... ...
			<lb n="12"/>
		and you know it, do not take it for yourself. And hail to you and mercy and blessings of God.
		und teile ihm mit, wieviel (mein Essig ausmacht), (und) laß ihn nicht (eigens bei Dir) erscheinen! ...
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
