<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1099" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_66" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 066</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_66</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168965</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى إسطوروس التّنّيسي بن بيسه السّاكن مدينة الأشمونين من المكنّا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بأبُو </lem><rdg resp="APD">بأبو</rdg></app> العلا القزّاز بن مينا السّقّا السّاكن بهذا المدينة المّذكورة في هذا 
<lb n="3"/>  الكتاب اشترى منه بماله لنفسه الّذي أنعم اللّه عز وجل عليه جميع المنزل بأسره وكماله الّذي أعلمه أنّه له وبملكه وفي يده ملكا صحيحا وحقّا واجبا 
<lb n="4"/>  بهذه المدينة المذكورة في الجانب البحري منها على الكوم المطل على الكنيسيّة المعروفة بالبرتانس ويحيط بهذا المنزل المبيع بأسره وكماله ويجمعه 
<lb n="5"/>  ويشتمل عليه حدود أربعة فالحد القبلي منه ينتهي إلى الزّقاق النّافذ من طرفيه إلى طرق شتّى وفيه يشرع بابه الأوّل كان والحد البحري منه ينتهي إلى بير 
<lb n="6"/>  تعرف بالصّعيدي وإلى بو طوربن مقابر المسلمين وفي هذا الحد يشرع بابه الثّاني والحد الشّرقي منه ينتهي إلى عرصة لبقطر البنّا وإلى دار منصور 
<lb n="7"/>  الرّسول كان وإلى منزل يعرف بسكنى غطارف بن مفلح كان والحد الغربي منه ينتهي إلى منزل جعفر بن سباع الإبشادي فاشترى إسطوروس 
<lb n="8"/>  التّنّيسي بن بيسه من المكنّا بأبو العلا القزّاز بن مينا السّقّا جميع هذا المنزل المحدود الموصوف في هذا الكتاب بحدّه وحدوده ومرافقه كلّها 
<lb n="9"/>  بأرضه وسمائه وسفله وعلوه ونقضه وبناه وفنائه وكل قليل وكثير هو له داخل فيه وكل قليل وكثير هو له خارج منه وما هو معروف به 
<lb n="10"/>  ومنسوب إليه ظاهره وباطنه عامره وغامره صفقة واحدة بثمن مبلغه أربعة دنانير وازنة جياد العيون مستنصريّة 
<lb n="11"/>  مسلّمة للبائع من حق السّوق شرى صحيحا وبيعا نافذا ماضيا لا شرط فيه ولا خيار ولا استثنى ولا إقالة ولا إعادة ولا رجعة ولا مثنويّة لا لردّه ولا 
<lb n="12"/>  لفسخه لا لأجل ولا لأبد ولا هو على سبيل رهن ولا تلجئة ودفع المشتري إسطوروس التّنّيسي بن بيسه إلى البائع له المكنّا بأبو العلا القزّاز 
<lb n="13"/>  بن مينا السّقّا جميع الثّمن المذكور ومبلغه أربعة دنانير وازنة مستنصريّة مسلّمة للبائع من حق السّوق فقبضـهم منه نقدا في يده تامّا 
<lb n="14"/>  وافيا وأبرأه من ذلك براه قبض له واستيفا بجميعه من كل قول وحجّة ويمين على جميع الوجوه والأسباب كلّها وسلّم البائع إلى المشتري 
<lb n="15"/>  منه جميع ما وقّع عليه هذا البيع المذكور وتسلّمه منه وحازه لنفسه وصار في يده وملكه ومالا من ماله يتحكّم فيه بحكم الملّاك في أملاكهم 
<lb n="16"/>  وذلك بعد معرفة منهما لما تبايعا عليه وتقليب منهما بجميعه وإنفاذ منهما له فتبايعا ذلك بينهما على ما يوجبه حكم بيع الإسلام وعهدته 
<lb n="17"/>  وضمان دركه وتمام شروطه وتضمّن البائع للمشتري منه جميع الدّرك في ذمّته ومحيايه ومماته وخالص ماله فما أدرك هذا المشتري 
<lb n="18"/>  فيما وقّع عليه هذا البيع الكذكور أو في شي منه ومن حقوقه من درك من أحد من النّاس كلّهم فعلى البائع له خلاصه من كل درك يدركه في ذلك 
<lb n="19"/>  شهد على إقرار البائع بالبيع وقبضه جميع الثّمن المذكور والمشتري بالحوز لنفسه بجميع ما فيه بعد أن قرئ عليهما فأقرّا بفهمه 
<lb n="20"/>  ومعرفة جميعه في صحّة عقولهما وأبدانهما وجواز أمورهما طائعين غير مكرهين ولا مجبرين ولا مضطّهدين وكتب 
<lb n="21"/>  في العشر الأوّل من ربيع الأوّل من سنة اثني وأربعين وأربعماية شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="22 right"/>  شهد عبد اللّه بن أحمد بن تقا على إقرار البائع والمشتري 
<lb n="23 right"/>  بما فيه في تأريخه 
<lb n="22 left"/>  شهد إسحق بن نجا بن عطا على إقرار البائع والمشتري بما فيه في تأريخه 
<lb n="24 right"/>  شهد الحسين بن علي بنِ حفص 
<lb n="25 right"/>  على إڤرارِ البائع المسمّا في 
<lb n="26 right"/>  هذا الكتاب بالبيع 
<lb n="27 right"/>  وقبض الثّمنِ بما في تأرِيخه 
<lb n="28 right"/>  وحوز المشتري لنفسه 
<lb n="24 left"/>  شهد علي بن حفصِ بنِ علي بن حفص على إقرار البائع 
<lb n="25 left"/>  بالبيع وقبض التّمن المذكور وحوز المشترِي بما فيه 
<lb n="26 left"/>  وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="23 center"/>  شهد العبّاد بن هبة اللّه بن العقرب على إقرار البائع بالبيع 
<lb n="24 center"/>  وقبض جميع الثّمن المذكور وحوز المشتري بما فيه في تأرپخه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʾisiṭūrūsu ăt tinnīsiyyu bnu bīsaha ăs sākinu madīnaẗa ăl ʾušmūnayni mina ăl mukannā bi ʾabū ăl ʿalāʾi ăl qazzāzi bni mīnā ăs saqqāʾi ăs sākini bi hāḏā ăl madīnaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi fī hāḏā 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl kitābi ĭštarà min hu bi māli hi li nafsi hi ăllaḏī ʾanʿama ăl lāhu ʿazza wa ǧalla ʿalay hi ǧamīʿa ăl manzili bi ʾasri hi wa kamāli hi ăllaḏī ʾaʿlama hu ʾanna hu la hu wa bi milki hi wa fī yadi hi milk:an ṣaḥīḥ:an wa ḥaqq:an wāǧib:an 
 <lb n="4"/>bi hāḏihi ăl madīnaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi fī ăl ǧānibi ăl baḥriyyi min hā ʿalà ăl kawmi ăl muṭilli ʿalà ăl kunaysiyyaẗi ăl maʿrūfaẗi bi ăl bartānusi wa yuḥīṭu bi hāḏā ăl manzili ăl mabīʿi bi ʾasri hi wa kamāli hi wa yaǧmaʿu hu 
 <lb n="5"/>wa yaštamilu ʿalay hi ḥudūd:un ʾarbaʿaẗ:un fa ăl ḥaddu ăl qibliyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà ăz zuqāqi ăn nāfiḏi min ṭarafay hi ʾilà ṭuruq:in šattà wa fī hi yašraʿu bābu hu ăl ʾawwalu kāna wa ăl ḥaddu ăl baḥriyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà bīr:in 
 <lb n="6"/>tuʿrafu bi ăṣ ṣaʿīdiyyi wa ʾilà bū ṭūrbuna maqābiri ăl muslimīna wa fī hāḏā ăl ḥaddi yašraʿu bābu hu ăṯ ṯānī wa ăl ḥaddu ăš šarqiyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà ʿarṣaẗ:in li buqṭura ăl bannāʾi wa ʾilà dāri manṣūr:ini 
 <lb n="7"/>ăr rasūli kāna wa ʾilà manzil:in yuʿrafu bi suknà ġaṭārifa bni mufliḥ:in kāna wa ăl ḥaddu ăl ġarbiyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà manzili ǧaʿfara bni sibāʿa ăl ʾibšādiyyi fa ĭštarà ʾisiṭūrūsu 
 <lb n="8"/>ăt tinnīsiyyu bnu bīsaha mina ăl mukannā bi ʾabū ăl ʿalāʾi ăl qazzāzi bni mīnā ăs saqqāʾi ǧamīʿa hāḏā ăl manzili ăl maḥdūdi ăl mawṣūfi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi bi ḥaddi hi wa ḥudūdi hi wa marāfiqi hi kulli hā 
 <lb n="9"/>bi ʾarḍi hi wa samāʾi hi wa sufli hi wa ʿulwi hi wa naqḍi hi wa bināʾi hi wa fināʾi hi wa kulli qalīl:in wa kaṯīr:in huwa la hu dāḫil fī hi wa kulli qalīl:in wa kaṯīr:in huwa la hu ḫāriǧ min hu wa mā huwa maʿrūf:un bi hi 
 <lb n="10"/>wa mansūb:un ʾilay hi ẓāhira hu wa bāṭina hu ʿāmira hu wa ġāmira hu ṣafqaẗ:an wāḥidaẗ:an bi ṯaman:in mablaġu hu ʾarbaʿaẗu danānīra wāzinaẗ:un ǧiyādu ăl ʿuyūni mustanṣiriyyaẗ:un 
 <lb n="11"/>musallamaẗ:un li ăl bāʾiʿi min ḥaqqi ăs sūqi šir:an ṣaḥīḥ:an wa bayʿ:an nāfiḏ:an māḍiy:an lā šarṭa fī hi wa lā ḫiyār:un wa lā ĭstiṯn:an wa lā ʾiqālaẗ:un wa lā ʾiʿādaẗ:un wa lā raǧʿaẗ:un wa lā maṯnawiyyaẗ:un lā li raddi hi wa lā 
 <lb n="12"/>li fasḫi hi lā li ʾaǧal:in wa lā li ʾabad:in wa lā huwa ʿalà sabīli rahn:in wa lā talǧiʾaẗ:in wa dafaʿa ăl muštarī ʾisiṭūrūsu ăt tinnīsiyyu bnu bīsaha ʾilà ăl bāʾiʿi la hu ăl mukannā bi ʾabū ăl ʿalāʾi ăl qazzāzi 
 <lb n="13"/>bni mīnā ăs saqqāʾi ǧamīʿa ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūri wa mablaġu hu ʾarbaʿaẗu danānīra wāzinaẗ:un mustanṣiriyyaẗ:un musallamaẗ:un li ăl bāʾiʿi min ḥaqqi ăs sūqi fa qabaḍa hum min hu naqd:an fī yadi hi tāmm:an 
 <lb n="14"/>wāfiy:an wa ʾabraʾa hu min ḏālika barāʾaẗa qabḍ:in la hu wa ĭstīfāʾ:in bi ǧamīʿi hi min kulli qawl:in wa ḥuǧǧaẗ:in wa yamīn:in ʿalà ǧamīʿi ăl wuǧūhi wa ăl ʾasbābi kulli hā wa sallama ăl bāʾiʿu ʾilà ăl muštarī 
 <lb n="15"/>min hu ǧamīʿa mā waqaʿa ʿalay hi hāḏā ăl bayʿu ăl maḏkūru wa tasallama hu min hu wa ḥāza hu li nafsi hi wa ṣāra fī yadi hi wa milki hi wa māl:an min māli hi yataḥakkamu fī hi bi ḥukmi ăl mullāki fī ʾamlāki him 
 <lb n="16"/>wa ḏālika baʿda maʿrifaẗ:in min humā li mā tabāyaʿā ʿalay hi wa taqlīb:in min humā bi ǧamīʿi hi wa ʾinfāḏ:in min humā la hu fa tabāyaʿā ḏālika bayna humā ʿalà mā yūǧibu hu ḥukmu bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdatu hu 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ḍamānu daraki hi wa tamāmu šurūṭi hi wa taḍammana ăl bāʾiʿu li ăl muštarī min hu ǧamīʿa ăd daraki fī ḏimmati hi wa maḥyāyi hi wa mamāti hi wa ḫāliṣi māli hi fa mā ʾadraka hāḏā ăl muštariya 
 <lb n="18"/>fī mā waqaʿa ʿalay hi hāḏā ăl bayʿu ăl maḏkūru ʾaw fī šayʾ:in min hu wa min ḥuqūqi hi min darak:in min ʾaḥad:in mina ăn nāsi kulli him fa ʿalà ăl bāʾiʿi la hu ḫalāṣu hu min kulli darak:in yudriku hu fī ḏālika 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi bi ăl bayʿi wa qabḍi hi ǧamīʿa ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūri wa ăl muštarī bi ăl ḥawzi li nafsi hi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay himā fa ʾaqarrā bi fahmi hi 
 <lb n="20"/>wa maʿrifaẗi ǧamīʿi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿuqūli himā wa ʾabdāni himā wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri himā ṭāʾiʿayni ġayra mukrahayni wa lā muǧbarayni wa lā muḍṭahadayni wa kutiba 
 <lb n="21"/>fī ăl ʿašri ăl ʾawwali min rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali min sanaẗi ĭṯnay wa ʾarbaʿīna wa ʾarbaʿi miyaẗ:in šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu ʾaḥmada bni tuqā ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī 
 <lb n="23"/>bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="24"/>šahida ʾisḥāqu bnu naǧāʾa bni ʿaṭāʾa ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="25"/>šahida ăl ḥusaynu bnu ʿaliyyi bni ḥafṣ:in 
 <lb n="26"/>ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi ăl musammā fī 
 <lb n="27"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi bi ăl bayʿi 
 <lb n="28"/>wa qabḍi ăṯ ṯamani bi mā fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="29"/>wa ḥawzi ăl muštarī li nafsi hi 
 <lb n="30"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ḥafṣi bni ʿaliyyi bni ḥafṣ:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi 
 <lb n="31"/>bi ăl bayʿi wa qabḍi ăt tamani ăl maḏkūri wa ḥawzi ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi 
 <lb n="32"/>wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="33"/>šahida ăl ʿabbādu bnu hibaẗi ăl lāhi bni ăl ʿaqrabi ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi bi ăl bayʿi 
 <lb n="34"/>wa qabḍi ǧamīʿi ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūri wa ḥawzi ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Isiṭôrôs, originating from Tinnîs, son of Bîsa, residing in the town of al-Ušmûnain, has bought from the surnamed Abuʾl ʿAlâ, the silk-mercer, son of Mînâ, the water-carrier, residing in the town, which is mentioned in this
			<lb n="3"/>
		act: he has bought from him with his own money, which God - He is mighty and sublime - has bestowed upon him as a favour, the whole dwelling house entirely and completely, that he (the seller) informed him that it was belonging to him and in his possession and in his hand(s) as a legal possession and a declared right, situated
			<lb n="4"/>
		at the north side of this (above) mentioned town, on the hill looking down upon the little church known as al-Bartânos (of the Virgin). Now four boundaries enclose, encompass and surround this dwelling house sold entirely and completely:
			<lb n="5"/>
		the southern boundary thereof extends to the lane forming from both sides the thoroughfare to diverse roads, with which its former first door communicates; and the northern boundary thereof extends to a well
			<lb n="6"/>
		known as aṣ-Ṣaʿîdî and to Bû Ṭûrbon, the Muslim cemetery, and with this boundary communicates its second door; and the eastern boundary thereof extends to the open area belonging to Boqṭor, the builder, and to the former house of Manṣûr,
			<lb n="7"/>
		the messenger, and to the dwelling house known as the former habitation of Ġaṭârif b. Mufliḥ; and the western boundary thereof extends to the dwelling house of Ǧaʿfar b. Sibâʿ, originating from Ibšâda. Isiṭôrôs,
			<lb n="8"/>
		originating from Tinnîs, son of Bîsa, has bought from the surnamed Abuʾl-ʿAlâ, the silk-mercer, son of Mînâ, the water-carrier, the whole of this dwelling house defined and described in this act, to its limit and its boundaries and all its appurtenances,
			<lb n="9"/>
		with its land and its sky, and (including) what is below and above the surface, and its beams and its building(s) and its fore-court, and all of little and much connected with it within, and all of little and much connected with it without, and what is known as appertaining
			<lb n="10"/>
		and relating to it, (be it) outside or inside, inhabited or empty, in one striking (of hands), for a price which amounts to four dînârs in full weight good gold-coins of al-Mustanṣir
			<lb n="11"/>
		handed over to the seller according to the market-value, in form of a valid purchase and an effectual (and fully) completed sale in which is no condition and no option (of return) and no reservation and no rescision (by mutual consent) and no possibility of recurrence and no proviso of the right of reversal and no reserving (of the right) either to return it or
			<lb n="12"/>
		to annul it, either temporarily or for good, and it is not in the way of a pledge nor an exclusive bequest. And the buyer Isiṭôrôs, originating from Tinnîs, son of Bîsa, has paid to the one who has sold it to him, the surnamed Abuʾl-ʿAlâ, the silk-mercer,
			<lb n="13"/>
		son of Mînâ, the water-carrier, the whole of the (above) mentioned price, the amount of which is four full weight-dînârs of al-Mustanṣir, handed over to the seller according to the market-value. So he has received it from him as a cash-payment (paid) into his hand(s) fully,
			<lb n="14"/>
		entirely, and he has given him a quittance for it by means of a receipt (acknowledging that he has) received for him(self) fully and entirely the whole of it, which releases him from any affirmation or proof or oath for any causes or reasons whatever; and the seller has handed over to the one who has bought
			<lb n="15"/>
		from him all in respect to which the (above) mentioned sale was effected, and he (the buyer) has taken it over from him and has acquired possession of it for himself and it has passed into his possession and his hand(s) and has become his property, he having free disposition of it according to the free disposition of proprietors over their property,
			<lb n="16"/>
		and this after their having been aware of what they both have sold and bought (respectively) and their having examined all of it and their having effected it (the transaction). So they both have bargained together according to what the rule of Islamic law of sale and covenant
			<lb n="17"/>
		and the guarantee of indemnity and the fulfilment of its conditions makes obligatory, and the seller has become responsible to the one who has bought from him for all claims according to his responsibility, be he alive or dead, and out of his own means. But should any evil consequence (vindicatio) ensue to this buyer
			<lb n="18"/>
		respecting that about which this (above) mentioned sale took place of respecting any part of it, or any rights (connected with it) from any person, it is incumbent upon the one who has sold (it) to him to indemnify him for any claim that may be made upon him in respect thereto.
			<lb n="19"/>
		(The following witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the seller respecting the sale and his taking over the whole of the price mentioned, and by the buyer respecting his having taken possession for himself of all that is herein, after (it) had been read to both of them, so that they have acknowledged that they have understood
			<lb n="20"/>
		and comprehended it entirely, they being in a state of sound mind and body and capable of transacting their business, voluntarily, without compulsion and not against their will and not under constraint, and (it) has been written
			<lb n="21"/>
		in the first decade of Rabîʿ I of the year four hundred and forty two. (The following witnesses) have testified to it.
			<lb n="22"/>
		ʿAbdallâh b. Ahmad b. Tuqâ is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer
			<lb n="23"/>
		respecting what (is contained) herein on its date.
			<lb n="24"/>
		Isḥâq b. Naǧâ b. ʿAṭâ is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer respecting what (is contained) herein on its date.
			<lb n="25"/>
		Al-Ḥusain b. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ is witness
			<lb n="26"/>
		to the acknowledgment by the seller named in
			<lb n="27"/>
		this act respecting the sale
			<lb n="28"/>
		and the taking over the price respecting what (is contained) herein on its date
			<lb n="29"/>
		and the taking possession by the buyer.
			<lb n="30"/>
		ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ b. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller
			<lb n="31"/>
		respecting the sale and the taking over the (above) mentioned price and the taking possession by the buyer respecting what is herein
			<lb n="32"/>
		and he has written in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="33"/>
		Al-ʿAbbâd b. Hibatallâh b. al-ʿAqrab is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller respecting the sale
			<lb n="34"/>
		and the taking over the whole of the (above) mentioned price and the taking possession by the buyer respecting what (is contained) herein on its date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
