<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="430" xml:id="Grohmann_TWAe_2" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.GrohmannWirtsch. 02 (= P.World p. 168)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_TWAe_2</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106625</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="recto 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="recto 2"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حفظـ</supplied>ـك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أكرمك</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأطال </lem><rdg resp="Diem">اللّه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">اللّه </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وحفظك</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بقاك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأبقاك</rdg></app> وأتم نعمه عليك وزاد فيها وفي إحسانه إليك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ونخبرك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وعندك</rdg></app> 
<lb n="recto 3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـا </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”">في</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الپك </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”">كتابنا </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">كتبنا</rdg></app> وپحن ڤى عافيه والحمد لله كپپرا كما هو اهله ومسپحڤه وصل كپاپك وما وحهت به 
<lb n="recto 4"/>  ووزن الدّينر والقطعتين دينر ونصف وثمن ودانق أخذت <app type="BL"><lem resp="Grohmann, Wirtschaft; Grohmann, World in translation, but differently in edition; Diem">لك </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World in edition, but differently in translation”">له</rdg></app> خمسة أقزاز قراطيس بدينر غير 
<lb n="recto 5"/>  ثلثي قيراط وهي أجود ما قدرنا عليه من الوسط لم نجد أجود منها إلّا أربعة بدينر وسدس على أنّه 
<lb n="recto 6"/>  قد أحسن إلينا من ذلك وقد أخذت هذه منه <app type="BL"><lem resp="Grohmann, Wirtschaft; Diem">بالخيار </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”">بالخير</rdg></app> على أن تراها فإن رضيتها أخذتها وإن لم 
<lb n="recto 7"/>  ترضاها <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وردتها </lem><rdg resp="Dietrich; Diem">رددتّها</rdg></app> وأخذت لك <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, Wirtschaft; Grohmann, World in translation, but differently in edition”">أرفع </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World in edition, but differently in translation; Diem">أربع</rdg></app> منها بهذا السّعر الّذي ذكرت لك وأخذت لك ثمنية 
<lb n="recto 8"/>  حزم بزّا بسدس دينر مشدودة رزمة واحدة وأخذت لك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ثلث </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ثلثة</rdg></app> أرباع قفيز زبيب بنصف 
<lb n="recto 9"/>  دينر <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وويبتي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وويبتين</rdg></app> إلّا ثلث لوز بنصف دينر وستّة أقداح ونصف رز بربع دينر على ويبة ونصف ونصف 
<lb n="recto 10"/>  ربع بدينر وأخذت لك قسط <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">من </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مرّ</rdg></app> رطل ونصف ووقيّة بالغيلاني بسدس على تسعة أرطال 
<lb n="recto 11"/>  ونصف بدينر وأخذت لك مسك بسدس في أربع قوارير وأخذت درهم ودانق كافور <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تصاعد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مصاعد</rdg></app> 
<lb n="recto 12"/>  بثمن دينر ونصف قيراط <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وجعلته </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World">وجعلت</rdg></app> كلّه في التّلّيس فذلك ثلثة دنانير غير ثمن ودانق وقد بقي 
<lb n="recto 13"/>  لك عندنا قيراطين بعد كرى الحمّال وذلك أن خرّجت لك الدّراهم على ثمنية عشر بدينر فاعلم ذلك 
<lb n="recto 14"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ورّاتك </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World, and Diem">ورأيك</rdg></app> في الكتاب بخبرك وحالك وحوائجك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تسرّنا </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World, and Diem, P.Berl.Arab.">تسرّنا </rdg><rdg resp="Diem, Review Wien">فتسرّنا</rdg></app> بذلك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حضّر </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann, World, and Diem">خصّ</rdg></app> نفسك بالسّلم كثيرا كثيرا وعلى 
<lb n="recto 15"/>  من أحببت من أصحابنا السّلم كثيرا والسّلم عليك ورحمت اللّه وبركاتـه 
<lb n="verso 1"/>  لأبي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">القسم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">جعفر</rdg></app> أكرمه اللّه من إبرهيم 
<lb n="verso 2"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, World”"><gap reason="illegible" extent="7" unit="character" /></rdg></app> بن ملك العطّار 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ḥafiẓa ʾakrama ka wa ăl ʾaṭāla lāhu ăl wa lāhu ḥafiẓa ø ka baqāʾa wa ka ʾabqā ø ka wa ʾatamma niʿama hu ʿalay ka wa zāda fī hā wa fī ʾiḥsāni hi ʾilay ka wa nuḫbiru ʿinda ka 
 <lb n="3"/>ø fī ***ʾ kitābi katabnā nā ø ʾilay ka wa naḥnu fī ʿāfiyaẗ:in wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi kaṯīr:an kamā huwa ʾahlu hu wa mustaḥiqqu hu waṣala kitābu ka wa mā waǧǧahta bi hi 
 <lb n="4"/>wa waznu ăd dīnāri wa ăl qiṭʿatayni dīnār wa niṣf wa ṯumn wa dānaq ʾaḫaḏtu la ka hu ḫamsaẗa ʾaqzāzi qarāṭīsa bi dīnār:in ġayra 
 <lb n="5"/>ṯulṯay qīrāṭ:in wa hiya ʾaǧwadu mā qadarnā ʿalay hi mina ăl wasaṭi lam naǧid ʾaǧwada min hā ʾillā ʾarbaʿaẗ:an bi dīnār:in wa suds:in ʿalà ʾanna hu 
 <lb n="6"/>qad ʾaḥsana ʾilay nā min ḏālika wa qad ʾaḫaḏtu hāḏihi min hu bi ăl ḫiyāri ḫayri ʿalà ʾan tarā hā fa ʾin raḍīta hā ʾaḫaḏta hā wa ʾin lam 
 <lb n="7"/>tarḍā hā wa ø radatta radadta hā wa ʾaḫaḏtu la ka ʾarfaʿa ʾarbaʿa min hā bi hāḏā ăs siʿri ăllaḏī ḏakartu la ka wa ʾaḫaḏtu la ka ṯamāniyaẗa 
 <lb n="8"/>ḥuzum:in bazz:an bi sudsi dīnār:in mašdūdaẗ:an rizmaẗ:an wāḥidaẗ:an wa ʾaḫaḏtu la ka ṯalāṯa ṯalāṯaẗa ʾarbāʿi qafīzi zabīb:in bi niṣfi 
 <lb n="9"/>dīnār:in wa waybatay waybatayni ʾillā ṯulṯi lawz:in bi niṣfi dīnār:in wa sittaẗa ʾaqdāḥ:in wa niṣfa ruzz:in bi rubʿi dīnār:in ʿalà waybaẗ:in wa niṣf:in wa niṣfi 
 <lb n="10"/>rubʿ:in bi dīnār:in wa ʾaḫaḏtu la ka qisṭ min murr raṭl:in wa niṣf:in wa wuqiyyaẗ:in bi ăl ġaylāniyyi bi suds:in ʿalà tisʿaẗi ʾarṭāl:in 
 <lb n="11"/>wa niṣf:in bi dīnār:in wa ʾaḫaḏtu la ka misk bi suds:in fī ʾarbaʿi qawārīra wa ʾaḫaḏtu dirham wa dānaqa kāfūr:in taṣāʿada muṣāʿad:in 
 <lb n="12"/>bi ṯumni dīnār:in wa niṣfi qīrāṭ:in wa ǧaʿaltu hu ø kulla hu fī ăt tallīsi fa ḏālika ṯalāṯaẗu danānīra ġayra ṯumn:in wa dānaq:in wa qad baqiya 
 <lb n="13"/>la ka ʿinda nā qīrāṭayni baʿda kirà ăl ḥammāli wa ḏālika ʾan ḫurriǧat la ka ăd darāhimu ʿalà ṯamāniyaẗa ʿašara bi dīnār:in fa iʿlam ḏālika 
 <lb n="14"/>wa warrātu ø raʾyu ka fī ăl kitābi bi ḫabari ka wa ḥāli ka wa ḥawāʾiǧi ka ø fa baššir tasurru nā bi ḏālika ḥaḍḍir ḫuṣṣi nafsa ka bi ăs salāmi kaṯīr:an kaṯīr:an wa ʿalà 
 <lb n="15"/>man ʾaḥbabta min ʾaṣḥābi nā ăs salāmu kaṯīr:an wa ăs salāmu ʿalay ka wa raḥmatu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu 
 <lb n="16"/>li ʾabī ăl ǧaʿfara qāsimi ʾakrama hu ăl lāhu min ʾibrāhīma 
 <lb n="17"/>*** ******* bni malik:ini ăl ʿaṭṭāri 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes des Barmherzigen, Gütigen!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!
			<lb n="2"/>
		(Gott) [behüte (?)] Dich und lasse Dich lange leben und vollende seine Gnaden an Dir und vermehre sie und seine Wohltaten an Dir. Wir benachrichtigen Dich
		May He protect thee and may God prolong thy life and fulfil His loving kindness unto thee and may He increase this and His bounty unto thee. We inform thee
			<lb n="3"/>
		[by] our (letter) to thee while we are in health, and praise be to God many times, as He deserves it and is entitled to it. Thy letter and that which thou hast sent have arrived as well as
		... Dein Schreiben und das, was Du mir (an Geld) übersandt hast, ist eingetroffen;
		....... Dir während wir uns wohl befinden - und Gott sei vielmals Preis wie er es verdient und beanspruchen kann. Dein Schreiben und das, was Du zusandtest, ist eingetroffen
			<lb n="4"/>
		sowie das Dīnārgewicht und die beiden (Münz-) Stücke zu einem Dīnār und einem halben und einem Achtel-Dīnār und einem Dāniq. Ich habe für Dich (um diesen Betrag) fünf gläserne Behältnisse für Papyrusrollen um einen Dīnār weniger
		the dînâr-weight and the two pieces (of coin) viz. one dînâr and a half and an eighth and a dâniq. I have taken for thee five glass-receptacles for papyrus-rolls for one dînâr, less
		und das Gewicht des Dinars und der beiden (Dinar)bruchstücke belief sich auf einen Dinar, einen halben und ein Achtel Dinar und einen Daniq
			<lb n="5"/>
		two thirds of a carat, and they are the best we could get of medium (size or quality), we did not find better than those, save four for one dînâr and a sixth, whereby he (the seller)
		zwei Drittel Karat genommen; es sind dies unter denen von mittlerer Qualität die besten, die wir aufzutreiben vermochten; bessere als sie haben wir nicht gefunden, es sei denn vier (Stück) um einen halben und einen Sechstel-Dīnār, wobei er sich
			<lb n="6"/>
		uns gegenüber schon diesbezüglich entgegenkommend gezeigt hatte. Ich habe also diese von ihm zur Auswahl genommen, unter der Bedingung, daß Du sie Dir ansiehst. Solltest Du damit zufrieden sein, so mögest Du sie nehmen; wenn Du aber
		was obliging us therein. - So I have taken this from him for preference under condition that thou mightest see it. If thou art satisfied therewith, take it, and if thou
			<lb n="7"/>
		art not satisfied with it, give it back. I have taken the best of it for the price which I have mentioned unto thee. And I took for thee eight
		nicht damit zufrieden bist, so mögest Du sie zurückgeben. Ich habe für Dich die allerbesten unter ihnen um den Preis genommen, den ich Dir angegeben habe. Ferner nahm ich für Dich acht
			<lb n="8"/>
		linen-girdles for a sixth of a dînâr, tied together in one bundle. Furthermore I took for thee three quarters of a qafîz of large raisins for half
		Linnengürtel um einen Sechstel-Dīnār, sämtliche in einem Bündel zusammengebunden; weiters nahm ich für Dich drei Viertel-Qafīz Zibeben um einen halben
			<lb n="9"/>
		a dînâr, and two less one third waiba almonds for half a dînâr, and six and a half qadaḥ rice for a quarter of a dînâr, at two and a half and an eighth waiba
		Dīnār und zwei weniger ein Drittel Waiba Mandeln um einen halben Dīnār und sechs und einen halben Qadaḥ Reis um einen Viertel-Dīnār zu eineinhalb und einer Achtel Waiba
			<lb n="10"/>
		... Ferner besorgte ich Dir Bitterkostwurz, eineinhalb Pfund und eine Unze ... um ein sechstel (Dinar) ...
		for one dînâr. Then I have taken for thee one xestes containig one and a half pound and one ounce according to the Ghailânî (weight) at nine
		for one dînâr. Then I have taken for thee one xestes containig one and a half pound and one ounce according to the Ghailânî (weight) of a sixth at nine
		um einen Dīnār. Sodann habe ich für Dich genommen ein Xestes zu einem und einem halben Pfunde und einer Unze nach ġailānitischem Maße zu neun 
			<lb n="11"/>
		and half a pound for one dînâr. And I have taken for thee musk for a sixth (of a dînâr) in four bottles and I have taken one dirham and one dâniq sublimated camphor
		einhalb Pfund um einen Dīnār. Ferner habe ich für Dich um einen Sechstel Dīnār Moschus in vier Fläschchen genommen, ferner habe ich einen Dirham und einen Dāniq sublimierten Kampfer
			<lb n="12"/>
		for an eighth of a dînâr and half a carat. All this I put in a sack. That makes three dînârs less an eighth and a dâniq. There remain therefore
		um einen Achtel-Dīnār und einen halben Karat genommen. Alles dies tat ich in einen Sack. Das macht also drei Dīnāre weniger einen Achtel (Dīnār) und einen Dāniq. Es verbleiben daher
			<lb n="13"/>
		to thy credit with us after deduction of the hire of the porter two carats reckoning the rate of the dirham at eighteen the dînâr. So take notice thereof;
		zu Deinen Gunsten bei uns nach (Abzug) der Miethe des Lastträgers zwei Karate, indem Dir die Dirhams zum Kurse von achtzehn auf einen Dīnār berechnet wurden. Nimm dies also zur Kenntnis.
			<lb n="14"/>
		and mightest thou consider (to send) a letter about thy news, thy situation and thy requirements, thou wilst give us pleasure therewith. Please receive (our) special reiterated greetings, and to
		Ich habe Dir im Briefe Deinen (Geschäfts)stand, Deine (augenblickliche) Lage und Deine nothwendigen Bedürfnisse aufgezeigt, erfreu und diesbezüglich mit guter Nachricht. Sei vielmals gegrüßt, und
			<lb n="15"/>
		anyone of our friends thou likest many greetings. And peace unto thee and the mercy of God.
		viele Grüße auch an wen Du willst von unseren Freunden. Heil Dir und Barmherzigkeit und Segnungen Gottes.
			<lb n="16"/>
		An Abu-ʾl-Qāsim, - Gott erweise sich ihm wohltätig - von Ibrahīm ...
		To Abu&#039;l-Qâsim - may God benefit him - from Ibrahîm
			<lb n="17"/>
		............ b. Malik, dem Droguisten.
		Ibn Malik, the druggist.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
