<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="353" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_138" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 138 (= Chrest.Khoury I 76)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_138</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106583</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـم</supplied> الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـلّه</supplied> الرّحـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمن</supplied> الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـرّ</supplied>حيـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـم</supplied> 
<lb n="2"/>  أ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">قرّ</supplied> كل واحد <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـپ <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>كريمة ولدين مطروح الأجير عند شهود 
<lb n="3"/>  هذا <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الكتاب</supplied> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شهدهم</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="AK">وأشهداهم</rdg></app> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>نفسهما في صحّة عقلهما وبدنهما وجواز أمورهـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمـ</supplied>ـا 
<lb n="4"/>  طائعين <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>نّهما التسما جميع ما <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">خـ</supplied>ـ<sic n="superfluous">لّقته</sic> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حـ</supplied>ـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـلفته</supplied> پهما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">والدتهما </lem><rdg resp="APD">نوينه</rdg></app> پوپپه اپپه 
<lb n="5"/>  بن حسن المريسي من رجل وبنات <sic n="superfluous">وقنثه</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">وقنية</supplied> وآلة وآيات وتسلّم كل واحد 
<lb n="6"/>  جميع حقّه وحصّته على فرائض اللّه عز وجل لتذكّر سبل خط الأثرين ولم يبقا 
<lb n="7"/>  لواحد منهما قبل صاحبه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">جميع</supplied> ما خلّفته والدتهما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تويبة </lem><rdg resp="APD">نوينة</rdg></app> المتوفّاة عنهما 
<lb n="8"/>  بمدينة الأشمونيـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـن</supplied> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">قليل</unclear> و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لا</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كثيـ</supplied>ـر ولا دعوا ولا طلبة ولا قول ولا حجّة 
<lb n="9"/>  ولا يمين على جميع <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـو<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">جـ</supplied>ـوه والأسباب كلّها ولم يبقا <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">بينهم</unclear>ا شركة في جميع ما خلّفته 
<lb n="10"/>  والدتهما غير المنزل الّذي خلّفته والدتهما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تويبة </lem><rdg resp="APD">نوينة</rdg></app> بخط حمّام طبري وبرئ كل 
<lb n="11"/>  واحد منهما من صاحبه بعد أن عرف كل واحد منهما حقّه وحصّته وتسلّمه 
<lb n="12"/>  وصار في يده وكل دعوا يدّعى بواحد منهما على صاحبه أو يدّعى ذلك له أو أحد 
<lb n="13"/>  نسبه في حياته أو بعد وفاته باطل دعواه ومن يدّعى له وإفك وعدوان 
<lb n="14"/>  شهد على إقرار الأخوين المقرّان بعضهما بـبعض بجميع ما فيه بعد أن قرئ عليهما 
<lb n="15"/>  وأقرّا بفهمه في العشر الأواخر من شهر رمضان سنة اثني عشر وأربع مائة وكتب هذا 
<lb n="16"/>  الإقرار <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لحي </lem><rdg resp="APD">لحين </rdg><rdg resp="Khoury">نسختين</rdg></app> بيد كل واحد منهما كتبه حجّة له وعليه شهد على ذلك 
<lb n="17 right"/>  شهد محمّد بن يوسف بن طيب على إقرار 
<lb n="18 right"/>  الرّجل والمرأة المقرّين بما <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">فيـ</supplied>ـه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> تأريخه 
<lb n="17 left"/>  شهد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">سريج </lem><rdg resp="APD">سريج</rdg></app> بن علي بن الحسين على إقرارهما بما فيه في تأريخه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaqarra kullu wāḥid:in **** ***B *** *** wa karīmaẗu waladayni maṭrūḥa ăl ʾaǧīri ʿinda šuhūdi 
 <lb n="3"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ʾašhada ʾašhadā hum ʿalà ʾanfusi himā fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿaqli himā wa badani himā wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri himā 
 <lb n="4"/>ṭāʾiʿayni ʾanna humā ĭltasamā ǧamīʿa mā ḫallafat hu bi himā wālidatu humā nuwaynaẗu tuwaybaẗu ĭbnaẗu hudayy:i 
 <lb n="5"/>bni ḥasan:in ăl marīsiyyi min riǧāl:in wa banāt:in wa qunyaẗ:in wa ʾālaẗ:in wa ʾāyāt:in wa tasallama kullu wāḥid:in 
 <lb n="6"/>ǧamīʿa ḥaqqi hi wa ḥiṣṣati hi ʿalà farāʾiḍi ăl lāhi ʿazza wa ǧalla li taḏakkuri subula ḫaṭṭi ḫuṭṭi ăl ʾaṯarayni wa lam yabqā 
 <lb n="7"/>li wāḥid:in min humā qibala ṣāḥibi hi fī ǧamīʿi mā ḫallafat hu wālidatu humā nuwaynaẗu tuwaybaẗu ăl mutawaffāẗu ʿan humā 
 <lb n="8"/>bi madīnaẗi ăl ʾušmūnayni qalīl:un wa lā kaṯīr:un wa lā daʿw:an wa lā ṭalibaẗ:un wa lā qawl:un wa lā ḥuǧǧaẗ:un 
 <lb n="9"/>wa lā yamīn:un ʿalà ǧamīʿi ăl wuǧūhi wa ăl ʾasbābi kulli hā wa lam yabqā bayna humā širkaẗ:un fī ǧamīʿi mā ḫallafat hu 
 <lb n="10"/>wālidatu humā ġayru ăl manzili ăllaḏī ḫallafat hu wālidatu humā nuwaynaẗu tuwaybaẗu bi ḫaṭṭi ḥammāmi ṭabariyy:in wa bariʾa kullu 
 <lb n="11"/>wāḥid:in min humā min ṣāḥibi hi baʿda ʾan ʿarafa kullu wāḥid:in min humā ḥaqqa hu wa ḥiṣṣata hu wa tasallama hu 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ṣāra fī yadi hi wa kullu daʿw:an yuddaʿà bi wāḥid:in min humā ʿalà ṣāḥibi hi ʾaw yuddaʿà ḏālika la hu ʾaw ʾaḥadi 
 <lb n="13"/>nasabi hi fī ḥayāti hi ʾaw baʿda wafāti hi bāṭil:un daʿwā hu wa man yuddaʿà la hu wa ʾifk:un wa ʿudwān:un 
 <lb n="14"/>šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl ʾaḫawayni ăl muqirrāni baʿḍi himā bi baʿḍ:in bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay himā 
 <lb n="15"/>wa ʾaqarrā bi fahmi hi fī ăl ʿašri ăl ʾawāḫiri min šahri ramaḍāna sanaẗa ĭṯnay ʿašara wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in wa kutiba hāḏā 
 <lb n="16"/>ăl ʾiqrāru lḥy liḥyānu nusḫatayni bi yadi kulli wāḥid:in min humā kataba hu ḥuǧǧaẗ:an la hu wa ʿalay hi šahida ʿalà ḏālika 
 <lb n="17"/>šahida muḥammadu bnu yūsufa bni ṭīb:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="18"/>ăr raǧuli wa ăl marʾaẗi ăl muqirrayni bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida surayǧu šurayḥu bnu ʿaliyyi bni ăl ḥusayni ʿalà ʾiqrāri himā bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Au n[om] de Di[eu] clé[ment] et mi[sé]ricor[dieux]!
		In the na[me] of Go[d], the Compassion[ate], the Me[r]cifu[l].
			<lb n="2"/>
		Both [........... viz. So and So and] Karîma, the two children of Maṭrûḥ, the journeyman, have acknowledged in the presence of the witnesses
		Chacun des [….] a re[con]nu […. et] Karīma, tout les deux enfants du journalier Maṭrūḥ, en présence des témoins
			<lb n="3"/>
		de ce [document], et [ils pirent à t´moin], étant dans la plénitude de leurs facultés  mentales et physiques et leur capacité juridique,
		of this [deed] having cal[led them to witness as to] their obligation they being in a state of sound mind and body and capable of transacting  thei[r] business,
			<lb n="4"/>
		de leur gré, qu’ils ont sollicité tout ce que leur a [l]aissé en héritage leur mère Tuwayba, fille de Huda[yy]
		voluntarily, [th]at both of them have demanded all that their mother Tuwaiba, daughter of Huda[yy]
			<lb n="5"/>
		b. Ḥasan, originating from Marîs, has left to them of men, maids, goods and chattels, tools and effects, and each of them has taken over
		Ibn Ḥasan al-Marīsī, comme hommes, filles, biens, outils et objets, et que chacun d’eux a prix
			<lb n="6"/>
		all his portion and share according to the ordinance of God - He is mighty and sublime - (binding himself) to be mindful of the public drinking fountains of the street of the &#034;two monuments&#034;; and there does not remain
		toute sa portion contingente et sa part, selon les prescriptions de Dieu, il est grand et puissant, (s’engageant) à se souvenir du puits public dans “le Quartier des Deux Monuments”; et il ne reste
			<lb n="7"/>
		à l’un d’eux auprès de son partenaire [en tout] ce que leur mère décédée Tuwayba leur a laissée en héritage
		for either of them from the side of his partner [in respect to all] that which their mother Tuwaiba, removed from them (by death)
			<lb n="8"/>
		dans la ville d’al-Ušmūnay [n] ni peu, ni [beaucoup], ni (cause d’une) action en justice, ni réclamation, ni d´position, ni acte probant,
		in the town of al-Ušmûnai[n], had left, little o[r much] or any cause for an action or claim or statement or any means of evidence
			<lb n="9"/>
		ni serment de n’importe quelle manière ou pour n’importe quel motif que ce soit; et il n’est resté entre eux deux aucun bien commun, en tout ce qu’a laissèe en héritage
		or oath for any causes or reasons whatever, and there does not remain between the two any common ownership in respect to all that which
			<lb n="10"/>
		leur mère, sauf la maison que Tuwayba a laissée en héritage dans “le Quartier du Bain Ṭabarī”. Et chacun
		their mother has left but the dwellinghouse in the street of Ṭabarî&#039;s bath which their mother Tuwaiba has left, and each of them
			<lb n="11"/>
		d’eux a été acquitté par son partenaire, après que chacun a pris connaiccance de sa portion contingente et de sa part, les a prises
		has released his partner after both of them had taken cognizance of his portion and share and had taken it over
			<lb n="12"/>
		and it had passed into his hand(s). And any action that is brought in by either of them against his partner - be it brought in for him or
		et est entré en possession de cela. Et chaque plainte que porterait en justice l’un d’eux contre son partenaire, ou que quelqu’un
			<lb n="13"/>
		de sa parenté porterait pour lui durant sa vie ou après sa mort, serait de nulle valeur, peu importe qui la revendiquerait pour lui, et mensonge et action illégitime.
		for one of his family, during his life or after his death - (then) his action (shall be groundless) and he for whom it had been brought in (shall be) without title, and (the action) a fraud and an unjust proceeding.
			<lb n="14"/>
		Témoins de la reconnaissance des deux frère et soeur qui tous les deux ont reconnu tout ce qui se trouve dans (ce document), après que celui-ci leur a été lu,
		(Witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the brother and sister who have mutually acknowledged all that (is contained) herein after (it) had been read to both of them,
			<lb n="15"/>
		and they have acknowledged that they have understood it, in the last decade of the month of Ramaḍân of the year four hundred and twelve. And this
		et qui ont reconnu l’avoir compris dans la dernière décade du mois de Ramaḍān de l’année quatre cent douze, et
			<lb n="16"/>
		acknowledgment has been written ....... by the hand (?) of each of them, who has written it as a proof for him and as to his obligation. (The following witnesses) have testified to it:
		cette reconnaissance fut écrite en deux copies, une copie de la main de chacund’entre eux deux, comme preuve pour et contre lui: témoins de cela:
			<lb n="17"/>
		A témoigné Muḥammad Ibn Yūsuf Ibn Ṭīb de la reconnaissance 
		Witness is Muḥammad b. Yûsuf b. Ṭîb to the acknowledgment by
			<lb n="18"/>
		de l’homme et de la femme qui ont reconnu ce qui s’[trouve, à] a la date (du document).
		the man and the woman, who have acknowledged that which (is contained) here[in on] its date.
			<lb n="19"/>
		A témoigné Šurayḥ Ibn ʿAlī Ibn al-Ḥusayn de la reconnaissance des deux de ce qui s’y trouve, à la date (du document).
		Witness is Šuraiḥ b. ʿAlî b. al-Ḥusain to their acknowledgment respecting that which (is contained) herein on its date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
