<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1102" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_67" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 067</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_67</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168966</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  ثبت عندي ذلك وكتب سليم بن 
<lb n="2"/>  يزيد بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="3"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="4"/>  هذا ما اشترى أبنيله وأبو البدر ولدي المكنّا بأبي السّري بن هليّه من خالهما قوريل بن أبنيلة وهم 
<lb n="5"/>  يومئذ من أهل الضّيعة المعروفة ببلجسوق ترس من بعض قرى كورة الفيّوم اشترا منه سفقة واحدا وعقدا واحدا جميع 
<lb n="6"/>  حقّه من مورثه من أبيه أبنيلة بن إسحق من المنزل الكبير شرقي الجامع العثيق بهذه الضّيعة المقدّم ذكرها ويحوط بهذا المنزل 
<lb n="7"/>  ويشتمل عليه حدود أربع الحد الأوّل منه وهو القبلي ينتهي إلي عرصة يحنّس بن بردسنه وخلاه من <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">قبلته</unclear> إلى منزل 
<lb n="8"/>  ينوق والحد الثّاني البحري ينتهي إلى الحصّة الّتي لهذا المنزل ممّا وقعت <sic n="superfluous">القسيمة</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">القسمة</supplied> ثلثة ديار إخوته قرا 
<lb n="9"/>  ورفرفيل والحد التّالت الشّرقي ينتهي إلي الدّار القورا الّتي لبلهيوه ابنت أبنيلة ومنه يشرع باب هذا المنزل والمدخل 
<lb n="10"/>  إليه والمخرج منه والحد الرّابع الغربي ينتهي إلى منزل ثيدر بن إسحق وهو دار يوميذ محرّق وكلّها قورا وما يخصّه 
<lb n="11"/>  من الخلا مع الحجارة إلي السّطح بلا سطح فاشترى أبنيله وأبو البدر ولدي المكنّا بأبي السّري بن هليه 
<lb n="12"/>  جميع ما ذكر ووصف في باطنها بحدّه وحدوده وسفله وعلوه وسمائه وأرضه وعراصه وأفنيه وكلّما يعرف 
<lb n="13"/>  له وينسب إليه شرا ثابت صحيحا منجزا لا شرط فيه ولا وعد ولا إتوى ولا خيار ولا وديعة ولا رهينة على بيع 
<lb n="14"/>  الإسلام وعهدتهم إن شا باع وإن شا وهب وإن شا صدّق بثمن مبلغه من العين ثلثة دنانير النّصف من ذلك 
<lb n="15"/>  دينار واحد ونصف قبض خالهما قوريل بن أبنيله بجميع هذا الثّمن المذكور علي تمامه وكماله فافترقوا جميعا 
<lb n="16"/>  منهم بالأبدان عن تراض منهم وبرئ كل من حي ومتى أدرك أبنيلة وأبو البدر ولدى المكنّا 
<lb n="17"/>  بأبي السري بن هليه في شرائهما هذا أو في شيا <del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">منهم</del> <sic n="superfluous">منهما</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">منه</supplied> درك علقة أو خصومة من سائر 
<lb n="18"/>  النّاس كلّهم قريب أم بعيد شاهد أم غائب طارئ بدين أو مستحق بميراث كان على خالهما 
<lb n="19"/>  قوريل بن أبنيله كائن ما كان وبالغ ما بلغ وبذلك أشهد على أنفسهم في صحّة عقولهم وجواز 
<lb n="20"/>  أمورهم في صفر من سنة خمسين وأربعمائة الحمد للّه كما هو أهله 
<lb n="21 right"/>  شهد أبو سهل بن خلف بن إبرهيم المودن على إقرار المقر 
<lb n="22 right"/>  بما فيه وكتب بيده في تأريخه 
<lb n="23 right"/>  الحمد للّه كما هو أهله 
<lb n="21 left"/>  شهد نهار بن سليمان بن إدريس 
<lb n="22 left"/>  على إقرار المقر بجميع ما فيه وذلك 
<lb n="23 left"/>  <sic n="superfluous">پپدحره</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">بعد جدّة</supplied> 
<lb n="24 left"/>  <sic n="superfluous">والحپه</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">الحذر</supplied> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ṯabata ʿind ī ḏālika wa kataba salīmu bnu 
 <lb n="2"/>yazīda bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="3"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="4"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʾabnīlahu wa ʾabū ăl badri waladayi ăl mukannā bi ʾabī ăs sariyyi bni hiliyaha min ḫāli himā qūrīla bni ʾabnīlaẗa wa hum 
 <lb n="5"/>yawma ʾiḏ:in min ʾahli ăḍ ḍayʿaẗi ăl maʿrūfaẗi bi bulǧusūqa tirisa min baʿḍi qurà kūraẗi ăl fayyūmi ĭštarā min hu safqaẗ:an wāḥid:an wa ʿaqd:an wāḥid:an ǧamīʿa 
 <lb n="6"/>ḥaqqi hi min mawraṯi hi min ʾabī hi ʾabnīlaẗa bni ʾisḥāqa mina ăl manzili ăl kabīri šarqiyya ăl ǧāmiʿi ăl ʿaṯīqi bi hāḏihi ăḍ ḍayʿaẗi ăl muqaddami ḏikru hā wa yaḥūṭu bi hāḏā ăl manzili 
 <lb n="7"/>wa yaštamilu ʿalay hi ḥudūd:un ʾarbaʿ:uni ăl ḥaddu ăl ʾawwalu min hu wa huwa ăl qibliyyu yantahī ʾilà ʿarṣaẗi yuḥannisa bni bardisanaha wa ḫalāʾi hi min qiblati hi ʾilà manzili 
 <lb n="8"/>yanūqa wa ăl ḥaddu ăṯ ṯānī ăl baḥriyyu yantahī ʾilà ăl ḥiṣṣaẗi ăllatī li hāḏā ăl manzili mimmā waqaʿati ăl qismaẗu ṯalāṯaẗa diyāri ʾiḫwati hi qarā 
 <lb n="9"/>wa rafrafīla wa ăl ḥaddu ăt tālitu ăš šarqiyyu yantahī ʾilà ăd dāri ăl qawrāʾi ăllatī li bilihiyūha ĭbnati ʾabnīlaẗa wa min hu yašraʿu bābu hāḏā ăl manzili wa ăl madḫalu 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾilay hi wa ăl maḫraǧu min hu wa ăl ḥaddu ăr rābiʿu ăl ġarbiyyu yantahī ʾilà manzili ṯiyudura bni ʾisḥāqa wa huwa dār:un yawma yiḏ:in muḥarraq:un wa kullu hā qawrāʾu wa mā yaḫuṣṣu hu 
 <lb n="11"/>mina ăl ḫalāʾi maʿa ăl ḥiǧāraẗi ʾilà ăs saṭḥi bi lā saṭḥ:in fa ĭštarà ʾabnīlahu wa ʾabū ăl badri waladayi ăl mukannā bi ʾabī ăs sariyyi bni hiliyaha 
 <lb n="12"/>ǧamīʿa mā ḏukira wa wuṣifa fī bāṭini hā bi ḥaddi hi wa ḥudūdi hi wa sufli hi wa ʿulwi hi wa samāʾi hi wa ʾarḍi hi wa ʿirāṣi hi wa ʾafniya hu wa kulla mā yuʿrafu 
 <lb n="13"/>la hu wa yunsabu ʾilay hi šir:an ṯābit ṣaḥīḥ:an munǧiz:an lā šarṭa fī hi wa lā waʿd:un wa lā ʾitāwà ʾitwà wa lā ḫiyār:un wa lā wadīʿaẗ:un wa lā rahīnaẗ:un ʿalà bayʿi 
 <lb n="14"/>ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati him ʾin šāʾa bāʿa wa ʾin šāʾa wahaba wa ʾin šāʾa ṣaddaqa bi ṯaman:in mablaġu hu mina ăl ʿayni ṯalāṯaẗu danānīra ăn niṣfu min ḏālika 
 <lb n="15"/>dīnār:un wāḥid:un wa niṣf:un qabaḍa ḫālu humā qūrīlu bnu ʾabnīlaha bi ǧamīʿi hāḏā ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūri ʿalà tamāmi hi wa kamāli hi fa ĭftaraqū ǧamīʿ:an 
 <lb n="16"/>min hum bi ăl ʾabdāni ʿan tarāḍ:in min hum wa bariʾa kull:un min ḥayy:in wa matà ʾadraka ʾabnīlaẗa wa ʾabū ăl badri waladayi ăl mukannā 
 <lb n="17"/>bi ʾabī ăs sariyyi bni hiliyaha fī širāʾi himā hāḏā ʾaw fī šayʾ:an min hu daraku ʿulqaẗ:in ʾaw ḫuṣūmaẗ:in min sāʾiri 
 <lb n="18"/>ăn nāsi kulli him qarīb:in ʾam baʿīd:in šāhid:in ʾam ġāʾib:in ṭāriʾ:in bi dayn:in ʾaw mustaḥiqq:in bi mīrāṯ:in kāna ʿalà ḫāli himā 
 <lb n="19"/>qūrīla bni ʾabnīlaha kāʾin mā kāna wa bāliġ mā balaġa wa bi ḏālika ʾašhada ʿalà ʾanfusi him fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿuqūli him wa ǧawāzi 
 <lb n="20"/>ʾumūri him fī ṣafar:in min sanaẗi ḫamsīna wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in ăl ḥamdu li ăl lāhi ka mā huwa ʾahlu hu 
 <lb n="21"/>šahida ʾabū sahli bnu ḫalafi bni ʾibrāhīma ăl muʾaḏḏinu ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl muqirri 
 <lb n="22"/>bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi yadi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="23"/>ăl ḥamdu li ăl lāhi ka mā huwa ʾahlu hu 
 <lb n="24"/>šahida nahāru bnu sulaymāna bni ʾidrīsa 
 <lb n="25"/>ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl muqirri bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi wa ḏālika 
 <lb n="26"/>baʿda ǧiddaẗi 
 <lb n="27"/>ăl ḥiḏri 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		This has been proved in my presence and Salîm b.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Yazîd has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="3"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="4"/>
		This is what Abnîle and Abu&#039;l-Badr, the sons of the surnamed Abu&#039;s-Sarî b. Helia, have bought from their maternal uncle Cyril b. Abnîle, they being
			<lb n="5"/>
		numbered at this time among the people of the domain known as Bulǧusûq Teres, one of the villages of the district of al-Fayyûm: they both have bought from him in one striking (of hands) and one contract the whole of
			<lb n="6"/>
		his share inherited from his father, Abnîle b. Isḥâq, of the great dwelling house east of the ancient mosque in this afore-said domain. Now four boundaries enclose
			<lb n="7"/>
		and surround this dwelling house: the first boundary, viz. the southern, extends to the open area of Yoḥannes b. Bardesane and the vacant space at the south of it as far as the dwelling house
			<lb n="8"/>
		of Yanûq; and the second, the northern boundary, extends to the share appertaining to this dwelling house, forming a part of that (property) which has been divided into the three houses of his brothers Qarâ
			<lb n="9"/>
		and Rafrafîl; and the third, the eastern boundary, extends to the large house, which belongs to Biliheu, daughter of Abnîle, with which the door of this dwelling house communicates, so as to afford entrance to
			<lb n="10"/>
		and exit from it; and the fourth, the western boundary, extends to the dwelling house of Theodor b. Isḥâq, this (now) being a house destroyed by fire and entirely unoccupied, and such free space as belongs to it,
			<lb n="11"/>
		including the (wall) stones as far as the uncovered roof. Abnîle and Abu&#039;l-Badr, the sons of the surnamed Abu&#039;s-Sarî b. Helia, have bought
			<lb n="12"/>
		all that is mentioned and described herein to its limit and its boundaries and (including) what is below and above the surface, and its sky and its land and its open areas and its fore-courts, and all that is known as appertaining
			<lb n="13"/>
		and relating to it in form of a right, valid, effected purchase in which is no condition and no promise and nothing that can bring about a loss and no option (of return) and no deposit and no pledge, according to Islamic
			<lb n="14"/>
		sale and to their (the Muslims) covenant, (so that) if he will, he may sell it, and if he will, he may give it away, and if he will, he may give it as an alms, for a price which in gold-coins amounts to three dînârs, the half thereof being
			<lb n="15"/>
		one and a half dînâr. Their maternal uncle Cyril b. Abnîle has received the whole of this (above) mentioned price fully and entirely. So they have all separated
			<lb n="16"/>
		from one another bodily to their mutual satisfaction, and quittance for all (this) has been given by a man in the quick, and should any evil consequence (vindicatio) with regard to this their purchase or any portion thereof ensue to
			<lb n="17"/>
		Abnîle and Abu&#039;l-Badr, the sons of the surnamed Abu&#039;s-Sarî b. Helia on the basis of any contention or litigation on the part of any
			<lb n="18"/>
		other persons, be they near or far, present or absent, (be it) one who suddenly appears with a debt or one who makes a claim on the basis of any inheritance, (then this) falls upon their maternal uncle
			<lb n="19"/>
		Cyril b. Abnîle whatever it might be or amount to, and with regard to this (purchase) witnesses have been called respecting their obligations they being in a state of sound mind and body and capable of transacting
			<lb n="20"/>
		their business, in Ṣafar of the year four hundred and fifty. Praise be to God, as He is worthy thereof.
			<lb n="21"/>
		Bû Sahl b. Ḫalaf b. Ibrahîm, the muezzin, is witness to the acknowledgment by the acknowledger
			<lb n="22"/>
		respecting what (is contained) herein and he has written (it) with his (own) hand on its date.
			<lb n="23"/>
		Praise be to God, as He is worthy thereof.
			<lb n="24"/>
		Nahâr b. Sulaimân b. Idrîs is witness
			<lb n="25"/>
		to the acknowledgment by the acknowledger respecting all that (is contained) herein, and this
			<lb n="26"/>
		after the most careful
			<lb n="27"/>
		attention. Valid.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
