<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="292" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_93" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 093</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_93</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106535</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="2"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شهر</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">رمـ</supplied>ـضـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـا</supplied>ن سنة إحدى وخمسين ومائتن شهد ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وكفا</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">باللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">شهيدا</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  وأحمد بن محمّد بمعرفته وشهد على مثل ذلك وكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـتب</supplied> شهادته بخطّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـه</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="4"/>  شهد <gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="character" /> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">على</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مثـ</supplied>ـل ذلك وكتبشها<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">دته</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" extent="6" unit="character" /> وبخـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـطّـ</supplied>ـه 
<lb n="5"/>  وشهد عبد اللّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بن</supplied> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـصر </lem><rdg resp="APD">بصر</rdg></app> على مثل ذلك وكتبشهادته بيـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـده</supplied> في شهر رمـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـضـ</supplied>ـان <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سـ</supplied>ـنـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـة</supplied> 
<lb n="6"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إ</supplied>حدى وخمسين وما<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ئتن</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> شهد عبد اللّه بن إسحق البزّاز على إقرار بقطر الأعرج بجميع 
<lb n="7"/>  ما في هذا الكتاب الكرى وكتب في شهر رمضان سنة إحدى وخمسين ومائى <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="8"/>  وبكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـر</supplied> بن عطا وكتب شهدته بخطّه 
<lb n="9"/>  وعلي بن <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـن عبد الرحيم بمثل ذلك وكتب في شهر رمضا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سـ</supplied>ـنة إحدى وخمسين ومائتن 
<lb n="10"/>  وإبرهيم بن عبد اللّه بن عيسى وكتب شهادته بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="11"/>  وعبيد بن علي بن زياد بمعرفته وفهمه وكتب شهادته بخطّه 
<lb n="12"/>  شهد عبد اللّه بن محمّد بن أبي السّري يكنّا أبا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لـ</supplied>ـسّائب </lem><rdg resp="APD">الشّائب</rdg></app> على 
<lb n="13"/>  إقرار بقطر الأعرج بجميع ما في هذا الكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـتا</supplied>ب من أوّله إلى آخـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـر</supplied>ه 
<lb n="14"/>  وشهد أحمد بن علي بن عبد الـرّحمن وكتب بخطّه <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="15"/>  شهد عبد اللّه بن محمّد بن عبد اللّه بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب 
<lb n="16"/>  وشهد عيسى بن الوليد على مثل ذلك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>**** ** **** 
 <lb n="2"/>fī šahri ramaḍāna sanaẗa ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni šahida ăl lāhu wa kafā bi ăl lāhi šahīd:an 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ʾaḥmadu bnu muḥammad:in bi maʿrifaẗi hi wa šahida ʿalà miṯli ḏālika wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi *** 
 <lb n="4"/>šahida ********** ʿalà miṯli ḏālika wa kataba šahādaẗa hu ****** wa bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="5"/>wa šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu baṣar:in naṣar:in naṣr:in ʿalà miṯli ḏālika wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi yadi hi fī šahri ramaḍāna sanaẗa 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni * šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu ʾisḥāqa ăl bazzāzu ʿalà ʾiqrāri buqṭura ăl ʾaʿraǧi bi ǧamīʿi 
 <lb n="7"/>mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi ăl kirà wa kataba fī šahri ramaḍāna sanaẗa ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatay * 
 <lb n="8"/>wa bakru bnu ʿaṭāʾa wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="9"/>wa ʿaliyyu bnu *** bni ʿabdi ăr raḥīmi bi miṯli ḏālika wa kataba fī šahri ramaḍāna sanaẗa ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ʾibrāhīmu bnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni ʿīsà wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="11"/>wa ʿubaydu bnu ʿaliyyi bni ziyād:in bi maʿrifaẗi hi wa fahmi hi wa kataba šahādaẗa hu bi ḫaṭṭi hi 
 <lb n="12"/>šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu muḥammadi bni ʾabī ăs sariyyi yukannā ʾabā ăs ăš sāʾibi šāʾibi ʿalà 
 <lb n="13"/>ʾiqrāri buqṭura ăl ʾaʿraǧi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi min ʾawwali hi ʾilà ʾāḫiri hi 
 <lb n="14"/>wa šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăr raḥmāni wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi * 
 <lb n="15"/>šahida ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu muḥammadi bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="16"/>wa šahida ʿīsà bnu ăl walīdi ʿalà miṯli ḏālika 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
			<lb n="2"/>
		[in the month of Rama]ḍ[â]n of the year two hundred and fifty one. [God] knoweth (it) [and God suffices as witness].
			<lb n="3"/>
		And Aḥmad b. Muḥammad out of his own knowledge, who is witness to the same, and he [has written] his testimony in [his] (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="4"/>
		Witness is [............................ to the] same and he has written his test[imony] ......... and in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="5"/>
		Witness is ʿAbdallâ[h b. Na]ṣr to the same and he has written his testimony with [his] (own) han[d] in the month of Rama[ḍ]ân of the [y]ea[r]
			<lb n="6"/>
		[two] hundred and fifty [o]ne (Handmark). Witness is ʿAbdallâh b. Isḥâq, the linen-merchant, to the acknowledgment by Boqṭor, the lame, respecting all that
			<lb n="7"/>
		(is contained) in this contract of lease and he has written (it) in the month of Ramaḍân of the year two hundred and fifty one (Handmark).
			<lb n="8"/>
		And Bak[r] b. ʿAṭâ, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="9"/>
		And ʿAlî b. [So and So b]en ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân (is witness) to the same and he has written (it) in the month of Ramaḍân of the year two hundred and fifty one.
			<lb n="10"/>
		And Ibrahîm b. ʿAbdallâh b. ʿÎsâ, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting (Handmark).
			<lb n="11"/>
		And ʿUbaid b. ʿAlî b. Ziyâd to his having taken cognizance of it and having understood it, and he has written his testimony in his (own) handwriting.
			<lb n="12"/>
		Witness is ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad b. Abi ʾs-Sarî, surnamed Abu ʾs-Sâʾib, to
			<lb n="13"/>
		the acknowledgment by Boqṭor, the lame, respecting all that (is contained) in this contract from its beginning to its [e]nd.
			<lb n="14"/>
		And witness is Aḥmad b. ʿAlî b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân, and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting (Handmark).
			<lb n="15"/>
		Witness is  ʿAbdallâh b. Muḥammad b. ʿAbdallâh to all that (is contained) in this contract.
			<lb n="16"/>
		And witness is ʿÎsâ b. al-Walîd to the same.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
