<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="347" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_136" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 136</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_136</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106578</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="2 right"/>  شهد إبرهيم بن عبيد اللّه بن جعفر على 
<lb n="3 right"/>  إقرار المقر بما فيه في تأريخه 
<lb n="4 right"/>  شهد <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نـ</supplied>ـعمان بن يوسف بن طيب على إقرار 
<lb n="5 right"/>  المقر بما فيه وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="2 left"/>  ما فيه وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="3 left"/>  شهد عبد الرّحمن بن محمّد بن هرون على إقرار 
<lb n="4 left"/>  المقر المسمّا بما فيه وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>**** **** **** **** 
 <lb n="2"/>šahida ʾibrāhīmu bnu ʿubaydi ăl lāhi bni ǧaʿfara ʿalà 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾiqrāri ăl muqirri bi mā fī hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="4"/>šahida nuʿmānu bnu yūsufa bni ṭīb:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="5"/>ăl muqirri bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="6"/>mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="7"/>šahida ʿabdu ăr raḥmāni bnu muḥammadi bni hārūna ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl muqirri ăl musammā bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
			<lb n="2"/>
		Ibrahîm b. ʿUbaid Allâh b. Ǧaʿfar is witness to
			<lb n="3"/>
		the acknowledgment by the acknowledger respecting that which (is contained) herein on its date.
			<lb n="4"/>
		Nuʿmân b. Yûsuf b. Ṭîb is witness to the acknowledgment
			<lb n="5"/>
		by the acknowledger respecting that which (is contained) herein, and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="6"/>
		what is contained herein, and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="7"/>
		ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân b. Muḥammad b. Harûn is witness to the acknowledgment
			<lb n="8"/>
		by the acknowledger named respecting that which (is contained) herein, and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
