<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1088" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_61" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 061</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_61</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168954</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى إسحق بن أبنيله البلجسوقي من ابنت أخته <sic n="superfluous">دلميه</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">دليمه</supplied> ابنت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يعوق </lem><rdg resp="“Dietrich”">بقوف</rdg></app> المنهراوي اشترى منها 
<lb n="3"/>  سفقة واحدا وعقدا واحدا جميع حقّها ومصابتها من المنزل والدّور القوراه المعر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وفة</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بإرث</supplied> 
<lb n="4"/>  من أبنيله بن إسحق البلجسوقي ويحيط بهذا المنزل ويشتمل عليه حدود أربع حدّه الأوّل وهو القبلي ينتهي 
<lb n="5"/>  إلى دار بني <sic n="superfluous">اپپى</sic> <app type="BL"><lem resp="final qāf with two dots above">ينوق </lem><rdg resp="final qāf with two dots above">يعوق</rdg></app> والحد الثّاني وهو البحري ينتهي إلى دار الغسّال ومنه يشرع بابه والحد الثّالث وهو الشّرقي ينتهي 
<lb n="6"/>  إلى منزل قنجوش بن شنوده والحد الرّابع وهو الغربي ينتهي إلى منزل ثيدر بن إسحق هذه جميع حدود هذا المنزل 
<lb n="7"/>  والدّور القوراه اشترى إسحق بن أبنيله ذلك كلّه بنصف دينار وثمن دينار ثمنا لما وقع عليه البيع المذكور 
<lb n="8"/>  وقبضت البائعة المذكورة هذا الثّمن تامّا وافيا كاملا وأبرت المشتري المذكور منه ومن وزنه ونقده وعيونه 
<lb n="9"/>  براه قبض واستيفا وسلّمت إليه جميع ما اشتراه منها وهو عن إرتها من أمّها أدوى ابنت أبنيله وحازه 
<lb n="10"/>  المشتري المذكور وملكه وصار له وفي يده ومال من ماله وملك من ملكه يتصرّف فيه تصرّف الملّاك في 
<lb n="11"/>  أملاكهم وتفرّقا بأبدانهما بعد تمام البيع ووجوبه عن تراض منهما جميعا بما تبايعا به وإنفاذ منهما 
<lb n="12"/>  له ومعرفة منهما به ووقوفهما عليه ونظر منهما له قبل الشّرى وبعده فتبايعا على ذلك بيعا صحيحا بتّا 
<lb n="13"/>  بتلا لا خيار فيه ولا أ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">تـ</supplied>ـوى ولا على سبيل رهن ولا توليج ولا شرط يفسده فما أدرك إسحق بن أبنيله في شرايه 
<lb n="14"/>  هذا أو أحد نسبه من درك أو علقة أو تبعة أو خصومة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عن </lem><rdg resp="“AK”">من</rdg></app> جميع النّاس كلّهم قريب أم بعيد على الوجوه 
<lb n="15"/>  والأسباب كلّها فعلى دليمه ابنت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يعوق </lem><rdg resp="“Dietrich”">بقوف</rdg></app> وتخلّص له ذلك في مالها وذمّتها كائنا ما كان وبالغ ما بلغ 
<lb n="16"/>  على ما يوجبه شرط بيع الإسلام وعهدته شهد على إقرار البائعة المذكورة بالبيع وقبض الثّمن المذكور 
<lb n="17"/>  مبلغه في هذا الكتاب وعلى إقرار المشتري بالشّرى والإحازة وعلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">معرفهما </lem><rdg resp="APD">معرفتهما</rdg></app> بإعيانتهما وأسمائهما 
<lb n="18"/>  وأنسابهما وإقرارهما على أنفسهما بجميع ما فيه بعد أن قرئ عليهما حرفا حرفا فأقرّا بفهمه ومعرفته 
<lb n="19"/>  في صحّة عقولهما وأبدانهما وجواز أمورهما غير مكرهين ولا مجبرين وذلك في رجب سنة ثلثة وعشرين وأربعمائة 
<lb n="20 right"/>  شهد فضل بن فرج بجميع 
<lb n="21 right"/>  ما في هذا الكتاب وكتب بيده 
<lb n="20 left"/>  شهد مكر بن أحمد 
<lb n="21 left"/>  <del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">و</del>بجميع ما فيه وكتب 
<lb n="22 left"/>  بيده 
<lb n="22 right"/>  شهد مسلم بن إسمعيل بن يعقوب على إقرار 
<lb n="23 right"/>  المقر بما فيه وكتب بيده في تأريخه 
<lb n="22 middle"/>  صح 
<lb n="20 left margin"/>  صح 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʾisḥāqu bnu ʾabnīlaha ăl bulǧusūqiyyu mina ĭbnati ʾuḫti hi dalīmaha ĭbnati yaʿūqa baqūfa ăl manharāwiyyi ĭštarà min hā 
 <lb n="3"/>safqaẗ:an wāḥid:an wa ʿaqd:an wāḥid:an ǧamīʿa ḥaqqi hā wa muṣābati hā mina ăl manzili wa ăd dawri dūri ăl qawrāhi ăl maʿrūfaẗi bi ʾirṯ:in 
 <lb n="4"/>min ʾabnīlaha bni ʾisḥāqa ăl bulǧusūqiyyi wa yuḥīṭu bi hāḏā ăl manzili wa yaštamilu ʿalay hi ḥudūd:un ʾarbaʿ:un ḥaddu hu ăl ʾawwalu wa huwa ăl qibliyyu yantahī 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾilà dāri banī yanūqa yaʿūqa wa ăl ḥaddu ăṯ ṯānī wa huwa ăl baḥriyyu yantahī ʾilà dāri ăl ġassāli wa min hu yašraʿu bābu hu wa ăl ḥaddu ăṯ ṯāliṯu wa huwa ăš šarqiyyu yantahī 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾilà manzili qanǧūša bni šanūdaha wa ăl ḥaddu ăr rābiʿu wa huwa ăl ġarbiyyu yantahī ʾilà manzili ṯiyudura bni ʾisḥāqa hāḏihi ǧamīʿu ḥudūdi hāḏā ăl manzili 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ăd dawri dūri ăl qawrāhi ĭštarà ʾisḥāqu bnu ʾabnīlaha ḏālika kulla hu bi niṣfi dīnār:in wa ṯumni dīnār:in ṯaman:an li mā waqaʿa wuqqiʿa ʿalay hi ăl bayʿu ăl maḏkūru 
 <lb n="8"/>wa qabaḍati ăl bāʾiʿaẗu ăl maḏkūraẗu hāḏā ăṯ ṯamana tāmm:an wāfiy:an kāmil:an wa ʾabraʾati ăl muštariya ăl maḏkūra min hu wa min wazni hi wa naqdi hi wa ʿuyūni hi 
 <lb n="9"/>barāʾaẗa qabḍ:in wa ĭstīfāʾ:in wa sallamat ʾilay hi ǧamīʿa mā ĭštarā hu min hā wa huwa ʿan ʾirti hā min ʾummi hā ʾadwà ĭbnati ʾabnīlaha wa ḥāza hu 
 <lb n="10"/>ăl muštarī ăl maḏkūru wa malaka hu wa ṣāra la hu wa fī yadi hi wa māl min māli hi wa milk min milki hi yataṣarrafa fī hi taṣarrufa ăl mullāki fī 
 <lb n="11"/>ʾamlāki him wa tafarraqā bi ʾabdāni himā baʿda tamāmi ăl bayʿi wa wuǧūbi hi ʿan tarāḍ:in min humā ǧamīʿ:an bi mā tabāyaʿā bi hi wa ʾinfāḏ:in min humā 
 <lb n="12"/>la hu wa maʿrifaẗ:in min humā bi hi wa wuqūfi himā ʿalay hi wa naẓar:in min humā la hu qabla ăš širà wa baʿda hu fa tabāyaʿā ʿalà ḏālika bayʿ:an ṣaḥīḥ:an batt:an 
 <lb n="13"/>batl:an lā ḫiyāra fī hi wa lā ʾatāwà wa lā ʿalà sabīli rahn:in wa lā tawlīǧ:in wa lā šarṭ:in yufsidu hu fa mā ʾadraka ʾisḥāqa bna ʾabnīlaha fī širāyi hi 
 <lb n="14"/>hāḏā ʾaw ʾaḥada nasabi hi min darak:in ʾaw ʿulqaẗ:in ʾaw tabiʿaẗ:in ʾaw ḫuṣūmaẗ:in ʿan min ǧamīʿi ăn nāsi kulli him qarīb:in ʾam baʿīd:in ʿalà ăl wuǧūhi 
 <lb n="15"/>wa ăl ʾasbābi kulli hā fa ʿalà dalīmaha ĭbnati yaʿūqa baqūfa wa tuḫalliṣa la hu ḏālika fī māli hā wa ḏimmati hā kāʾin:an mā kāna wa bāliġ mā balaġa 
 <lb n="16"/>ʿalà mā yūǧibu hu šarṭu bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdati hi šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi bi ăl bayʿi wa qabḍi ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūru 
 <lb n="17"/>mablaġu hu fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl muštarī bi ăš širà wa ăl ʾiḥāzaẗi wa ʿalà maʿrafi maʿrifati himā bi ʾiʿyānati himā wa ʾasmāʾi himā 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʾansābi himā wa ʾiqrāri himā ʿalà ʾanfusi himā bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay himā ḥarf:an ḥarf:an fa ʾaqarrā bi fahmi hi wa maʿrifati hi 
 <lb n="19"/>fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿuqūli himā wa ʾabdāni himā wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri himā ġayra mukrahayni wa lā muǧbarayni wa ḏālika fī raǧab:in sanaẗa ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida faḍlu bnu faraǧ:in bi ǧamīʿi 
 <lb n="21"/>mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa kataba bi yadi hi 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida makru bnu ʾaḥmada 
 <lb n="23"/>bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi wa kataba 
 <lb n="24"/>bi yadi hi 
 <lb n="25"/>šahida muslimu bnu ʾismāʿīla bni yaʿqūba ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="26"/>ăl muqirri bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi yadi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="27"/>ṣaḥḥa 
 <lb n="28"/>ṣaḥḥa 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Isḥâq b. Abnîle, originating from Bulǧusûq, has bought from his sister&#039;s daughter Dalîma, daughter of Yaʿûq, originating from Manharî: he has bought from her
			<lb n="3"/>
		in one striking (of hands) and one contract the whole of her share and portion of the dwelling house and the capacious appartments kno[wn as an inheritance]
		in one striking (of hands) and one contract the whole of her share and portion of the dwelling house and the capacious storey kno[wn as an inheritance]
			<lb n="4"/>
		from Abnîle b. Isḥâq, originating from Bulǧusûq. Now four boundaries enclose and surround this dwelling house: the first boundary, viz. the southern, extends
			<lb n="5"/>
		to the house of the sons of Yanûq, and the second boundary, viz. the northern, extends to the house of al-Ġassâl, with which its door communicates, and the third boundary, viz. the eastern, extends
			<lb n="6"/>
		to the dwelling house of Qanǧûš b. Šanûda, and the fourth boundary, viz. the western, extends to the dwelling house of Theodor b. Isḥâq; these are all the boundaries of this dwelling house
			<lb n="7"/>
		and the capacious appartments. Isḥâq b. Abnîle has bought this all for a half and an eighth of a dînâr as the price of that for which the above mentioned sale has been effected,
			<lb n="8"/>
		and the aforesaid seller has received this price entirely, fully, wholly, and has given the above mentioned buyer a quittance for it and its weight, and ready money in cash and gold-coins,
			<lb n="9"/>
		by means of a receipt, (acknowledging that she has) received and taken (it) over fully, and has handed over to him all that he has bought from her, this being her inheritance from her mother Adwâ (?), daughter of Abnîle; and the buyer
			<lb n="10"/>
		has acquired and taken possession of it and it has passed into his possession and into his hands and (has become) his own property and possession, (so that) he may do with it according to the practice of proprietors in respect to
			<lb n="11"/>
		their property; and they both have separated from one another after the completion and ratification of the sale to the mutual satisfaction of both of them in respect to that which they both have sold and bought, and (after) they both had declared it effective
			<lb n="12"/>
		and had taken cognizance of it and had comprehended it and looked into it before and after the purchase. So they have both sold and bought in this way, in the form of a valid, definitive, irrevocable
			<lb n="13"/>
		sale, in which is no option (of return) and nothing that can bring about a loss, and it is not in the way of a pledge, nor a disguised irregular gift, nor a stipulation that renders it (the purchase) ineffective; but so far as there might ensue to
			<lb n="14"/>
		Isḥâq b. Abnîle or one of his family any evil consequence (vindicatio) with regard to this his purchase, or a contention or a vindication or a litigation on the part of any persons, be they near of far, for any
			<lb n="15"/>
		causes or reasons, then (this falls) upon Dalîma, daughter of Yaʿûq, who shall indemnify him for it out of her property and at her expense, whatever it might be and amount to
			<lb n="16"/>
		according to what Islamic law of sale and covenant makes obligatory. (The following witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the above mentioned seller respecting the sale and the receipt of the price, the amount
			<lb n="17"/>
		of which is mentioned in this deed, and to the acknowledgment by the buyer respecting the purchase and the taking over (the property), and that they are acquainted with one another by sight and by name
			<lb n="18"/>
		and by their relationships, and to their acknowledgment to one another respecting all that (is contained) herein, after that it had been read to them both word by word. So they have acknowledged that they have understood it and comprehend it, they being
			<lb n="19"/>
		in a state of sound mind and body, and capable of transacting their business, without compulsion, and not against their will, and this in Raǧab of the year four hundred and twenty three.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Faḍl b. Faraǧ is witness to all
			<lb n="21"/>
		that (is contained) in this act, and he has written with his (own) hand.
			<lb n="22"/>
		Makr b. Aḥmad is witness
			<lb n="23"/>
		to all that (is contained) herein, and he has written
			<lb n="24"/>
		with his (own) hand.
			<lb n="25"/>
		Muslim b. Ismâʿîl b. Yaʿqûb is witness to the acknowledgment
			<lb n="26"/>
		by the acknowledger respecting all that (is contained) herein, and he has written with his (own) hand and on its date (= the date it bears).
			<lb n="27"/>
		Valid.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
