<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1825" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_331" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 331</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_331</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169562</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  المستخرج على جهته وباللّه قسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الحالف </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لي</rdg></app> 
 <lb n="2"/>  إنّي في إضاقة عظيمة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لولا </lem><rdg resp="UB and Diem">لو</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دلك </lem><rdg resp="UB and Diem">لا</rdg></app> لما 
 <lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="UB, accounting for Grohmann's translation">صايفت </lem><rdg resp="Grohmann in edition and reading UB">ضايقت</rdg></app> غلامه في هذا المقدار وأمّا 
 <lb n="4"/>  قوله أن رسم الكرم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عين </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ quotiation of recto line 9, of which we have no image">غير</rdg></app> رسم الحكم 
 <lb n="5"/>  فالأمر أقرب من هذا وقد مضى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الى </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ the scribe omitted the name of the person who went to Ṭaḥā"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/></rdg></app> 
 <lb n="6"/>  طحا يجيني بشي لي هناك بأي وقت ورد 
 <lb n="7"/>  أنفذت إليه الدّينارين ولم أوحرها 
 <lb n="8"/>  عنه سمعا وطاعة لأمره إن شا اللّه 
 <lb n="9"/>  توكّلت على اللّه 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl mustaḫraǧ ʿalà ǧihati hi wa bi ăl lāhi qasama ø l ø ī ăl ḥālifi ḥālifu ḥālu 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾin nī fī ʾiḍāqaẗ:in ʿaẓīmaẗ:in li law walāʾi ø lā ḏālika la lammā mā ø 
 <lb n="3"/>ṣāyaftu ḍāyaqtu ġulāma hu fī hāḏā ăl miqdāri wa ʾammā 
 <lb n="4"/>qawlu hu ʾanna rasma ăl karmi ʿaynu ġayru rasmi ăl ḥukmi 
 <lb n="5"/>fa ăl ʾamru ʾaqrabu min hāḏā wa qad maḍà ø *** ʾilà 
 <lb n="6"/>ṭaḥā yaǧī nī bi šayʾ:in l ī hunāka bi ʾayyi waqt:in warada 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾanfaḏtu ʾilay hi ăd dīnārayni wa lam ʾuʾaḫḫir hā 
 <lb n="8"/>ʿan hu samʿ:an wa ṭāʿaẗ:an li ʾamri hi ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="9"/>tawakkaltu ʿalà ăl lāhi 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  das zu seinen Lasten zu erhebende. Bei Gott, die Umstände haben mir (das Schicksal) zugeteilt,
 	  The copy of the letter which has been sent to its place (?), and by God, it is the oath of him who swears (i.e. I&#039;m swearing),
 	  The (letter) which has been sent to its place (?) And he who has taken the oath has taken it in the name of God.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  daß ich in einer riesengroßen finanziellen Schwierigkeit bin. Wenn dies nicht wäre,
 	  I am in great affliction. If it was not for that (affliction), I would not
 	  Verily, I am in great affliction because of being that man&#039;s friend, when
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  hätte ich seinem (sc. des Adressaten) Burschen nicht solche Schwierigkeiten wegen dieses Betrages gemacht. ...
 	  have troubled his boy to this extent. And as to
 	  I hired his mate for the summer in this space of time. And as to
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  his saying &#034;the tax on the vines is the same as the regular tax&#034;,
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  now the matter is nearer (more probable) than this. He has already departed to
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  Ṭaḥâ, to bring me what appertains there to me. As soon as he has arrived
 	  ... Wann auch immer er ankommt,
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  I paid to him the two dînârs, and I never withheld it
 	  werde ich ihm (sc. dem Schreiber von recto) die zwei Dinar übersenden und sie ihm nicht vorenthalten,
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  from him. I hear and obey his order, if God wills.
 	  indem ich seinem (sc. des Adressaten) Befehl unverzüglich gehorche. ...
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  I trust in God.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
