<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="752" xml:id="Grohmann_FWAP_p_132" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.World p. 132</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_FWAP_p_132</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106828</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا كتاب من سفين بن قرعة 
<lb n="3"/>  عامل الأمير عبد اللّه بن المسيّب 
<lb n="4"/>  حفظه اللّه على كورة 
<lb n="5"/>  أهناس والبهنسى وواحها 
<lb n="6"/>  إلى جميع من بكورة أهناس 
<lb n="7"/>  من المسلمين وأهل الذّمّة 
<lb n="8"/>  سلم عليكم فإنّي أحمد اللّه إليكم 
<lb n="9"/>  اللّه الّذي لا إله إلّا هو 
<lb n="10"/>  أمّا بعد فإن الأمير عبد اللّه بن 
<lb n="11"/>  المسيّب حفظه اللّه كتب 
<lb n="12"/>  إلي وإليكم كتابا 
<lb n="13"/>  يحكمنا فيه الّذي تقرّر عند أمير 
<lb n="14"/>  المومپپن أطال اللّه بقاه من 
<lb n="15"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">جزايـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـة</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="“Dietrich p. 86”">جباية</rdg></app> مصر وما لأفياهم 
<lb n="16"/>  ومن تولية الأمير عبد اللّه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بن</supplied> 
<lb n="17"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">المسيّب</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" extent="16" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="18"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأمير</supplied> عبد اللّه بن المسيّب 
<lb n="19"/>  بإعانته وقوّم إليها من <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="20"/>  لما وثق به من حاله واحتكم من 
<lb n="21"/>  استصلاحه 
<lb n="22"/>  وقد أتاكم من جنس دأبه في الرّفق 
<lb n="23"/>  بكم واعـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـتـ</supplied>رض على استلابكم 
<lb n="24"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> في تجنّيه عليكم 
<lb n="25"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> عنكم 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā kitāb:un min sufyāna bni qurʿaẗa 
 <lb n="3"/>ʿāmili ăl ʾamīri ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni ăl musayyabi 
 <lb n="4"/>ḥafiẓa hu ăl lāhu ʿalà kūraẗi 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾahnāsa wa ăl bahnasà wa wāḥi hā 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾilà ǧamīʿi man bi kūraẗi ʾahnāsa 
 <lb n="7"/>mina ăl muslimīna wa ʾahli ăḏ ḏimmaẗi 
 <lb n="8"/>salām:un ʿalay kum fa ʾin nī ʾaḥmadu ăl lāha ʾilay kumu 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl lāha ăllaḏī lā ʾilāha ʾillā huwa 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾammā baʿdu fa ʾinna ăl ʾamīra ʿabda ăl lāhi bni 
 <lb n="11"/>ăl musayyabi ḥafiẓa hu ăl lāhu kataba 
 <lb n="12"/>ʾilay ya wa ʾilay kum kitāb:an 
 <lb n="13"/>yaḥkumu nā fī hi ăllaḏī taqarrara ʿinda ʾamīri 
 <lb n="14"/>ăl muʾminīna ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa hu min 
 <lb n="15"/>ǧazāyaẗi ǧibāyaẗi miṣra wa mā li ʾafyāʾi him 
 <lb n="16"/>wa min tawliyaẗi ăl ʾamīri ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni 
 <lb n="17"/>ăl musayyabi **************** 
 <lb n="18"/>ăl ʾamīr ʿabd ăl lāhi bn ăl musayyabi 
 <lb n="19"/>bi ʾiʿānati hi wa qawwim ʾilay hā min **** 
 <lb n="20"/>li mā waṯiqa bi hi min ḥāli hi wa ĭḥtakama mini 
 <lb n="21"/>ĭstiṣlāḥi hi 
 <lb n="22"/>wa qad ʾatā kum min ǧinsi daʾbi hi fī ăr rifqi 
 <lb n="23"/>bi kum wa ĭʿtaraḍa ʿalà ĭstilābi kum 
 <lb n="24"/>*** fī taǧannī hi ʿalay kum 
 <lb n="25"/>*** ʿan kum 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes des Allbarmherzigen! 
		In the name of God the Compassionate, the Merciful !
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate. 
			<lb n="2"/>
		Dies ist das Schreiben des Sufjân ibn Kuráʾa, 
		This is the decree from Sufyân b. Qurʿa,
		This writing is from Sufyan ibn Qurrʿa 
			<lb n="3"/>
		Finance-Director of the Governor ʿAbdallâh ibn al Musayyab
		Finanzdirectors des Statthalters ʿAbd allâh ibn al-Musajjab 
		the executive of the governor (amīr) ʿAbdallāh ibn al-Musayyib, 
			<lb n="4"/>
		(den Gott beschützen möge!), welcher gesetzt ist über den Bezirk 
		may God protect him, over the district of 
		- may God protect him - over the Kûra
			<lb n="5"/>
		Ahnās and al-Bahnasā and the oases, 
		of Ehnâs, al-Bahnasâ and its oasis,
		von Ahnâs (Heracleopolis), el-Behnesâ (Oxyrryhnchos) und die dazu gehörigen Oasen,
			<lb n="6"/>
		to all [people] belonging to the Kûra of Ehnâs
		to everyone who belongs to the district of Ahnās 
			<lb n="7"/>
		an sämmtliche Muslimen des Districtes Ahnâs und der Hauptstadt! 
		of Moslims and protected people.
		of Muslims and protected people. 
			<lb n="8"/>
		Friede über euch! Ich preise gegen euch 
		Hail unto you! I praise unto you
		Peace be upon you. And I praise to you God, 
			<lb n="9"/>
		God, besides whom there is no god.
		God beside whom there is no other God. 
		Gott, außer dem es keinen Gott gibt. 
			<lb n="10"/>
		As for the following, verily the governor, ʿAbdallāh ibn 
		Thereafter: The Governor ʿAbdallâh ibn
		Und weiter: Fürwahr, der Statthalter ʿAbd allâh ibn 
			<lb n="11"/>
		al-Musayyab - may God protect him - has written
		al-Musayyib, may God protect him, wrote 
		el-Musayyab schrieb 
			<lb n="12"/>
		a letter to me and to you 
		mir und euch 
		to me and to you a letter,
			<lb n="13"/>
		in which he confirms to us what has been settled in the presence of the Commander of
		in which he delivers a judgement which was reached with the Commander of 
		vor den Steuertribut und hat uns dieserwegen Recht und Vollmacht ertheilt, gemäß dem, was durch 
			<lb n="14"/>
		den Fürsten der Gläubigen festgesetzt worden ist von 
		the Faithful, may God prolong his life, about 
		the Faithful - may God prolong his life - respecting the assessment of
			<lb n="15"/>
		der Grundsteuer Ägyptens. ...
		Egypt&#039;s taxes in money (jizāʾ, pl. of jizya), and about their afyāʾ (pl. of fayʾ, i.e., income from conquered lands classified as spoils), 
		the tribute of Egypt and (respecting) what belongs to their Fayyland
			<lb n="16"/>
		and about nominating ʿAbdallāh ibn 
		and (respecting) his nominating ʿAbdallāh [ibn]
			<lb n="17"/>
		[al-Musayyab Governor ...........]
		al-Musayyib governor [...] 
			<lb n="18"/>
		[the Governor] ʿAbdallâh ibn al-Musayyab
			<lb n="19"/>
		in assisting him, and keep well thereto (?) of (?) [......]
		to aid and assist him in [...] 
			<lb n="20"/>
		as far as he is confidant in his condition and (is able) to follow his own judgement respecting
		since he is confident in his position and in his decision about 
			<lb n="21"/>
		his acting well.
		its reclamation (istiṣlāḥhi). 
			<lb n="22"/>
		And you are already aware of the way of his endeavour to be lenient
		You have learned from the manner of his persistence in friendship 
			<lb n="23"/>
		towards you, and he has opposed to your being robbed
		with you. And he is opposed to your conspiring [...] 
			<lb n="24"/>
		in blaming you [...] 
		[...] respecting his accusing you falsely
			<lb n="25"/>
		[...] from you
		from you.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
