<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="990" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_45" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 045 (= P.World p. 196 = Chrest.Khoury I 11)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_45</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113731</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بسم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> الرّحمن ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لرّحيم</supplied> 
<lb n="2"/>  هذ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied> ما أصدق حسن بن الـمكنّا بأبو القدر السّاكن يومئذ مدينة <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الأشمونين</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  ضيا ابنة <sic n="superfluous">عپار</sic> <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">غثّام </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">غثّام </rdg><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">غنّام</rdg></app> الـطّرّاف السّاكنة يومئذ بهذه المدينة المذ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كورة</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="4"/>  وتزوّجها به تزويجا مستأنفا إذ كانت زوجته به <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> هذا <gap reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="5"/>  ودخل بها وأصابها وطلّقها طلقة واحدة واسترجعها بهذا 
<lb n="6"/>  الصّداق أصدقها أربعة دنانير مستنصريّة جياد العيون نقدها 
<lb n="7"/>  مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـن</supplied> ذلك دينار واحدا قبضته منه لنفسها نقدا في يدها تامّا وافيا 
<lb n="8"/>  وأبرأته منه ومن اليمين عليه براه قبض واستيفى وأخّرت الثّلاثة دنانير 
<lb n="9"/>  الباقي مهرها عليه إلى انقضى خمسة ليلي متواليات أوّلهن تأريخ 
<lb n="10"/>  هذا الكتاب وعليه أن يتّقي اللّه عز وجل فيـها ويحسن صحبتها بالمعروف 
<lb n="11"/>  كما أمر اللّه سبحانه في كتابه وسنّة نبيّه محمّد صلّى اللّه عليه وعلى آله 
<lb n="12"/>  وسلّم تسليما وله عليها مثل ذلك ودرجة زائدة وولي تزويجها إيّاه بذلك 
<lb n="13"/>  الشّيخ أبو الفضل العبّاس بن هبة اللّه بن عفيف بأمر القاضي أبو القاسم 
<lb n="14"/>  عبد اللّه بن علي بن عبد الرّحمن خليفة القاضي أبي الحسن مسرّة بن عبد اللّه 
<lb n="15"/>  على الحكم والصّلاة والخطابة والقضا والمظالم بمدينة الأشمونين وأعمالها إليه 
<lb n="16"/>  بكشف حالها وتزوّجها وكيل المتولّي ذلك وكشف عن حالها <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فوجّبها </lem><rdg resp="Khoury">فوجدها</rdg></app> مستحقّة 
<lb n="17"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">النّاكحة </lem><rdg resp="Khoury">المناكحة</rdg></app> فزوّجها من الزّوج المسمّا معها فيه بإذنها <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ورضا </lem><rdg resp="‭‫ها‬ added in Chrest.Khoury.">ورضاها</rdg></app> وبالمهر المذكور عاجله 
<lb n="18"/>  وآجله المذكورين في هذا الكتاب وشاهدي عدل شهدا له عليها بالرّضا وقبل 
<lb n="19"/>  الزّوج من المتولّي هذا النّكاح ورضي به وألزمه نفسه بمخاطبة جرت بينهما على جميعه 
<lb n="20"/>  شهد على إقرار الزّوجين والمتولّي الشّيخ بجميع ما فيه بعد أن قرئ عليهم فأقرّوا بفهمه 
<lb n="21"/>  بمعرفة جميعه وكتب في العشر الأخير من جمادى الآخر سنة إحدى وستّين وأربعمائة 
<lb n="22"/>  شهد علي بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.; Grohmann, World”">نجيد </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann, P.Cair.Arab.”">نجد</rdg></app> بن علي المغربي على إقرار الزّوجين والمتولّي وكتب في تأريخه شهد علي بن حفص بن علي بن حفص على إقرار الزّوجين 
<lb n="23"/>  والمتولّي بما فيه وكتب في تأريخه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ʾaṣdaqa ḥasanu bnu ăl mukannā bi ʾabū ăl qadri ăs sākinu yawma ʾiḏ:in madīnaẗa ăl ʾušmūnayni 
 <lb n="3"/>ḍiyāʾa ĭbnaẗa ʿaṯṯāma ġaṯṯāma ġannāma ăṭ ṭarrāfi ăs sākinaẗa yawma ʾiḏ:in bi hāḏihi ăl madīnaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi *** 
 <lb n="4"/>wa tazawwaǧa hā bi hi tazwīǧ:an mustaʾnif:an ʾiḏ kānat zawǧaẗa hu bi hi **** hāḏā ***** 
 <lb n="5"/>wa daḫala bi hā wa ʾaṣāba hā wa ṭallaqa hā ṭalqaẗ:an wāḥidaẗ:an wa ĭstarǧaʿa hā bi hāḏā 
 <lb n="6"/>ăṣ ṣadāqi ʾaṣdaqa hā ʾarbaʿaẗa danānīra mustanṣiriyyaẗ:an ǧiyāda ăl ʿuyūni naqada hā 
 <lb n="7"/>min ḏālika dīnār:an wāḥid:an qabaḍat hu min hu li nafsi hā naqd:an fī yadi hā tāmm:an wāfiy:an 
 <lb n="8"/>wa ʾabraʾat hu min hu wa mina ăl yamīni ʿalay hi barāʾaẗa qabḍ:in wa ĭstīf:an wa ʾaḫḫarati ăṯ ṯalāṯaẗa danānīra 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl bāqiya mahri hā ʿalay hi ʾilà ĭnqiḍà ḫamsaẗi layālī mutawāliyāt:in ʾawwalu hunna taʾrīḫu 
 <lb n="10"/>hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ʿalay hi ʾan yattaqiya ăl lāha ʿazza wa ǧalla fī hā wa yuḥsina ṣuḥbata hā bi ăl maʿrūfi 
 <lb n="11"/>kamā ʾamara ăl lāhu subḥāna hu fī kitābi hi wa sunnaẗi nabiyyi hi muḥammad:in ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalay hi wa ʿalà ʾāli hi 
 <lb n="12"/>wa sallama taslīm:an wa la hu ʿalay hā miṯlu ḏālika wa daraǧaẗ:un zāʾidaẗ:un wa waliya tazwīǧa hā ʾiyyā hu bi ḏālika 
 <lb n="13"/>ăš šayḫu ʾabū ăl faḍli ăl ʿabbāsu bnu hibaẗi ăl lāhi bni ʿafīf:in bi ʾamri ăl qāḍī ʾabū ăl qāsimi 
 <lb n="14"/>ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni ʿaliyyi bni ʿabdi ăr raḥmāni ḫalīfaẗi ăl qāḍī ʾabī ăl ḥasani masarraẗa bni ʿabdi ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="15"/>ʿalà ăl ḥukmi wa ăṣ ṣalāẗi wa ăl ḫiṭābaẗi wa ăl qaḍāʾi wa ăl maẓālimi bi madīnaẗi ăl ʾušmūnayni wa ʾaʿmāli hā ʾilay hi 
 <lb n="16"/>bi kašfi ḥāli hā tazawwuǧi wa hā tazawwaǧa hā wakīlu ăl mutawallī ḏālika wa kašafa ʿan ḥāli hā fa waǧǧaba waǧada hā mustaḥiqqaẗa 
 <lb n="17"/>ăn nākiḥaẗi munākaḥaẗi fa zawwaǧa hā mina ăz zawǧi ăl musammā maʿa hā fī hi bi ʾiḏni hā wa riḍāʾ:in riḍā ø hā wa bi ăl mahri ăl maḏkūri ʿāǧilu hu 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʾāǧilu hu ăl maḏkūrayni fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa šāhiday ʿadl:in šahidā la hu ʿalay hā bi ăr riḍāʾi wa qabila 
 <lb n="19"/>ăz zawǧu mina ăl mutawallī hāḏā ăn nikāḥa wa raḍiya bi hi wa ʾalzama hu nafsa hu bi muḫāṭabaẗ:in ǧarat bayna humā ʿalà ǧamīʿi hi 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăz zawǧayni wa ăl mutawallī ăš šayḫi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay him fa ʾaqarrū bi fahmi hi 
 <lb n="21"/>bi maʿrifaẗi ǧamīʿi hi wa kutiba fī ăl ʿašri ăl ʾaḫīri min ǧumādà ăl ʾāḫiri sanaẗa ʾiḥdà wa sittīna wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu nuǧaydi nāǧidi bni ʿaliyy:ini ăl maġribiyyu muġribiyyu ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăz zawǧayni wa ăl mutawallī wa kataba fī taʾrīḫi hi šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ḥafṣi bni ʿaliyyi bni ḥafṣ:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăz zawǧayni 
 <lb n="23"/>wa ăl mutawallī bi mā fī hi wa kataba fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		[Au nom de Dieu] clément [et miséricordieux !]
		[In the name of God,] the Compassionate, th[e Merciful].
			<lb n="2"/>
		Ceci est la dot donnée par Ḥasan fils du surnommé Abū al-Qadr, habitant en ce moment-là la ville d&#039;[al-Ušmūnayn], à
		Thi[s is] what Ḥasan, son of the surnamed Abuʾl-Qadr, residing at this time in the town of [al-Ušmūnain], has stipulated (as a nuptial gift) to
			<lb n="3"/>
		Ḍiyâ, daughter of ʿAṯṯâm, the tentmaker, residing at this time in this town men[tioned ...]
		Ḍiyā, fille de ʿAṯṯām, fabricant de tentes, et habitant en ce moment-là la ville sus[nommée....],
			<lb n="4"/>
		and by it (the ṣadâq) he takes her anew in marriage, since she was his wife ...... this ...... [...]
		moyennant quoi il se maria à elle une nouvelle fois, car elle était son épouse [...] ceci [....],
			<lb n="5"/>
		and he had gone into her and obtained his enjoyment of her and had divorced her a single pronouncement, he has now taken her back by virtue of this
		and he had gone into her and obtained his enjoyment of her and had divorced her in a single pronouncement, he has now taken her back by virtue of this
		et il avait consommé le mariage avec elle, eu des liaisons avec elle et divorcé d&#039;elle d&#039;une seule répudiation; (ainsi) il la reprit par le moyen de cette 
			<lb n="6"/>
		dot. Il lui donna comme dot quatre dīnārs d&#039;al-Mustanṣir, excellentes pièces d&#039;or, lui paya
		nuptial gift. He has stipulated to her four dînârs of Mustanṣir, good gold-pieces, (and) he has paid to her
			<lb n="7"/>
		d[e] cela un seul dīnār qu&#039;elle reçut de lui au comptant, pour elle dans sa main, parfaitement et complètement,
		one dînâr there[of], which she has taken for herself as a payment in her hand, full, entire,
		one dînâr [there]of, which she has taken over from him for herself as a payment in her hand, full, entire,
			<lb n="8"/>
		et elle l&#039;acquitta de cela et du serment qui lui incombe par le moyen d&#039;une quittance de libération attestant réception et perception intégrale, et repoussa les trois dīnārs
		from which she has released him and from his oath by means of a receipt (acknowledged that she has) received and taken it over fully: and the three dînârs,
		fro[m] which she has released him and from his oath by means of a receipt (acknowledging that she has) received and taken it over fully: and the three dînârs,
			<lb n="9"/>
		du restant de sa dot qu&#039;il lui doit jusqu&#039;à l&#039;écoulement de cinq nuit suivies, dont le début est la date
		the remainder of her dowry, are outstanding to his debit till the expiration of five successive nights, reckoning from the date
			<lb n="10"/>
		de ce document. Il a le devoir de craindre Dieu, qu&#039;il est puissant et sublime, en ce qui la concerne, et d&#039;avoir avec elle de bons rapports, en ce qui est reconnu (convenable),
		of this act. And it is his obligation to fear God - He is mighty and sublime - in respect to her and to make relationship to her pleasing in amenity,
		of this act. And it is his obligation to fear God - He is the Mighty and Sublime - in respect to her and to make relationship to her pleasing in amenity,
			<lb n="11"/>
		according to the ordinance of God - praise to Him - in His book and to the rule of His Prophet Muḥammad - may the blessing of God be upon him and upon his family,
		comme Dieu, gloire à lui, l&#039;a ordonné dans son Livre et la Sunna de son Prophète Muḥammad, que Dieu le bénisse, ainsi que sa famille,
			<lb n="12"/>
		and may He give him peace - and the same is her obligation towards him, but he is a rank higher. And the Šaiḫ
		and may He give him peace - and the same is her obligation towards him, but he is a rank higher. And the Shaikh
		et le salue, et elle lui doit la même chose (et il a sur elle) une prééminence. Sons mariage avec lui par ce moyen a été pris en charge par
			<lb n="13"/>
		Abuʾl-Faḍl al-ʿAbbâs b. Hibat Allâh b. ʿAfīf has undertaken to give her in marriage to him for this (ṣadâq) by order of the qâḍî Abuʾl-Qâsim
		Abuʾl-Faḍl al-ʿAbbâs b. Hibat Allâh b. ʿAfīf has undertaken to give her in marriage to him for this (ṣadâq) by order of the Qâḍî Abuʾl-Qâsim
		le šayḫ Abū l-Faḍl al-ʿAbbās Ibn Hibat Allāh Ibn ʿAfīf, sur ordre du juge Abū l-Qāsim
			<lb n="14"/>
		ʿAbdallâh b. ʿAlî b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân, the representative of the qâḍî Abuʾl-Ḥasan Masarra b. ʿAbdallâh, entrusted with  
		ʿAbdallâh b. ʿAlî b. ʿAbd ar-Raḥmân -, the representative of the Qâḍî Abuʾl-Ḥasan Masarra b. ʿAbdallâh, entrusted with
		ʿAbd Allāh Ibn ʿAlī Ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān, suppléant du juge Abū l-Ḥasan Masarra Ibn ʿAbd Allah
			<lb n="15"/>
		concernant les questions du jugement, de la célébration de la prière, de la prédication et les décision judiciaires et celles touchant les délits dans la ville d&#039;al-Ušmūnayn et ses circonscriptions; à lui
		the jurisdiction and the conduct of prayer(s) and the office of preacher and the pronouncing of judgements and the deciding of complaints in the town of al-Ušmûnain and its districts - to him that he should
		the jurisdiction and the conduct of prayers in the office of preacher and the pronouncing of judgements and the deciding of complaints in the town of al-Ushmûnain and its districts to him that he should
			<lb n="16"/>
		d&#039;examiner son état et de la marier, (en tant que) représentant de ce mandataire-là; il examina son état et la trouva qualifiée pour
		enquire into her state. And this representative of the guardian has given her in marriage, and has enquired into her state, and he has affirmed her full title to
			<lb n="17"/>
		le mariage, et la maria avec le mari nommé avec elle dans (le document), avec son autorisation et &lt;son&gt; consentement et la dot mentionnée, dont une partie, payable immédiatement au comptant,
		the status of a married (woman). So he married her to the husband named together with her herein, by her will and her consent, and by virtue of the above mentioned dowry, (part) immediately exigible
			<lb n="18"/>
		and (part) held over, both mentioned in this act. And two just witnesses have testified on his behalf with regard to her consent and the acceptance by the husband of
		et l&#039;autre, avec un délai de paiement, sont susnommées dans ce document. Deux témoins intègres ont témoigné, en faveur du mari et à la charge de la femme, du consentement,
			<lb n="19"/>
		et le mari accepta du mandataire ce mariage, y consentit et s&#039;en fit un devoir, en raison d&#039;un entretien que eut lieu entre eux deux concernant tout le document.
		this marriage from the guardian; and so he has agreed to it and has bound himself by it on the basis of the discussion which took place between them both with regard to it all.
		this marriage from the guardian; and so he has agreed to it and has bound himself to it on the basis of the discussion which took place between them both with regard to it all.
			<lb n="20"/>
		On a témoigné de la reconnaissance des deux mariés et su šayḫ mandataire de tout le contenu du document, après que celui-ci leur a été lu; ils reconnurent ainsi l&#039;avoir compris,
		(The following witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the couple and the guardian, the Šaiḫ, of all that (is contained) herein, after its having been read to them. Thus they have acknowledged that they have understood it
		(The following witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the couple and the guardian, the Shaikh, respecting all that (is contained) therein, after its having been read to them. Thus they have acknowledged that they understood it
			<lb n="21"/>
		(and) that they comprehended it entirely, and it has been written in the last ten days of the Ǧumādà II of the year four hundred and sixty one.
		(and) that they comprehend it entirely, and it has been written in the last decade of Ǧumādà II of the year four hundred and sixty one.
		&lt;et&gt; saisi entièrement. Ecrit dans la dernière décade de ǧumādā II de l&#039;année quatre cent soicante-et-un.
			<lb n="22"/>
		ʿAlî b. Nuǧaid b. ʿAlî, the Maghrabî, is witness to the acknowledgment by the couple and the guardian, and he has written (it) on its date. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ b. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ is witness to the acknowledgment by the couple
		ʿAlî b. Nuǧaid b. ʿAlî, the Maġribî, is witness to the acknowledgment by the couple and the guardian, and he has written (it) on its date. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ b. ʿAlî b. Ḥafṣ is witness to the acknowledgment by the couple
		ʿAlī Ibn Nuǧayd Ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī a témoigné de la reconnaissance des eux mariés et du mandataire, et on (l&#039;)écrivit à sa date. ʿAlī Ibn Ḥafṣ Ibn ʿAlī Ibn Ḥafṣ a témoigné de la reconnaissance des deux mariés
			<lb n="23"/>
		and the guardian of what is herein, and he has written (it) on its date.
		et du mandataire de son contenu, et on (l&#039;)écrivit à sa date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
