<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1770" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_306" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 306</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_306</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169511</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="verso 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="verso 2"/>  كتابي يا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أحمد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أخي</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">هدي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وسيّدي</rdg></app> أطال اللّه بقاك وأدام عزّك وتأييدك 
<lb n="verso 3"/>  من قوص عن حال سلامة وعافية لمولاها الحمد والمنّة يوم 
<lb n="verso 4"/>  الخميس لثمان خلون من رجب عزّه اللّه لوليّه وبركة ما يأتي بعده 
<lb n="verso 5"/>  من السّنين والأعوام والحمد للّه رب العالمين وقد كتبت إليك 
<lb n="verso 6"/>  من يوم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الحواد<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ث</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الحدّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عده </lem><rdg resp="APD">أوّل</rdg></app> كپپ الى إلپطرپق <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكپپ </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الطّرپق </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">الطّرپڤيّ</rdg></app> ڤد اوصپپك أن پكأنپپى 
<lb n="verso 7"/>  من أخميم فلم تفعل وجا كتاب بشر إلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إخوته </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أخوه</rdg></app> مع فرج البطريقي ولم يكون 
<lb n="verso 8"/>  لك معه كتاب وكنت قد كتبت إليك رقعتين قبل هذه على يد يحيى أعزّه اللّه 
<lb n="verso 9"/>  أنت تقف عليها وبعد ذلك وصل بقيّة الخشب الّذي بالأقصر وهو 
<lb n="verso 10"/>  ستّة وعشرين قطعة وقد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حملتها </lem><rdg resp="Diem">حملتها</rdg></app> على معدية عيسى بن تنوس سلّمها <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فيه </lem><rdg resp="Diem">اللّه</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 11"/>  وبقي بالأقصر ست قطع <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لم</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تحمل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تحمل</rdg></app> منها زوج في الجزيرة وزوج الّذي في الرّمل 
<lb n="verso 12"/>  وأصابوا الزّوج الّذي كان على القربوس قد انفسد وتهرّأ فلم يحمل وقد 
<lb n="verso 13"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">شا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">سألت</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يحب </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> سيّدي القاضي أدام اللّه عزّه كتب لي كتاب إلى الشّيخين أيّدهما 
<lb n="verso 14"/>  اللّه بإيقاف اثنا عشر دينارا وأرجوا أنّهم يفعلوا لأنّك تعلم أن 
<lb n="verso 15"/>  قد وقف على الشّيخ أيّده اللّه أوّل وآخر ستّة دنانير فإن أوقفوها 
<lb n="verso 16"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بحقّنا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لحقنا</rdg></app> في ذلك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">التّحقيق </lem><rdg resp="Diem">التّخفيف</rdg></app> وقد وافقت أبو جعفر أيّده اللّه على <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إنّما </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أنّها</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 17"/>  إن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وقفت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وقفت</rdg></app> أوقفت عنك دينارين ممّا عليك وكتبت ذلك بأربعة عشر الّذي 
<lb n="verso 18"/>  عند الشّيخ وكذلك أبو جعفر أعزّه اللّه ويكون الّذي للشّيخ <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ستّا </lem><rdg resp="APD">ستّا</rdg></app> فإن تم 
<lb n="verso 19"/>  هذا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فأتى </lem><rdg resp="APD">قام</rdg></app> أبو جعفر عنه وعن علي بمائتي وعشرين دينار وتقوم أنت بثلاثين 
<lb n="verso 20"/>  دينار ويقوم يحيى بأربعة دنانير من جملة ثمانية وخمسين وتقوم جماعة منها 
<lb n="verso 21"/>  بدينارين وقد كتبت التّذكرة ليحيى بخط أبو جعفر بما لي وما لكم وهي مع 
<lb n="verso 22"/>  يحيى والّذي أخذ <sic n="superfluous">متى</sic><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">منّي</supplied> بعدك دينار <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">منحّت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">منجر</rdg></app> ودينار ونصف <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أجرة </lem><rdg resp="proposed by Grohmann, preferred by Diem">أجرة</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الحساب </lem><rdg resp="APD">الحسّاب </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">الخشب</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 23"/>  ودينار عن أبو الحسن بن حاطب لا نعلم أنّك حاسبتني على دينار <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">وردپه</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">قد</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 24"/>  في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أجرة </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أجرة</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الحساب </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الخشب</rdg></app> على أن يكون على كل واحد منّا ثلث دينار وادفع أيضا من عندي 
<lb n="verso 25"/>  لكيل ثلث دينار يكون لي <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> پصح مپه شى ولم پاحد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">طاهر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">منّا</rdg></app> سپإ الا پصف 
<lb n="verso 26"/>  قبل أن تنفذ 
<lb n="verso 27"/>  المعدية 
<lb n="verso 28"/>  بحمل الخشب 
<lb n="verso 29"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ومعما </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وفيما</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 30"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حديث </lem><rdg resp="“UB”">حدّثت </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">كتبت</rdg></app> إليك 
<lb n="verso 31"/>  له <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">كفالتي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">كفاية</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 32"/>  قرأت 
<lb n="verso 33"/>  عليك 
<lb n="verso 34"/>  السّلم 
<lb n="verso 35"/>  وولدك 
<lb n="verso 36"/>  وأخوك 
<lb n="verso 37"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأصح </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأهلك</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> في كل 
<lb n="verso 38"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ما </lem><rdg resp="APD">عافية</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فيه </lem><rdg resp="APD">ø</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تقرئه </lem><rdg resp="“UB”">تقرئه </rdg><rdg resp="APD">يقروا</rdg></app> 
<lb n="verso 39"/>  عليك السّلم 
<lb n="40 = recto 1"/>  وبعد أن كتبت هذا الكتاب جا عمر بن صالح <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وانتقل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">واعتقل</rdg></app> الخشب 
<lb n="41 = recto 2"/>  وقال ما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يفرج </lem><rdg resp="Diem">نفرج </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">يفرج</rdg></app> إلّا بدينارين وثمن فكتبت إلى أبوك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ينفذ </lem><rdg resp="APD">ينفذ</rdg></app> إلى الدّينار 
<lb n="42 = recto 3"/>  الّذي دفعت إليه ليدفعه إليه وأدفع أنا إليه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بالباقي </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ the preposition is a mistake by the scribe">الباقي</rdg></app> و<del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">كڤـ</del>ـا 
<lb n="43 = recto 4"/>  وكان هذا الخطاب بحضرة أبو جعفر أعزّه اللّه 
<lb n="44 = recto 5"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><del rend="erasure" status="unremarkable">ڤپد</del><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">د</supplied>فع </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فيدفع</rdg></app> الدّينا<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ر</supplied> الآخر إلى يحيي أعزّه اللّه 
<lb n="45 = recto 6"/>  لأخي وسيّدي أبي عبد اللّه محمّد بن موسى من الحسن بن نعمان البليناوي 
<lb n="46 = recto 7"/>  أطال اللّه بقاه وأدام عزّه و<gap reason="illegible" extent="7" unit="character" /> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>kitāb ī yā ʾaḥmadu ʾaḫ ø ī bnu ø ø wa hudayy:in sayyid ø ī ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾadāma ʿizza ka wa taʾyīda ka 
 <lb n="3"/>min qūṣa ʿan ḥāli salāmaẗ:in wa ʿāfiyaẗ:in li mawlā hā ăl ḥamdu wa ăl minnaẗu yawma 
 <lb n="4"/>ăl ḫamīsi li ṯamān:in ḫalawna min raǧab:in ʿazza hu ăl lāhu li waliyyi hi wa barakaẗu mā yaʾtī baʿda hu 
 <lb n="5"/>mina ăs sinīna wa ăl ʾaʿwāmi wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi rabbi ăl ʿālamīna wa qad katabtu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="6"/>min yawmi ăl ḥawādiṯi ḥaddi ø ʾawwala ʿiddaẗa kutub:in ʾilà ăl biṭrīqi ṭrBqi ṭrBFiyyi wa kuntu qad ʾawṣaytu ka ʾan tukātiba nī 
 <lb n="7"/>min ʾaḫmīma fa lam tafʿal wa ǧāʾa kitābu bišr:in ʾilà ʾiḫwati ʾaḫū hi hu maʿa faraǧ:ini ăl baṭrīqiyyi wa lam yakūn 
 <lb n="8"/>la ka maʿa hu kitāb:un wa kuntu qad katabtu ʾilay ka ruqʿatayni qabla hāḏihi ʿalà yadi yaḥyà ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="9"/>ʾanta taqifu ʿalay hā wa baʿda ḏālika waṣala baqiyyaẗu ăl ḫašabi ăllaḏī bi ăl ʾuqṣuri wa huwa 
 <lb n="10"/>sittaẗ:un wa ʿišrīna qiṭʿaẗ:an wa qad ḥamaltu ḥammaltu hā ʿalà maʿdiyaẗi ʿīsà bni tanūsa sallama hā fī ăl hi lāhu 
 <lb n="11"/>wa baqiya bi ăl ʾuqṣuri sittu qiṭaʿ:in bal lam tuḥmal yaḥmilu min hā zawǧ fī ăl ǧazīraẗi wa zawǧ ăllaḏī fī ăr ramli 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ʾaṣābū ăz zawǧa ăllaḏī kāna ʿalà ăl qarabūsi qadi ĭnfasada wa taharraʾa fa lam yuḥammal wa qad 
 <lb n="13"/>šāʾa saʾaltu yuḥibbu ø sayyid ī ăl qāḍī ʾadāma ăl lāhu ʿizza hu kataba l ī kitāb ʾilà ăš šayḫayni ʾayyada humā 
 <lb n="14"/>ăl lāhu bi ʾīqāfi ĭṯnā ʿašara dīnār:an wa ʾarǧū ʾanna hum yafʿalū liʾanna ka taʿlamu ʾanna 
 <lb n="15"/>qad waqafa ʿalà ăš šayḫi ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu ʾawwal wa ʾāḫir sittaẗu danānīra fa ʾin ʾawqafū hā 
 <lb n="16"/>bi laḥiqnā ḥaqqi ø nā ø fī ḏālika ăt taḥqīqi taḫfīfa wa qad wāfaqtu ʾabū ǧaʿfara ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu ʿalà ʾinnamā ʾanna ø hā 
 <lb n="17"/>ʾin wafaqta waqafat ʾawqaftu ʿan ka dīnārayni mimmā ʿalay ka wa katabtu ḏālika bi ʾarbaʿaẗa ʿašara ăllaḏī 
 <lb n="18"/>ʿinda ăš šayḫi wa ka ḏālika ʾabū ǧaʿfara ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu wa yakūnu ăllaḏī li š šayḫi šayʾ:an sitt:an fa ʾin tamma 
 <lb n="19"/>hāḏā fa ø ʾatà qāma ʾabū ǧaʿfara ʿan hu wa ʿan ʿaliyy:in bi miʾatay wa ʿišrīna dīnār wa taqūmu ʾanta bi ṯalāṯīna 
 <lb n="20"/>dīnār wa yaqūmu yaḥyà bi ʾarbaʿaẗi danānīra min ǧumlaẗi ṯamāniyaẗ:in wa ḫamsīna wa taqūmu ǧamāʿaẗ:un min hā 
 <lb n="21"/>bi dīnārayni wa qad katabtu ăt taḏkiraẗa li yaḥyà bi ḫaṭṭi ʾabū ǧaʿfara bi mā l ī wa mā la kum wa hiya maʿa 
 <lb n="22"/>yaḥyà wa ăllaḏī ʾaḫaḏa min nī baʿda ka dīnāru dīnār:un munaḥḥat:un minǧar:in wa dīnār:un wa niṣf:un ʾāḫiraẗa ʾuǧraẗa ăl ḥisābi ḥussābi ḫašabi 
 <lb n="23"/>wa dīnār:un ʿan ʾabū ăl ḥasani bni ḥāṭib:in lā naʿlamu ʾanna ka ḥāsabta nī ʿalà dīnār:in ø qad wa ø radta wazantu hu 
 <lb n="24"/>fī ʾāḫiraẗi ʾuǧraẗi ăl ḥisābi ḫašabi ʿalà ʾan yakūna ʿalà kulli wāḥid:in min nā ṯulṯu dīnār:in wa ĭdfaʿ ʾayḍ:an min ʿind ī 
 <lb n="25"/>li kayl:in ṯulṯa dīnār:in yakūnu l ī yaṣiḥḥu min hu šayʾ:un wa lam yaʾḫuḏ ṭāhir:un šayʾ:an min ø nā ʾillā niṣfa dīnār:in 
 <lb n="26"/>qabla ʾan tanfuḏa 
 <lb n="27"/>ăl maʿdiyaẗu 
 <lb n="28"/>bi ḥamli ăl ḫašabi 
 <lb n="29"/>wa maʿa fī mā 
 <lb n="30"/>ḥaddaṯtu ḥdyṯ katabtu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="31"/>la hu kafālat kifāyaẗ:un ī 
 <lb n="32"/>qaraʾtu 
 <lb n="33"/>ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="34"/>ăs salāma 
 <lb n="35"/>wa waladi waladu ka 
 <lb n="36"/>wa ʾaḫū ka 
 <lb n="37"/>wa ʾuṣiḥḥu ʾahlu ø ka la ø ka ø fī kulli 
 <lb n="38"/>mā ʿāfiyaẗ:in fī ø hi ø taqraʾu yuqriʾu yuqrū hu 
 <lb n="39"/>ʿalay ka ăs salāma salāmu 
 <lb n="40"/>wa baʿda ʾan katabtu hāḏā ăl kitāba ǧāʾa ʿumaru bnu ṣāliḥ:in wa ĭntaqala ĭʿtaqala ăl ḫašaba ḫašabu 
 <lb n="41"/>wa qāla mā nafraḥu nufriǧu yufriǧu ʾillā bi dīnārayni wa ṯumn:in fa katabtu ʾilà ʾabū ka bi ø naqd:in yunfiḏa ʾilay ya ăd dīnāra 
 <lb n="42"/>ăllaḏī dafaʿtu ʾilay hi li yadfaʿa hu ʾilay hi wa ʾadfaʿu ʾanā ʾilay hi bi ø ăl bāqī bāqiya wa 
 <lb n="43"/>wa kāna hāḏā ăl ḫiṭābu bi ḥaḍraẗi ʾabū ǧaʿfara ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="44"/>ø fa dafaʿa yadfaʿa ăd dīnāra ăl ʾāḫara ʾilà yaḥyà ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="45"/>li ʾaḫ ī wa sayyid ī ʾabī ʿabdi ăl lāhi muḥammad:ini bni mūsà mina ăl ḥasani bni nuʿmāna ăl bulyanāwiyyi 
 <lb n="46"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa hu wa ʾadāma ʿizza hu wa ******* 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		I am writing, O Aḥmad b. Hudayy - may God prolong your life and may He cause your might and strength to continue -
			<lb n="3"/>
		from Qûṣ in safety and good health - praise and thanks be to their giver - on Thurs-
			<lb n="4"/>
		day when eight (nights) had passed of Raǧab - may God make it honoured for his favourite - and blessings on all
			<lb n="5"/>
		the years to come; and praise be to God, the Lord of all created beings. Now I have written many letters to you
			<lb n="6"/>
		since the day of the last incidents to the patricius, and I have already requested you to write me
			<lb n="7"/>
		from Aḫmîm, but you have not done so. And there came a letter of Bišr&#039;s to his brothers with Faraǧ al-Baṭrîqî, but he had no
			<lb n="8"/>
		letter for you. Now I have already written two notes to you through Yaḥyâ - may God exalt him - before this present one
			<lb n="9"/>
		of which you may become aware. Thereafter arrived the rest of the timber which is (now) in Luxor, viz.
			<lb n="10"/>
		twenty-six pieces, which I had already loaded on the ferry-boat of ʿÎsâ b. Tanûs, who has there delivered them (i.e. in Luxor),
		... und ich habe es (sc. das Holz) auf die Fähre von ʿĪsā b. Tanūs verladen (lassen) - Gott lasse sie wohlbehalten ankommen!
			<lb n="11"/>
		and six pieces (from a former stock ?) were still in Luxor, nay, two (pieces) thereof have been discharged in the island (al-Ǧazīra), and (there are) two (pieces) lying in the sand,
		Und es sind in Luxor sechs Stück (Holz) verblieben, die noch nicht verladen worden sind. ...
			<lb n="12"/>
		and two pieces, which had been on the crab (ϰάραβος), were found spoiled and damaged, so that they were not loaded.
			<lb n="13"/>
		My lord the judge - whose might may God cause to continue - would like to write a letter for me to both the masters - may God strengthen
			<lb n="14"/>
		them - respecting the keeping back of twelve dînârs, and I hope that they will do (so). For you know that
			<lb n="15"/>
		... Denn wenn sie diese (12 Dinar) stehen lassen,
		the master - may God strengthen him - has to pay six dînârs all in all. But verily, they have kept them (sc. the six dînârs) back
			<lb n="16"/>
		erlangen wir (dadurch) hierin (sc. bei der finanziellen Transaktion) Erleichterung. Und ich einigte mich mit Abū Ǧaʿfar - Gott stütze ihn - darauf, daß,
		in spite of our claim according to that confirmation, and I have agreed with Abû Ǧaʿfar - whom God may strengthen - that,
			<lb n="17"/>
		supposing you find it suitable, I have kept back two dînârs from your debt, and I have booked this with the fourteen dînârs, which are
		wenn sie (sc. die 12 Dinar) stehen bleiben, ich in Deinem Namen zwei Dinar stehen lasse. ...
			<lb n="18"/>
		... und das Guthaben des Scheichs beträgt sechs (Dinar). Wenn diese Transaktion abgeschlossen ist,
		with the master and also (with) Abû Ǧaʿfar - may God exalt him - and a small balance remains in favour of the master. This is perfect.
			<lb n="19"/>
		Now Abû Ǧaʿfar has brought on his behalf and on behalf of ʿAlî two hundred and twenty dînârs, while you all shall pay thirty
		übernimmt Abū Ǧaʿfar für sich und für ʿAlī zweihundertzwanzig Dinar. ...
			<lb n="20"/>
		dînârs, and Yaḥyâ shall pay four dînârs instead of the sum of fifty-eight (dînârs); and you may balance the whole amount thereof
		... und eine Gruppe (von restlichen Personen) übernimmt hiervon
			<lb n="21"/>
		(jeweils) zwei Dinar. ...
		with two dînârs. I have already written the memorandum for Yaḥyâ respecting the bond of Abû Ǧaʿfar for that which is to my credit and to your credit, this being with
			<lb n="22"/>
		... Das, was er nach Deiner Abreise von mir erhalten hat, ist ein Dinar (für den) Hobel (?), eineinhalb Dinar Gebühr des Holzes
		Yaḥyâ, and what, after you, he took from me is one clipped dînâr and one dînâr and a half as balance of the account
			<lb n="23"/>
		and one dînâr for Abuʾl-Ḥasan b. Ḥâṭib; we do not know that you have called me to render account for one dînâr  and (that) you have returned it
		und ein Dinar namens Abū l-Ḥasan b. Ḥāṭibs. Ich wüsste nicht, daß Du mit mir wegen eines Dinars abgerechnet hast, den ich für
			<lb n="24"/>
		for balancing of the account, provided that to the debit of every one of us there will be a third of a dînâr. Hand over also of my own
		für die Gebühr des Holzes bezahlt habe. ...
			<lb n="25"/>
		to Chael a third of a dînâr, which shall be to me credit 〚......〛 anything thereof being settled. And Ṭâhir did not receive anything but a half [of a dînâr],
			<lb n="26"/>
		before the ferry-boat
			<lb n="27"/>
		with the
			<lb n="28"/>
		load of timbers arrived
			<lb n="29"/>
		and with that which
		Das, was
			<lb n="30"/>
		ich Dir (hier) geschrieben habe,
		I ... ... ... to you
			<lb n="31"/>
		for him as my guarantee (pledge ?)
		muß genügen!
			<lb n="32"/>
		I greet
			<lb n="33"/>
		you
			<lb n="35"/>
		and your son
		Dein Sohn,
			<lb n="36"/>
		and your brother
		Dein Bruder
			<lb n="37"/>
		and ......................
		and I attest the authenticity of all that is 
		und Deine Leute (d.h. Deine Ehefrau bzw. Eine Ehefrauen) sind bei bester
			<lb n="38"/>
		Gesundheit; sie grüßen
		in it for you and you (can) read it
			<lb n="39"/>
		Dich.
		Greetings to you.
			<lb n="40"/>
		And after I had written this letter, ʿUmar b. Ṣâliḥ came and removed the timbers.
		And after I had written this letter, ʿUmar b. Ṣâliḥ came and the timbers were removed.
		Nachdem ich diesen Brief geschrieben hatte, kam ʿUmar b. Ṣāliḥ und beschlagnahmte die Bretter.
			<lb n="41"/>
		Er sagte, er werde (sie) nur für zweieinhalb Dinar freigeben. ... So schrieb ich denn Deinem Vater, er möge mir den Dinar übersenden,
		He said &#034;We are not satisfied but with two dînârs and a third (of a dînâr)&#034;. So I wrote to your father, that he should pay me in cash the dînâr,
			<lb n="42"/>
		den ich ihm gegeben hatte. ...
		which I had handed over to him that he should pay it to him; and I will pay him the rest〚and it suffices〛.
			<lb n="43"/>
		This discourse took place in the presence of Abû Ǧaʿfar - may God exalt him.
			<lb n="44"/>
		Er (sc. der Vater des Adressaten, vgl. r 2f.) möge also den anderen Dinar Yaḥyā - Gott stärke ihn - übergeben.
		〚Now he han〛ded over the other dînâ&lt;r&gt; to Yaḥyâ, may God exalt him.
			<lb n="45"/>
		To my brother and lord Abû ʿAbdallâh Muḥammad b. Mûsâ from al-Ḥasan b. Nuʿmân, originating from al-Bulyanâ.
			<lb n="46"/>
		May God prolong his life and may he cause his might and ...... to continue.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
