<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="161" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_82" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 082 (= CPR XXI 16)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_82</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106514</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /> هر مرقوره بن الححه أنّك 
 <lb n="2"/>  سألتني وطلبت إلي أن أكريك أربعة 
 <lb n="3"/>  عشر فدّانا أرض طيّبة سودا من أرض 
 <lb n="4"/>  مقطول على أن تزرعها قمح وكتّان 
 <lb n="5"/>  بـأحد عشر دينرا نقد بيت 
 <lb n="6"/>  المال ووزنه فأجبتك إلى ذلك 
 <lb n="7"/>  فازرع على بركة اللّه وعونـه فما 
 <lb n="8"/>  تزيّدت فحساب ذلك وما بوّرت فعليك 
 <lb n="9"/>  خراجه وذلك لما ولخراج سنة 
 <lb n="10"/>  ثلث وخمسين ومائتن 
 <lb n="11"/>  من ذلك من أرض المتعة تزرع كتّان δ بدينر ϝ 
 <lb n="12"/>  مجرى أرض سدهيوه من αχ 
 <lb n="13"/>  ومن ذلك قمح غير <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الـور </lem><rdg resp="Frantz-Murphy">الذرّ</rdg></app> ε دينر من χ 
 <lb n="14"/>  عند البئر في الرّأس القبلي بجول الأندر 
 <lb n="15"/>  شهد رضوان بن عبد الواحد على إقرار الحارث 
 <lb n="16"/>  بن اللّيث بجميع ما في هذا الكتاب وذلك في شوّال 
 <lb n="17"/>  سنة ثلث وخمسين ومائى شهد الـحر بن علي 
 <lb n="18"/>  بن سليمن بما في هذا السجل 
 <lb n="19"/>  شهد عيسى بن نجد على إقرار الحارث بن الليث 
 <lb n="20"/>  بهذا السجل 
 <lb n="21"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="6" unit="character" /> مرقوره <gap reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="character" /> من هذا السجل 
 <lb n="22"/>  من قبل صحب أو سلطان <gap reason="illegible" extent="15" unit="character" /> 
 <lb n="23"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /> ذلك 
 <lb n="24"/>  شهد أحمد بن عبد الخالق على ما في هذا الكتاب 
 <lb n="25"/>  فدّان دينر 
 <lb n="26"/>  ιδ ια كتّان δ ϝ 
 <lb n="27"/>  وڤمح ι ε من χ 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** ** har marqūrah bn ăl ḥḥh ʾanna ka 
 <lb n="2"/>saʾalta nī wa ṭalabta ʾilay ya ʾan ʾukriya ka ʾarbaʿaẗa 
 <lb n="3"/>ʿašara faddān:an ʾarḍ ṭayyibaẗ:an sawdāʾa min ʾarḍi 
 <lb n="4"/>maqṭūla ʿalà ʾan tazraʿa hā qamḥ wa kattān 
 <lb n="5"/>bi ʾaḥada ʿašara dīnār:an naqda bayti 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl māli wa wazni hi fa ʾaǧabtu ka ʾilà ḏālika 
 <lb n="7"/>fa ĭzraʿ ʿalà barakaẗi ăl lāhi wa ʿawni hi fa mā 
 <lb n="8"/>tazayyadta fa ḥisābu ḏālika wa mā bawwarta fa ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="9"/>ḫarāǧu hu wa ḏālika li māʾi wa li ḫarāǧi sanaẗi 
 <lb n="10"/>ṯalāṯ:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾatayni 
 <lb n="11"/>min ḏālika min ʾarḍi ăl mutʿaẗi tazraʿu kattān 4 bi dīnār:in 6 
 <lb n="12"/>maǧriya ʾarḍi sadhayūh min 1+1/2 
 <lb n="13"/>wa min ḏālika qamḥ:un ġayru ăl ăḏ warri ḏarri 5 dīnār min 1/2 
 <lb n="14"/>ʿinda ăl biʾri fī ăr raʾsi ăl qibliyyi bi ǧawli ăl ʾandari 
 <lb n="15"/>šahida riḍwānu bnu ʿabdi ăl wāḥidi ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl ḥāriṯi 
 <lb n="16"/>bni ăl layṯi bi ǧamīʿi mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi wa ḏālika fī šawwāl:in 
 <lb n="17"/>sanaẗa ṯalāṯ:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗay šahida ăl ḥurru bnu ʿaliyyi 
 <lb n="18"/>bni sulaymāna bi mā fī hāḏā ăs siǧilli 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida ʿīsà bnu naǧid:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl ḥāriṯi bni ăl layṯi 
 <lb n="20"/>bi hāḏā ăs siǧilli 
 <lb n="21"/>****** marqūrah ***** min hāḏā ăs siǧilli 
 <lb n="22"/>min qibali ṣāḥib:in ʾaw sulṭān:in *************** 
 <lb n="23"/>** ḏālika 
 <lb n="24"/>šahida ʾaḥmadu bnu ʿabdi ăl ḫāliqi ʿalà mā fī hāḏā ăl kitābi 
 <lb n="25"/>faddān dīnār 
 <lb n="26"/>14 11 kattān 4 1/2 
 <lb n="27"/>wa qamḥ 10 5 min 1/2 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  [.........] ....... Marqūrah ibn [....] Verily you
 	  .................. Merqûre b. ...... (?). Verily thou
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  asked me and requested of me that I rent to you four-
 	  hast asked and petitioned that I lease unto thee four-
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  teen faddâns of good black earth belonging to the land of
 	  teen faddans of good black land of the land
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  Maqṭûl that thou mayest sow it with wheat and flax
 	  of Maqṭūl, on the condition that thou sow it with wheat and flax
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  for eleven dinars cash of the treasury
 	  for eleven dînârs full weight money of
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  and it was weighted out. Herewith I grant you that.
 	  the Treasury. I have, therefore, granted thee this.
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  So sow with the blessing of God and his aid. And whatever
 	  Sow, then, with the blessing and help of God; what
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  thou hast done in addition (to what thou hast been obliged) shall be (reckoned) to (thy) account, and what thou hast fallowed, the land-
 	  you increased, there will be a reckoning of that. And whatever you fallowed,
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  tax thereof is incumbent upon thee, viz. for water and for the impost of the year
 	  you owe its kharāj. And that is for the water and for the kharāj of the year
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  three and fifty and two hundred.
 	  two hundred and fifty three.
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  Of this 4 (faddâns) are usufruct land (12) (by) the canal of the land of Sadheu (?), (11) to be sown with flax, at (a rent of) 6 dînâr(s)
 	  Part of that, part of the usufruct land (mutaʿ), you will sow with flax 4 &#039;for a dinar&#039;
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  along the land of (Sadhiyu) rented at 1 1/2
 	  (reckoning) at 1 1/2 dînâr(s per faddân)
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  and of that, without [......], 5 rented at &#039;dinar&#039; 1/2
 	  and thereof (for) wheat without parings 5 dînârs, (reckoning) at 1/4 dînâr (per faddân)
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  at the well at the southern end at the side of the treshing floor.
 	  near the well at the southern edge in the circuit of the treshing-floor (?)
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  Riḍwân b. ʿAbd al-Wâḥid is witness to the acknowledgment by al-Ḥâriṯ
 	  Riḍwān ibn ʿAbd al-Wāḥid bore witness to the agreement of al-Ḥārith
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  b. al-Laiṯ respecting all that (is contained) in this contract, and this in Šawwâl
 	  ibn. al-Layth to all that is in this writing. And that is in Shawwāl
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  of the year three and fifty and two hundred. Al-Ḥurr ibn ʿAlī
 	  of the year two hundred and fifty three. Al-Ḥurr b. ʿAlî
		 <lb n="18"/>
 	  b. Sulaimân is witness to the tenor of this siǧill. 
 	  ibn Sulayman bore witness to what is in this register.
		 <lb n="19"/>
 	  ʿÎsa b. Naǧid is witness to the acknowledgment by al-Ḥâriṯ b. al-Laiṯ
 	  ʿĪsā b. Najd bore witness to the agreement of al-Ḥārith ibn al-Layth
		 <lb n="20"/>
 	  in this register. 
 	  respecting this siǧill. 
		 <lb n="21"/>
 	  ......... Marqūrah ........................ from this register. 
 	  ......... Merqûre ........................ of this siǧill. 
		 <lb n="22"/>
 	  from any administrator or governor ...........................
 	  on the part of an associate or the authority (sulṭān) have [.....
		 <lb n="23"/>
 	  [.....] that
		 <lb n="24"/>
 	  Aḥmad b. ʿAbd al-Ḫāliq is witness to the tenor of this contract.
 	  Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Khāliq bore witness to what is in this writing.
		 <lb n="25"/>
 	  faddan dinar
 	  Faddân dînâr
		 <lb n="26"/>
 	  14 11 flax 4 6
 	  14 ... 11 ... flax ... 4 (faddâns for) 6 (dînârs)
		 <lb n="27"/>
 	  and wheat ... 10 ... 5 reckoning at 1/2 (dînâr per faddân)
 	  wheat 10 5 rented at 1/2
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
