<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1793" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_316" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 316</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_316</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169534</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  تفضّل يا سيّدي أطال اللّه بقاك واكتب لسيّدي أبي الحسن 
<lb n="3"/>  أيّده اللّه براه عن طوبة باثنا عشر دراهما كنت دفعته إليك 
<lb n="4"/>  ‮بصرّة وزنها ‪ιγχ‬ بها جواز ‪δχ‬ فصار الجمع معسول محتق ‪ιβ‬ 
<lb n="5"/>  فلا توحر عنه البراه بذلك إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="6"/>  ما صار في جملة نفقات سيّدي أيّده اللّه حسبنا اللّه ونعم الوكيل 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>tafaḍḍal yā sayyid ī ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ŭktub li sayyid ī ʾabī ăl ḥasani 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu barāʾaẗ:an ʿan ṭūbaẗa bi ĭṯnā ʿašara darāhim:an kuntu dafaʿtu hu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="4"/>bi ṣurraẗ:in waznu hā ‪13 1/2 bi hā ǧawāz:un ‪4 1/2 fa ṣāra ăl ǧamʿu maʿsūl:un muḥtaqq:un ‪12 
 <lb n="5"/>fa lā tuʾaḫḫir ʿan hu ăl barāʾaẗa bi ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="6"/>mā ṣāra fī ǧumlaẗi nafaqāti sayyid ī ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu ḥasbu nā ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Be so good, O my lord - may God prolong your life - and write to my lord Abu&#039;l-Ḥasan
			<lb n="3"/>
		- may God help him - a quittance from (the month of) Tybi (Ṭûbe) for twelve dirhams, which I had delivered to you
			<lb n="4"/>
		in a purse weighing 13 1/2 (dirhams) therein were current 4 1/2, so that the total was 12 correctly counted out, adjusted.
			<lb n="5"/>
		So do not keep back from him the quittance concerning this, if God wills.
			<lb n="6"/>
		What has come for the entire maintenance of my lord - may God help him. Our sufficiency is God, and He is the best trustee.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
