<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1813" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_326" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 326</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_326</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169552</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  تتقدّم يا سيّدي وشيخي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" extent="8" unit="character" /> </lem><rdg resp="APD">ومن</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">اطال </lem><rdg resp="APD">أعزّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الله </lem><rdg resp="APD">وأجلّ</rdg></app> 
<lb n="3"/>  بقاك وأدام عزّك وجعلني فداك إلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الفلع </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الغلام</rdg></app> 
<lb n="4"/>  بأن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يدفع </lem><rdg resp="“EG”">تدفع</rdg></app> إلى أبي طاهر ثمن جلبّان وحوائج ابتعناها 
<lb n="5"/>  منه لسيّدي الشّريف أدام اللّه عزّه ثلثة دنانير 
<lb n="6"/>  ونصف وقيراطين من ثمن العسل المحمول 
<lb n="7"/>  من عندنا إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="8"/>  الحمد للّه وسلم على مختاره الّذي اصطفى 
<lb n="9"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وحسبنا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وحسبي</rdg></app> اللّه <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">وحده</unclear> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>tataqaddamu yā sayyid ī wa šayḫ ī ******** wa ø man ø ʾaʿazzu ø ø wa ʾaǧallu ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="3"/>baqāʾa ka wa ʾadāma ʿizza ka wa ǧaʿala nī fidāʾa ka ʾilà ăl falaʿi ġulāmi 
 <lb n="4"/>bi ʾan tadfaʿa yadfaʿa ʾilà ʾabī ṭāhir:in ṯamana ǧulubbāna wa ḥawāʾiǧa ĭbtaʿnā hā 
 <lb n="5"/>min hu li sayyid ī ăš šarīfi ʾadāma ăl lāhu ʿizza hu ṯalāṯaẗa danānīra 
 <lb n="6"/>wa niṣf wa qīrāṭayni min ṯamani ăl ʿasali ăl maḥmūli 
 <lb n="7"/>min ʿindi nā ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa salām:un ʿalà muḫtāri hi ăllaḏī ĭṣṭafà 
 <lb n="9"/>wa ḥasbu nā ī ăl lāhu waḥda hu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes, des Barmherzigen und Erbarmungsvollen!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Betake yourself, O my lord and master ........................... - may God prolong
		Gib, o mein Herr und Scheich und (mir) Hochgeehrter und Hochverehrter - Gott lasse Dich lange
			<lb n="3"/>
		leben, gewähre Dir weiterhin Ansehen und mache mich zu Deinem Lösegeld -, dem Burschen (sc. dem Schreiber) Anweisung,
		your life and may He cause your might to continue, and may He make me your ransom - to al-Falaʿ (?)
			<lb n="4"/>
		daß er Abū Ṭāhir den Preis von Platterbsen und (anderen) Dingen, die wir
		that you may pay to Abû Ṭâhir the price for the chickling pea and the articles which we have bought
			<lb n="5"/>
		from him for my noble lord, whose might God cause to continue, three dînârs
		von ihm für meinen edlen Herrn (sc. den Adressaten) - Gott gewähre ihm weiterhin Ansehen - gekauft haben, aushändigt, drei Dinar
			<lb n="6"/>
		and a half and two carats of the price for the honey, which was carried away
		und einen halben (oder und ein halber) und zwei Karat als Preis des
			<lb n="7"/>
		aus unserem Bestand gelieferten Honigs, so Gott will.
		from what we have, if God wills.
			<lb n="8"/>
		Praise be to God and safety to His elected, who has been chosen
		Preis sei Gott! Er spende seinem Auserwählten, den er erkoren hat, Heil!
			<lb n="9"/>
		and my sufficiency is God alone (?) ...
		Mein Genüge ist Gott allein!
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
