<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1814" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_327" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 327</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_327</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169553</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="0"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="1"/>  وعافية والحمد للّه رب العلمين كثيرا ولو لا شغلي لكنت موضع 
<lb n="2"/>  كتابي <app type="BL"><lem resp="sīn with dash above">ليسلّم </lem><rdg resp="Diem ‹Ligatur ʾalif-lām›?">أسلّم</rdg></app> عليك وحقّك علينا واجب وقد كنت وجّهت 
<lb n="3"/>  إليك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دفعتي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">رقعتي</rdg></app> مع فاتك فسلّمت إليه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دينارا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">دينار</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">قيمته </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وزنه</rdg></app> أحد وعشرين 
<lb n="4"/>  قيراط ونصف <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فقد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وقد</rdg></app> بلغني ما فعلت وربع دينار إلّا حبّة 
<lb n="5"/>  جواز صار <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دينر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">دينار</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="sīn with dash above">مغسول </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مغسول</rdg></app> قيراطين جواز وكان <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">يبقا</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ the word is fully preserved">بقا</rdg></app> من شهر 
<lb n="6"/>  رمضان فأحب عزّك اللّه أن تحاسبه من حساب ثلثي دينار كما 
<lb n="7"/>  رسمت علي فقال حقّي منه وأنا محتشم منك وأنا أكتب إليك 
<lb n="8"/>  في كل وقت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بحقّي </lem><rdg resp="APD">فبحقّي</rdg></app> عليك يا سيّدي إن قصرت في هذا <app type="BL"><lem resp="šīn with dash above">الشّي </lem><rdg resp="APD">الكسر</rdg></app> 
<lb n="9"/>  فإنى محتاج إليه وأنا مار إلى الفسطاط <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إشّا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">إنشاء</rdg></app> اللّه قرأت عليك 
<lb n="10"/>  السّلم كثيرا وعلى جميع <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ارعو</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ omitted by the scribe who originally started a phrase like ‹ʾahli baytika›">من</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">پاپه </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ yaḥūṭu, but see translation">تحوط</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عساپپك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">به</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">السلم </lem><rdg resp="Diem, with one superfluous tooth before the ʾalif">عنايتك</rdg></app> كپپرا 
<lb n="11"/>  حسبي اللّه ونعم الوكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـيل</supplied> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="2"/>wa ʿāfiyaẗ:in wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi rabbi ăl ʿālamīna kaṯīr:an wa law lā šuġl ī la kuntu mawḍiʿa 
 <lb n="3"/>kitāb ī li ø yusallima ʾusallima ʿalay ka wa ḥaqqu ka ʿalay nā wāǧib:un wa qad kuntu waǧǧahtu 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾilay ka dafʿat ruqʿat ī maʿa fātik:in fa sallamta ʾilay hi dīnār:an dīnār qīmatu waznu hu ʾaḥad:un wa ʿišrīna 
 <lb n="5"/>qīrāṭ wa niṣf:un fa wa qad balaġa nī mā faʿalta wa rubʿu dīnār:in ʾillā ḥabbaẗ:an 
 <lb n="6"/>ǧawāz:un ṣāra dīnār maġsūl maʿsūl qīrāṭayni ǧawāz:un wa kāna yabqā baqā min šahri 
 <lb n="7"/>ramaḍāna fa ʾuḥibbu ʿazza ka ăl lāhu ʾan tuḥāsiba hu min ḥisābi ṯulṯay dīnār:in kamā 
 <lb n="8"/>rasamta ʿalay ya fa qāla ḥaqq ī min hu wa ʾanā muḥtašim:un min ka wa ʾanā ʾaktubu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="9"/>fī kulli waqt:in ø fa bi ḥaqq ī ʿalay ka yā sayyid ī ʾin qaṣurta fī hāḏā ăš ăl šayʾi kasri 
 <lb n="10"/>fa ʾin nī muḥtāǧ:un ʾilay hi wa ʾanā mārr:un ʾilà ăl fusṭāṭi ʾiš ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu qaraʾtu ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="11"/>ăs salāma kaṯīr:an wa ʿalà ǧamīʿi ʾrʿw man ø taḥūṭu BʾBh bi ø hi ʿsʾBBk ʿināyatu ø ka ăs salāmu kaṯīr:an 
 <lb n="12"/>ḥasb iya ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		[Ich schreibe Dir - Eulogie (?) im Zustand der Wohlbehaltenheit]
			<lb n="2"/>
		and health, and praise be often to God, the Lord of all created beings. And if it had not been for my work, I would have come in the place
		und der Gesundheit, Preis sei Gott, dem Herrn der Welt, vielmals. Wäre ich nicht (zu sehr) beschäftigt, so wäre ich an der Stelle
			<lb n="3"/>
		(dieses) meines Briefes, um Dich zu grüßen, ist doch Dein Anspruch mir gegenüber (für mich) verpflichtend! Ich hatte
		of my letter to greet you; and your claim (thereto) is binding upon us. I have already dispatched
			<lb n="4"/>
		Dir durch Fātik meine Zahlungsanweisung (zu seinen Gunsten) überbringen lassen, worauf Du ihm einen Dinar ausgehändigt hast, dessen Gewicht einundzwanzig
		my payment to you with Fâtik. He has therefore handed over to you one dînâr in the value of twenty one
			<lb n="5"/>
		carats and a half-(carat). Information as to what you have done has reached me along with a current quarter of a dînâr less one ḥabba
		einhalb Karat war - ich habe erfahren, was Du getan hast -, und einen passablen Vierteldinar weniger eine Ḥabba;
			<lb n="6"/>
		das ergibt einen vollen Dinar (und) zwei passable Karat, und zwar war (der Fātik zustehende Betrag) ein Rest aus dem Monat
		which makes one dînâr correctly counted out (and) two current carats, which had &lt;remained&gt; from the month of
			<lb n="7"/>
		Ramaḍān. Ich möchte deshalb - Gott stärke Dich -, daß Du mit ihm (sc. Fātik) in Höhe von zwei Drittel Dinar abrechnest, wie
		Ramaḍân. Now I wish - may God exalt you - that you should deduct from the account of two thirds of a dînâr, as
			<lb n="8"/>
		Du es (nunmehr) mir vorgeschrieben hast. Er sagt nämlich (zu mir): &#039;Mein Anspruch (auf das noch ausstehende Geld) ist ihm gegenüber, und ich habe (deshalb) Dir gegenüber Hemmungen (es von Dir zu verlangen).&#039; Ich bin mit Dir ständig
		you have assigned (it) to me. But he said: &#034;I have (to obtain) a claim from him&#034;. And I feel respect for you and write to you
			<lb n="9"/>
		at all times. By the claim which I have on you, O my lord, if you have fallen short in this matter,
		in brieflichem Kontakt. Deshalb, bei meinem Anspruch gegen Dich, o mein Herr: Sei nicht nachlässig bei diesem Bruchteilsbetrag!
			<lb n="10"/>
		Ich kann ihn nicht entbehren, da ich nach al-Fusṭāṭ hinübergehen werde, so Gott will! Ich grüße Dich
		I indeed need it while I pass over to al-Fusṭâṭ, if God wills. I greet you
			<lb n="11"/>
		vielmals, und alle {Angehö}, &lt;die&gt; Deine Fürsorge umfängt, viele Grüße!
		warmly and also (to all) the ..................... copious greetings.
			<lb n="12"/>
		Gott ist mein Genüge; er ist der beste Sachwalter!
		Our sufficiency is God, and He ist the best trustee.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
