<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="205" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_83" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 083 (= Chrest.Khoury I 70)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_83</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">106517</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  ‮ـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>‬ 
<lb n="2"/>   اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="3"/>  ‮هذا كتاب سجل من أبو النّجم بدر الاو<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>‬ 
<lb n="4"/>  ‮كتبه لشبيب بن إسطرهيوه إنّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـك</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سألتني</supplied>‬‬ 
<lb n="5"/>  ‮وطلبت إلي أن أسجّلك من أراضي ساقية قلود<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ه</supplied>‬ 
<lb n="6"/>  من ثلثة فدادين أرض طيّبة بثلثة سودا بثلثة 
<lb n="7"/>  دنانير على الرّسم البلد الجاري الأجود البلد في الصرف الأجود 
<lb n="8"/>  والحين والآن فأجبتك إلى ذلك على أن تودى خراجك 
<lb n="9"/>  عندهم على على نـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـفسه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مـ</supplied>ـن 
<lb n="10"/>  على بركة اللّه وعونه فما تزيّد<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ت</supplied> فحساب بسجلّك 
<lb n="11"/>  وما بوّرته فخراجه لازم لك وذلك لخراج سنة 
<lb n="12"/>  ثمان وأربعين وثلثماية 
<lb n="13"/>  تزرع في المعلن فدّان بدينر 
<lb n="14"/>  ‫ما وجب ‫γ‬ ‫γ‬ 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** *** *** 
 <lb n="2"/>bi ĭsmi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="3"/>hāḏā kitābu siǧill:in min ʾabū ăn naǧmi badr:ini ăl ʾaw*** 
 <lb n="4"/>kataba hu li šabībi bni ʾisṭurhayūha ʾinna ka saʾalta nī 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ṭalabta ʾilay ya ʾan ʾusaǧǧila ka min ʾarāḍī sāqiyaẗi qalūdaha 
 <lb n="6"/>mina ăl baladi ṯalāṯaẗa fadādīna ʾarḍ ṭayyibaẗ:an sawdāʾa bi ṯalāṯaẗi 
 <lb n="7"/>danānīra maʿsūlaẗ:in ʿalà ăr rasmi ăl ǧārī fī ăl baladi fī ăṣ ṣarfi ăl ʾaǧwadi 
 <lb n="8"/>wa ăl ḥīni wa ăl ʾāni fa ʾaǧabtu ka ʾilà ḏālika ʿalà ʾan tuʾaddiya ḫarāǧa ka 
 <lb n="9"/>maʿa ʾanǧumi ăs sulṭāni ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu wa ʾawqāti hi fa ĭzraʿ 
 <lb n="10"/>ʿalà barakaẗi ăl lāhi wa ʿawni hi fa mā tazayyadta fa ḥisāb:un bi siǧilli ka 
 <lb n="11"/>wa mā bawwarta hu fa ḫarāǧu hu lāzim:un la ka wa ḏālika li ḫarāǧi sanaẗi 
 <lb n="12"/>ṯamān:in wa ʾarbaʿīna wa ṯalāṯi miyaẗ:in 
 <lb n="13"/>tazraʿu fī ăl muʿlani faddān bi dīnār:in 
 <lb n="14"/>mā waǧaba 3 3 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
			<lb n="2"/>
		Au nom de Dieu clément et miséricordieux!
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful 
			<lb n="3"/>
		Ceci es tune contrat de bail de la part d‘Abū l-Naǧm Badr al-[...]
		This is the certificate of registration of Abu ʾn-Naǧm Badr al-Aw[...]
			<lb n="4"/>
		il l’a écrit pour Šabīb Ibn Isṭurheu: [Tu m’as demandé]
		which he has written for Šabîb b. Isṭurheu. Verily th[ou hast asked] 
			<lb n="5"/>
		and petitioned that I might register for thee the lands of Sâqiyat Qalûde (Claudios), 
		et sollicité de t’affermer, parmi les domaines de Sāqiyat Qlūde
			<lb n="6"/>
		appartenant au district, trois faddān-s de bonne terre noire pour troisppertaining to the district, three faddâns for thee of good black earth for three
		appertaining to the district, three faddâns for thee of good black earth for three
			<lb n="7"/>
		dīnārs authentiques selon l’usage courant &lt;dans le district&gt; et d’après le meilleur cours de change
		dînârs, to be counted out at the usual, current, best exchange 
			<lb n="8"/>
		at any time and now. I have, therefore, granted thee this, so that thou mayest pay thy land-tax 
		en tout temps et maintenant. Et j’ai répondu à cela, à condition que tu paies ton impôt foncier
			<lb n="9"/>
		ensemble avec les quotes-parts du gouverneur, que Dieu le fortifie, et en ses termes. Ainsi sème
		together with the instalments of the Governor - may God exalt him - at the due time. Sow, then, 
			<lb n="10"/>
		avec la bénédiction de Dieu et son aide; et ce que tu cultives en plus, (il y aura) un compte (là-dessu);
		with the blessing and the help of God; what thou hast done in addition shall be reckoned in accordance with thy contract, 
			<lb n="11"/>
		and what thou hast fallowed, the land-tax thereof is obligatory upon thee, viz. for the impost of the year 
		et ce que tu laisses inculte, son impôt t’incombe, et ceci de l’impôt de l’année
			<lb n="12"/>
		three hundred and forty eight. 
		trois cent quarante-huit
			<lb n="13"/>
		Thou sowest on (the land) publicly known ... faddân, for dînâr(s) 
		Tu sèmes dans du terrain publiquement connu. Faddān pour dinar
			<lb n="14"/>
		Ce qui est dû 3 3
		that which has been obligatory: ... 3 ... 3
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
