<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1109" xml:id="Grohmann_APEL_68" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Cair.Arab. 068</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Grohmann_APEL_68</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">168967</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم وما توفيقي <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">إلّا</supplied> باللّه عليه توكّلت وإليه أنيب 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى ريحان بن نشوان المعروف بالعجلاني من جملة العبيد البربر المستخدم بمركز الأشمونين من إسطوراس التّنّيسي بن بييسه النّصراني السّاكن 
<lb n="3"/>  يومئذ بهذه المدينة المذكورة في هذا الكتاب اشترى منه بماله لنفسه الّذي أنعم اللّه عز وجل به عليه جميع المنزل بأسره وكماله الّذي أعلمه أنّه له وبملكه 
<lb n="4"/>  وفي يده ملكا صحيحا وحقّا واجبا بهذه المدينة المذكورة في الجانب البحري منها على الكوم المطل على الكنيسيّة <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">المعروفة</supplied> <sic n="superfluous">بالترتاپس</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">بالبرتانس</supplied> ويحيط بهذا المنزل <sic n="superfluous">المبتع</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">المبيع</supplied> 
<lb n="5"/>  بأسره وكماله ويجمعه ويشتمل عليه حدود أربعة فالحد القبلي منه ينتهي إلى الزّقاق النّافذ من طرفيه إلى طرق شتّى وفيه يشرع بابه الأوّل 
<lb n="6"/>  كان والحد البحري منه ينتهي إلى بير تعرف بالصّعيدي وإلى بو طوربن مقابر المسلمين وفي هذا الحد يشرع بابه الثّاني والحد الشّرقي منه ينتهي إلى عرصة لبقطر البنّا 
<lb n="7"/>  وإلى دار تعرف لمنصور الرّسول كان وإلى منزل يعرف بسكنا غطارف كان تم انتقل ذلك إلى الأمير ناهض الدّولة وموفّقها والحد الغربي منه 
<lb n="8"/>  ينتهي إلى منزل جعفر بن سباع الإبشادي فاشترى ريحان بن نشوان المعروف بالعجلاني من جملة العبيد البربر المقدّم ذكره من إسطوراس بن 
<lb n="9"/>  بييسه التّنّيسي النّصراني جميع هذا المنزل المحدود الموصوف في هذا الكتاب بحدّه وحدوده ومرافقه كلّها بأرضه وسمائه وسفله وعلوه 
<lb n="10"/>  ونقضه وبنائه وفنائه وكل كثير وقليل هو له داخل فيه وكل قليل وكثير هو له خارج منه وما هو معروف <sic n="superfluous">الپه</sic> به ومنسوب إليه ظاهره // 
<lb n="11"/>  وباطنه عامره وغامره بثمن مبلغه من العين خمسة دنانير إلّا ثلث دينار جياد العيون مستنصريّة مسلّمة للبايع من حق السّوق // 
<lb n="12"/>  شرى صحيحا وبيعا نافذا ماضيا لا شرط فيه ولا خيار ولا استثنى ولا إقالة ولا إعادة ولا رجعة ولا متنويّة لا لردّه ولا لنفسه 
<lb n="13"/>  ولا لأجل ولا لأبد ولا هو على سبيل رهن ولا تلجئة ودفع المشتري إلى البائع له المذكورين في هذا الكتاب جميع ما وقع عليه // 
<lb n="14"/>  هذا البيع المذكور فقبضه منه نقدا في يده تامّا وافيا وأبرأه منه ومن جميعه براه قبض واستيفى بجميعه من كل قول ويمين وحجّة 
<lb n="15"/>  على جميع الوجوه والأسباب كلّها وسلّم البائع إلى المشتري المسمّيين في هذا الكتاب فتسلّمه منه وحازه لنفسه وصار مالا من ماله يتحكّم فيه 
<lb n="16"/>  بحكم الملّاك في أملاكهم وذلك بعد معرفة منهما لما تبايعا عليه وتقليب منهما بجميعه وإنفاذ منهما له فتبايعا ذلك بينهما على ما يوجبه 
<lb n="17"/>  حكم بيع الإسلام وعهدته وضمان دركه وتمام شروطه وتضمّن البائع للمشتري منه جميع الّدرك في ذمّته ومحياه ومماته وخالص 
<lb n="18"/>  ماله فما أدرك هذا المشتري فيما وقع عليه هذا البيع المذكور أو في شي منه من درك من أحد من النّاس كلّهم فعلى البائع له خلاصه 
<lb n="19"/>  من كل درك يدركه في ذلك أو في شي من حقوقه شهد على إقرار البائع بالبيع وقبضه جميع الثّمن المذكور والمشتري بالحوز لنفسه // 
<lb n="20"/>  بجميعه ما فيه بعد أن قرئ عليها فأقرّا بفهمه ومعرفة جميعه في صحّة عقولهما وأبدانهما وجواز أمورهما طائعان غير مكرهان ولا مجبران 
<lb n="21"/>  وكتب في العشر الأوّل من شوّال سنة تسع وخمسين وأربعمائة وفيه لحق حرف مثاله ريحان وأيضا لحق آخر وما هو معروف 
<lb n="22 right"/>  وإصلاح حرف مثاله وأبدانهما ولذلك وقعت الشّهادة 
<lb n="22 left"/>  شهد علي بن أحمد بن خيثم <sic n="superfluous">عن</sic> على إقرار البائع والمشتري بما فيه وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه صح 
<lb n="23 right"/>  شهد علي بن محمّد بن علي المغربي على إقرار البائع والمشتري المقرّين بما فيه 
<lb n="24 right"/>  وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="23 left"/>  شهد سپداپح بن علي بن محمّد على إقرار البائع والمشتري بما فيه وكتب بخطّه في تأريخه 
<lb n="25 far right"/>  شهد محمّد بن عيسى بن عبيدة على إقرار 
<lb n="26 far right"/>  البائع وقبضه الثمن وحوز المشتري بما فيه صح 
<lb n="25 centre right"/>  شهد نطف بن طاهر بن علي 
<lb n="26 centre right"/>  على إقرار البائع بالبيع وقبضه 
<lb n="27 centre right"/>  الثّمن المذكور وحوز المشتري بما فيه 
<lb n="25 centre left"/>  شهد <gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="character" /> الحسن على 
<lb n="26 centre left"/>  إقرار البائع والبيّاع بما فيه وكتب بخطّه في <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">تأريخه</unclear> 
<lb n="25 far left"/>  شهد العبّاد بن هبة اللّه بن العقرب 
<lb n="26 far left"/>  على إقرار البائع والمشتري وكبپ پحطه ڤى 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi wa mā tawfīq ī ʾillā bi ăl lāhi ʿalay hi tawakkaltu wa ʾilay hi ʾunību 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà rayḥānu bnu našwāna ăl maʿrūfu bi ăl ʿaǧlāniyyi min ǧumlaẗi ăl ʿabīdi ăl barbari ăl mustaḫdamu bi markazi ăl ʾušmūnayni min ʾisiṭūrāsa ăt tinnīsiyyi bni bīyisaha ăn naṣrāniyyi ăs sākini 
 <lb n="3"/>yawma ʾiḏ:in bi hāḏihi ăl madīnaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi ĭštarà min hu bi māli hi li nafsi hi ăllaḏī ʾanʿama ăl lāhu ʿazza wa ǧalla bi hi ʿalay hi ǧamīʿa ăl manzili bi ʾasri hi wa kamāli hi ăllaḏī ʾaʿlama hu ʾanna hu la hu wa bi milki hi 
 <lb n="4"/>wa fī yadi hi milk:an ṣaḥīḥ:an wa ḥaqq:an wāǧib:an bi hāḏihi ăl madīnaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi fī ăl ǧānibi ăl baḥriyyi min hā ʿalà ăl kawmi ăl muṭilli ʿalà ăl kunaysiyyaẗi ăl maʿrūfaẗi bi ăl bartānusi wa yuḥīṭu bi hāḏā ăl manzili ăl mabīʿi 
 <lb n="5"/>bi ʾasri hi wa kamāli hi wa yaǧmaʿu hu wa yaštamilu ʿalay hi ḥudūd:un ʾarbaʿaẗ:un fa ăl ḥaddu ăl qibliyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà ăz zuqāqi ăn nāfiḏi min ṭarafay hi ʾilà ṭuruq:in šattà wa fī hi yašraʿu bābu hu ăl ʾawwalu 
 <lb n="6"/>kāna wa ăl ḥaddu ăl baḥriyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà bīr:in tuʿrafu bi ăl ṣaʿīdiyyi wa ʾilà bū ṭūrbuna maqābiri ăl muslimīna wa fī hāḏā ăl ḥaddi yašraʿu bābu hu ăṯ ṯānī wa ăl ḥaddu ăš šarqiyyu min hu yantahī ʾilà ʿarṣaẗ:in li buqṭura ăl bannāʾi 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ʾilà dār:in tuʿrafu li manṣūr:ini ăr rasūli kāna wa ʾilà manzil:in yuʿrafu bi suknā ġaṭārifa kāna tumma ĭntaqala ḏālika ʾilà ăl ʾamīri nāhiḍi ăd dawlaẗi wa muwaffiqi hā wa ăl ḥaddu ăl ġarbiyyu min hu 
 <lb n="8"/>yantahī ʾilà manzili ǧaʿfara bni sibāʿa ăl ʾibšādiyyi fa ĭštarà rayḥānu bnu našwāna ăl maʿrūfu bi ăl ʿaǧlāniyyi min ǧumlaẗi ăl ʿabīdi ăl barbari ăl muqaddami ḏikru hu min ʾisiṭūrāsa bni 
 <lb n="9"/>bīyisaha ăt tinnīsiyyi ăn naṣrāniyyi ǧamīʿa hāḏā ăl manzili ăl maḥdūdi ăl mawṣūfi fī hāḏā ăl kitābi bi ḥaddi hi wa ḥudūdi hi wa marāfiqi hi kulli hā bi ʾarḍi hi wa samāʾi hi wa sufli hi wa ʿulwi hi 
 <lb n="10"/>wa naqḍi hi wa bināʾi hi wa fināʾi hi wa kulli kaṯīr:in wa qalīl:in huwa la hu dāḫil fī hi wa kulli qalīl:in wa kaṯīr:in huwa la hu ḫāriǧ min hu wa mā huwa maʿrūf:un bi hi wa mansūb:un ʾilay hi ẓāhira hu // 
 <lb n="11"/>wa bāṭina hu ʿāmira hu wa ġāmira hu bi ṯaman:in mablaġu hu mina ăl ʿayni ḫamsaẗu danānīra ʾillā ṯulṯa dīnār:in ǧiyādu ăl ʿuyūni mustanṣiriyyaẗ:un musallamaẗ:un li ăl bāyiʿi min ḥaqqi ăs sūqi // 
 <lb n="12"/>šir:an ṣaḥīḥ:an wa bayʿ:an nāfiḏ:an māḍiy:an lā šarṭa fī hi wa lā ḫiyār:un wa lā ĭstiṯn:an wa lā ʾiqālaẗ:un wa lā ʾiʿādaẗ:un wa lā raǧʿaẗ:un wa lā matnawiyyaẗ:un lā li raddi hi wa lā li nafsi hi 
 <lb n="13"/>wa lā li ʾaǧal:in wa lā li ʾabad:in wa lā huwa ʿalà sabīli rahn:in wa lā talǧiʾaẗ:in wa dafaʿa ăl muštarī ʾilà ăl bāʾiʿi la hu ăl maḏkūrayni fī hāḏā ăl kitābi ǧamīʿa mā waqaʿa ʿalay hi // 
 <lb n="14"/>hāḏā ăl bayʿu ăl maḏkūru fa qabaḍa hu min hu naqd:an fī yadi hi tāmm:an wāfiy:an wa ʾabraʾa hu min hu wa min ǧamīʿi hi barāʾaẗa qabḍ:in wa ĭstīf:an bi ǧamīʿi hi min kulli qawl:in wa yamīn:in wa ḥuǧǧaẗ:in 
 <lb n="15"/>ʿalà ǧamīʿi ăl wuǧūhi wa ăl ʾasbābi kulli hā wa sallama ăl bāʾiʿu ʾilà ăl muštarī ăl musammayayni fī hāḏā ăl kitābi fa tasallama hu min hu wa ḥāza hu li nafsi hi wa ṣāra māl:an min māli hi yataḥakkamu fī hi 
 <lb n="16"/>bi ḥukmi ăl mullāki fī ʾamlāki him wa ḏālika baʿda maʿrifaẗ:in min humā li mā tabāyaʿā ʿalay hi wa taqlīb:in min humā bi ǧamīʿi hi wa ʾinfāḏ:in min humā la hu fa tabāyaʿā ḏālika bayna humā ʿalà mā yūǧibu hu 
 <lb n="17"/>ḥukmu bayʿi ăl ʾislāmi wa ʿuhdatu hu wa ḍamānu daraki hi wa tamāmu šurūṭi hi wa taḍammana ăl bāʾiʿu li ăl muštarī min hu ǧamīʿa ăd daraki fī ḏimmati hi wa maḥyā hu wa mamāti hi wa ḫāliṣi 
 <lb n="18"/>māli hi fa mā ʾadraka hāḏā ăl muštariya fī mā waqaʿa ʿalay hi hāḏā ăl bayʿu ăl maḏkūru ʾaw fī šayʾ:in min hu min darak:in min ʾaḥad:in mina ăn nāsi kulli him fa ʿalà ăl bāʾiʿi la hu ḫalāṣu hu 
 <lb n="19"/>min kulli darak:in yudriku hu fī ḏālika ʾaw fī šayʾ:in min ḥuqūqi hi šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi bi ăl bayʿi wa qabḍi hi ǧamīʿa ăṯ ṯamani ăl maḏkūra wa ăl muštarī bi ăl ḥawzi li nafsi hi // 
 <lb n="20"/>bi ǧamīʿi hi mā fī hi baʿda ʾan quriʾa ʿalay himā fa ʾaqarrā bi fahmi hi wa maʿrifaẗi ǧamīʿi hi fī ṣiḥḥaẗi ʿuqūli himā wa ʾabdāni himā wa ǧawāzi ʾumūri himā ṭāʾiʿāni ġayru mukrahāni wa lā muǧbarāni 
 <lb n="21"/>wa kutiba fī ăl ʿašri ăl ʾawwali min šawwāl:in sanaẗa tisʿ:in wa ḫamsīna wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in wa fī hi laḥiqa ḥarf:un miṯālu hu rayḥānu wa ʾayḍ:an laḥiqa ʾāḫaru wa mā huwa maʿrūf:un 
 <lb n="22"/>wa ʾiṣlāḥu ḥarf:in miṯālu hu wa ʾabdāni himā wa li ḏālika waqaʿati ăš šahādaẗu 
 <lb n="23"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu ʾaḥmada bni ḫayṯama ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi ṣaḥḥa 
 <lb n="24"/>šahida ʿaliyyu bnu muḥammadi bni ʿaliyy:ini ăl maġribiyyu ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī ăl muqirrayni bi mā fī hi 
 <lb n="25"/>wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="26"/>šahida SBDʾBḤu bnu ʿaliyyi bni muḥammad:in ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="27"/>šahida muḥammadu bnu ʿīsà bni ʿubaydaẗa ʿalà ʾiqrāri 
 <lb n="28"/>ăl bāʾiʿi wa qabḍi hi ăṯ ṯamana wa ḥawzi ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi ṣaḥḥa 
 <lb n="29"/>šahida naṭifu bnu ṭāhiri bni ʿaliyy:in 
 <lb n="30"/>ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi bi ăl bayʿi wa qabḍi hi 
 <lb n="31"/>ăṯ ṯamana ăl maḏkūra wa ḥawzi ăl muštarī bi mā fī hi 
 <lb n="32"/>šahida ********** ăl ḥasani ʿalà 
 <lb n="33"/>ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl bayyāʿi bi mā fī hi wa kataba bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
 <lb n="34"/>šahida ăl ʿabbādu bnu hibaẗi ăl lāhi bni ăl ʿaqrabi 
 <lb n="35"/>ʿalà ʾiqrāri ăl bāʾiʿi wa ăl muštarī bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī taʾrīḫi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful, and my success is &lt;only&gt; with God, in Him do I trust and to Him shall I return.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is what Raiḥân b. Našwân, known as al-ʿAǧlânî, belonging to the body of the Berber slaves, employed in the district of al-Ušmûnain, has bought from Isiṭôrâs, originating from Tinnîs, son of Bîsa, the Christian, residing
			<lb n="3"/>
		at this time in the town mentioned in this act: he has bought from him with his own money, which God - He is mighty and sublime - has bestowed upon him as a favour, the whole dwelling house entirely and completely, that he (the seller) informed him that it was belonging to him and in his possession
			<lb n="4"/>
		and in his hand(s), as a legal possession and a declared right, situated at the north side of this (above) mentioned town, on the hill looking down upon the little church &lt;known&gt; as al-Bartânos (of the Virgin). Now four boundaries enclose, encompass and surround this dwelling house,
			<lb n="5"/>
		sold entirely and completely: the southern boundary thereof extends to the lane forming from both sides the thoroughfare to diverse roads, with which its former first door communicates;
			<lb n="6"/>
		and the northern boundary thereof extends to a well known as aṣ-Ṣaʿídí and to Bû Ṭûrbon, the Muslim cemetery, and with this boundary communicates its second door; and the eastern boundary thereof extends to the open area belonging to Boqṭor, the builder,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and to the house known as formerly belonging to Manṣûr, the messenger, and to the dwelling house known as the former habitation of Ġaṭârif, then this (house)  passed to the Amîr Nâhiḍ ad-Daula who directs it (the empire) to prosperity; and the western boundary thereof
			<lb n="8"/>
		extends to the dwelling house of Ǧaʿfar b. Sibâʿ, originating from Ibšâda. So the aforesaid Raiḥân b. Našwân, known as al-ʿAǧlânî, belonging to the body of the Berber slaves, has bought from Isiṭôrâs b.
			<lb n="9"/>
		Bîsa, originating from Tinnîs, the Christian, the whole of this dwelling house, defined and described in this act, to its limit and its boundaries and all its appurtenances, with its land and its sky, and (including) what is below and above the surface,
			<lb n="10"/>
		and its beams and its building(s) and its fore-court and all of much and little connected with it within, and all of little and much connected with it without, and what is known as appertaining and relating to it, (be it) outside
			<lb n="11"/>
		or inside, inhabited or empty, for a price which amounts in gold-coins to five dînârs less a third of a dînâr, good gold-coins of al-Mustanṣir, handed over to the seller according to the market-value,
			<lb n="12"/>
		in form of a valid purchase and an effectual (and fully) completed sale in which is no condition and no option (of return) and no reservation and no rescision (by mutual consent) and no possibility of recurrence and no proviso of the right of reversal and no reserving (of the right) either to return it or to annul it,
			<lb n="13"/>
		either temporarily or for good, and it is not in the way of a pledge nor an exclusive bequest. And the buyer has paid to the one who has sold it to him - both mentioned in this act - all (the price) for which this (above) mentioned sale
			<lb n="14"/>
		was effected. Thus he (the buyer) has received it from him as a cash-payment (paid) into his hand(s) fully, entirely, and he has given him a quittance for it and for all of it by means of a receipt (acknowledging that he has) received fully and entirely the whole of it, which releases him from any affirmation or oath or proof
			<lb n="15"/>
		for any causes or reasons whatever; and the seller has handed (it) over to the buyer, both of whom are mentioned in this act, and he has taken it over from him and has acquired possession of it for himself and it has become his own property, he having free disposition of it
			<lb n="16"/>
		according to the free disposition of proprietors over their property, and this after their having been aware of what they both have sold and bought (respectively) and their having examined all of it and their having effected it (the transaction). So they both have bargained together according to what the rule
			<lb n="17"/>
		of Islamic law of sale and covenant and the guarantee of its indemnity and the fulfilment of its conditions makes obligatory, and the seller has become responsible to the one who has bought from him for all claims according to his responsibility, be he alive or dead and out of his own
			<lb n="18"/>
		means. But should any evil consequence (vindicatio) ensue to this buyer respecting that about which this (above) mentioned sale took placee or respecting any portion thereof from any person whatever, it is incumbent upon the one who has sold (it) to him to indemnify him
			<lb n="19"/>
		for any claim that may be made upon him in respect thereto or any rights (connected with it). (The following witnesses) have testified to the acknowledgment by the seller respecting the sale and his taking over the whole of the price mentioned and by the buyer respecting (his) having taken possession for himself
			<lb n="20"/>
		of all that (is contained) herein, after (it) had been read to both of them, so that they have acknowledged that they have understood and comprehended it entirely, they being in a state of sound mind and body and capable of transacting their business, voluntarily, without compulsion and not against their will,
			<lb n="21"/>
		and it has been written in the first decade of Šawwâl of the year four hundred and fifty nine; and herein has been added a word, viz. &#034;Raiḥân&#034; (l. 8) and also another, viz. &#034;and what is known&#034; (l. 10),
			<lb n="22"/>
		and a correction of a word, viz. &#034;and their body&#034; (l. 20) and testimony has been given to this.
			<lb n="23"/>
		ʿAlí b. Aḥmad b. Ḫaiṯam is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer respecting what (is contained) herein and he has written in his (own) handwriting on its date. Valid.
			<lb n="24"/>
		ʿAlî b. Muḥammad b. ʿAlî, originating from the Maġrib, is witness to the acknowledgment by the buyer and seller, both acknowledging what (is contained) herein,
			<lb n="25"/>
		and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="26"/>
		.................. b. ʿAlî b. Muḥammad is witness to the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer in respect of what (is contained) herein and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="27"/>
		Muḥammad b. ʿÎsâ b. ʿUbaida is witness to the acknowledgment
			<lb n="28"/>
		by the seller and his receipt of the price and the taking possession by the byer of what (is contained) herein. Valid.
			<lb n="29"/>
		Naṭif b. Ṭâhir b. ʿAlî is witness
			<lb n="30"/>
		to the acknowledgment by the seller respecting the sale and his receipt
			<lb n="31"/>
		of the mentioned price and the taking possession by the buyer of what (is contained) herein.
			<lb n="32"/>
		........................... son of al-Ḥasan is witness to
			<lb n="33"/>
		the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer respecting what (is contained) herein and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
			<lb n="34"/>
		Al-ʿAbbâd b. Hibatallâh b. al-ʿAqrab is witness
			<lb n="35"/>
		to the acknowledgment by the seller and buyer and he has written (it) in his (own) handwriting on its date.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
