<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="985" xml:id="Guo_Quseir_82" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.QuseirArab. I 82</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Guo_Quseir_82</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113728</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  للمرأة أراد<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ت</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـها الولد 
<lb n="2"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم لطحيطهطيل اللّه لكل شي 
<lb n="3"/>  إذا السّما انشقّت وأذنت لربّها وحقّت وإذا الأرض 
<lb n="4"/>  مدّت وألقتت ما فيها وتخلّت ألقت كل مسلمة في 
<lb n="5"/>  بطنها مسلمة أفيق أفيق من تحت طلقك الوثيق 
<lb n="6"/>  ارمي وأوثق هذا شهرك الحقيق حتّا ولدت 
<lb n="7"/>  مريم مريم يا رب عيسى عليه السّلام وإن انشقّت السّما 
<lb n="8"/>  فكانت وردة كالدّهان فبأي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">آلا</supplied> ربّكما تكذّبان 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>li l marʾaẗi ʾarādat *** hā ăl walad 
 <lb n="2"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi l lṭḥyṭhṭyl ṭ ḥ y ṭ h ṭ y l ăl lāhu li kulli šayʾ:in 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾiḏā ăs samāʾu ĭnšaqqat wa ʾaḏinat li rabbi hā wa ḥuqqat wa ʾiḏā ăl ʾarḍu 
 <lb n="4"/>muddat wa ʾalqat mā fī hā wa taḫallat ʾalqat kullu muslimaẗ:in fī 
 <lb n="5"/>baṭni hā muslimaẗu ʾafīq ʾafīq min taḥti ṭalqi ki ăl waṯīqi 
 <lb n="6"/>ĭrmī wa ʾawṯiq hāḏā šahru ki ăl ḥaqīqu ḥattā waladat 
 <lb n="7"/>maryamu maryamu yā rabbu ʿīsà ʿalay hi ăs salāmu wa ʾini ĭnšaqqati ăs samāʾu 
 <lb n="8"/>fa kānat wardaẗ:an ka ăd dihāni fa bi ʾayyi ʾālāʾi rabbi kumā tukaḏḏibāni 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		For woman who wanted [to have] a boy.
			<lb n="2"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate. (Mystical letters.) May God bless everything!
			<lb n="3"/>
		When heaven is rent assunder and gives ear to its Lord, and is fitly disposed; when earth
			<lb n="4"/>
		is streched out and casts forth what is in it, and voids itself, every Muslim woman may cast forth [what is] in
			<lb n="5"/>
		her womb. [O] Muslim woman! Wake up, wake up from under [the effect of] your tight labor!
			<lb n="6"/>
		Cast forth and hold tight! This is your month of truth! Until
			<lb n="7"/>
		The Virgin Mary gave birth to Jesus, O Lord, peace be upon Him! And when heaven is split asunder,
			<lb n="8"/>
		and turns crimson like red leather - O which of your Lord&#039;s bounties will you and you deny?
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
