<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2171" xml:id="Hinds_Nubia" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.HindsNubia (= P.AbuSafiyaRisalatMusa)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Hinds_Nubia</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  من موسى بن كـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـعب</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إلى</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> صاحب مقرّ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ة</supplied> ونوبة سلم على 
<lb n="3"/>  أوليا اللّه وأهل طاعته <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> وأحمد إليهم اللّه ا 
<lb n="4"/>  لدى لإ إلّه الا 
<lb n="5"/>  أمّا بعد قد عرفت الّذي صولحتم عليه والّذي جعلتم على 
<lb n="6"/>  أنفسكم من الوفا به فأحرزتم بذلك دماكم وأموالكم إن 
<lb n="7"/>  أنتم وفيتم واللّه تبارك وتعالى يقول في كتابه أوفوا 
<lb n="8"/>  بعهد اللّه إذا عهدتم ولا تنقضوا الإيمان بعد 
<lb n="9"/>  توكيدها وقد جعلتم اللّه عليكم كفيلا إن اللّه 
<lb n="10"/>  يعلم ما تفعلون وقال أوفوا بعهدي أوف بعهدكم 
<lb n="11"/>  وإيّاي فارهبون وقد وفينا لكم بالّذي جعلنا لكم علينا من ا 
<lb n="12"/>  لكف عن دماكم واموالكم وعرڤپ امپكم ڤى 
<lb n="13"/>  وسكونكم حيث أحببتم منها واختلاف تجّاركم إلينا لا يصل 
<lb n="14"/>  إليهم منّا ظلم ولا غشم ولا يعتدى على أحد ممّن قبلنا منكم 
<lb n="15"/>  ولا يمنع من حقّه ولا يحال بين تجّاركم وبين ما أرادوا آمنين 
<lb n="16"/>  مطمأنّين حيث سلكوا من بلادنا وفا بعهدنا وصدقا لقولنا 
<lb n="17"/>  وإيمانا بربّنا وتصديقا لنبيّنا 
<lb n="18"/>  وأنتم فيما بيننا وبينكم على غير ذلك لا تودون إلينا 
<lb n="19"/>  ما عليكم من البقط الّذي صولحتم عليه ولا تردّون من أبق 
<lb n="20"/>  إليكم من أرقّائنا ولا يأمن فيكم تجّارنا ولا تعجّلون تسريح 
<lb n="21"/>  رسلنا إلينا وأنت تعرف أن أهل الأديان كلّها 
<lb n="22"/>  والملل الّذين لا يعرفون ربّا ولا يومپون ببعث ولا يرجون ثوابا 
<lb n="23"/>  ولا يخافون عقابا لا يهجمون تاجرا ولا يحبسون رسولا 
<lb n="24"/>  وأنت تظهر لأهل ملّتك الإيمان بالّذي خلق 
<lb n="25"/>  السّموت والأرض وما بينهما وتومن بعيسى بن مريم وبكتابه 
<lb n="26"/>  وتظهر العدل لهم والعمل بالحق وعملكم فيما بيننا 
<lb n="27"/>  وبينكم مخالف لما تظهر فقد أتاكم تاجر من تجّار أهل 
<lb n="28"/>  بلدنا يقال له سعد قد ذهب بأموال كثيرة زائغا 
<lb n="29"/>  بها من أهلها فحبستموه قبلكم وحلتم بينه وبين من يطلبه بحق 
<lb n="30"/>  ومنعتموه منه وبعث إليكم رجل من أهل أسوان يقال له 
<lb n="31"/>  محمّد بن زيد تاجرا له في تجارته وطلب حقوق له فا 
<lb n="32"/>  حپپسپموه وما كان معه من المال <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ڤكپپ </lem><rdg resp="APD">إلى</rdg></app> الى 
<lb n="33"/>  على أسوان يذكر أنّه كتب إلى خليفتك 
<lb n="34"/>  فيه فكتب إليه خليفتك يسله أن يبعث إليه محمّد 
<lb n="35"/>  بن زيد صاحب ذلك التّاجر ليستخلفه على ما كان معه من 
<lb n="36"/>  المال فبعثه إليه في رهط من المسلمين فضربه ضربا 
<lb n="37"/>  سيّئا وكسر يده وحبسه ثلث ليال عنده حتّى ظن أنّه قاتله 
<lb n="38"/>  ثم خلّى سبيله فدعاه سلم بن سليمن عاملي على أسوان بالبيّنة 
<lb n="39"/>  على وصول تاجره إليكم وعلى ما صنع به خليفتك 
<lb n="40"/>  فأتاه برهط من المسلمين عدول من سكّان أسوان فشهدوا 
<lb n="41"/>  له بما ذكر من أمره وأمر تاجره وكتب إلي بذلك كلّه 
<lb n="42"/>  وبعث إلي محمّد بن زيد صاحب ذلك التّاجر فوافى 
<lb n="43"/>  قدوم بطرة رسولك إلينا فجمعت بينهما ومع بطرة 
<lb n="44"/>  رهط من أهل ملّتك فذكروا أنّهم 
<lb n="45"/>  ظنّوا حين أخذوه أنّه ممّن كان يغير عليهم من البجة 
<lb n="46"/>  فأمرت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">غوث </lem><rdg resp="Plumley, cf. transl.">عون</rdg></app> بن سليمن قاضي أهل مصر أن ينظر في أمرهم 
<lb n="47"/>  ثم تحمّلتم على مثل ما تحمّل عليه النّاس من الحق والعدل 
<lb n="48"/>  فقضى على بطرة أن يرد ذلك التّاجر وما كان معه من 
<lb n="49"/>  المال إن كان حيّا وإن كان قد قتل فعليكم ديته 
<lb n="50"/>  ألف دينر 
<lb n="51"/>  وبعث إليكم سلم رسولا له منذ تسعة أشهر ورسولا منذ أربعة 
<lb n="52"/>  أشهر فحبستموهم معما عندكم من أرقّا أهل الإسلم 
<lb n="53"/>  وأهل ذمّتنا وما عليكم من البقط فإنّه قد ذكر 
<lb n="54"/>  لي أن عليكم بقط سنين لم تودوه وما بعثتم به من البقط 
<lb n="55"/>  بعثتم بما لا خير فيه بين أعور أو أعرج أو كبير ضعيف 
<lb n="56"/>  أو صبي صغير 
<lb n="57"/>  فانظر فيما كتبت إليك به وعجّل 
<lb n="58"/>  البعثة إلينا بما بقي عليكم من البقط للسّنين الّتي 
<lb n="59"/>  قبلكم ولا تبعث بما لا خير فيه فلا نقبله وابعث 
<lb n="60"/>  إلينا بتاجر محمّد بن زيد وبما كان معه من المال إلّا إن 
<lb n="61"/>  يكون قد قتل فتبعث بألف دينر ديته وبما كان معه 
<lb n="62"/>  من مال وابعث إلينا سعد التّاجر الّذي قبلكم ولا توحر 
<lb n="63"/>  من ذلك شيئا إن كنتم تحبّون أن نفي لكم بعهدنا 
<lb n="64"/>  ونكون على ما كنّا عليه من الاستقامة لكم وعجّل 
<lb n="65"/>  ذلك ولا توحره وإن أنت لم تمتثل رأيت فيما 
<lb n="66"/>  بيني وبينكم رأي إن شا اللّه فإنّي قد أحببت أن أعذر 
<lb n="67"/>  إليكم وأتّخذ الحجّة عليكم والسّلم على أوليا 
<lb n="68"/>  اللّه وأهل طاعته وكتب ميمون يوم الأحد 
<lb n="69"/>  لاثنتي عشرة ليلة بقيت من رجب سنة إحدى وأربعين ومائة 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>min mūsà bni kaʿb:in ʾilà *** ṣāḥibi muqurraẗa wa nūbaẗa salām:un ʿalà 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾawliyāʾi ăl lāhi wa ʾahli ṭāʿati hi *** wa ʾaḥmadu ʾilay himi ăl lāha ăllaḏī 
 <lb n="4"/>lā ʾilāha ʾillā huwa 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾammā baʿdu qad ʿarafta ăllaḏī ṣūliḥtum ʿalay hi wa ăllaḏī ǧaʿaltum ʿalà 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾanfusi kum mina ăl wafāʾi bi hi fa ʾaḥraztum bi ḏālika dimāʾa kum wa ʾamwāla kum ʾin 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾantum wafaytum wa ăl lāhu tabāraka wa taʿālà yaqūlu fī kitābi hi ʾawfū 
 <lb n="8"/>bi ʿahdi ăl lāhi ʾiḏā ʿāhadtum wa lā tanquḍū ăl ʾīmāna baʿda 
 <lb n="9"/>tawkīdi hā wa qad ǧaʿaltumu ăl lāha ʿalay kum kafīl:an ʾinna ăl lāha 
 <lb n="10"/>yaʿlamu mā tafʿalūna wa qāla ʾawfū bi ʿahd ī ʾūfu bi ʿahdi kum 
 <lb n="11"/>wa ʾiyyā ya fa ĭrhabū ni wa qad wafaynā la kum bi ăllaḏī ǧaʿalnā la kum ʿalay nā mina ăl kaffi 
 <lb n="12"/>ʿan dimāʾi kum wa ʾamwāli kum wa ʿarafta ʾamna kum fī bilādi nā 
 <lb n="13"/>wa sukūna kum ḥayṯu ʾaḥbabtum min hā wa ĭḫtilāfa tuǧǧāri kum ʾilay nā lā yaṣilu 
 <lb n="14"/>ʾilay him min nā ẓulm:un wa lā ġašm:un wa lā yuʿtadà ʿalà ʾaḥad:in mimman qibala nā min kum 
 <lb n="15"/>wa lā yumnaʿu min ḥaqqi hi wa lā yuḥālu bayna tuǧǧāri kum wa bayna mā ʾarādū ʾāminīna 
 <lb n="16"/>muṭmaʾinnīna ḥayṯu salakū min bilādi nā wafāʾ:an bi ʿahdi nā wa ṣidq:an li qawli nā 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ʾīmān:an bi rabbi nā wa taṣdīq:an li nabiyyi nā 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʾantum fī mā bayna nā wa bayna kum ʿalà ġayri ḏālika lā tuʾaddūna ʾilay nā 
 <lb n="19"/>mā ʿalay kum mina ăl baqṭi ăllaḏī ṣūliḥtum ʿalay hi wa lā taruddūna man ʾabaqa 
 <lb n="20"/>ʾilay kum min ʾariqqāʾi nā wa lā yaʾmanu fī kum tuǧǧāru nā wa lā tuʿaǧǧilūna tasrīḥa 
 <lb n="21"/>rusuli nā ʾilay nā wa ʾanta taʿrifu ʾanna ʾahla ăl ʾadyāni kulli hā 
 <lb n="22"/>wa ăl milali ăllaḏīna lā yaʿrifūna rabb:an wa lā yuʾminūna bi baʿṯ:in wa lā yarǧūna ṯawāb:an 
 <lb n="23"/>wa lā yuḫāfūna ʿiqāb:an lā yahǧumūna tāǧir:an wa lā yaḥbisūna rasūl:an 
 <lb n="24"/>wa ʾanta tuẓhiru li ʾahli millati ka ăl ʾīmāna bi ăllaḏī ḫalaqa 
 <lb n="25"/>ăs samawāti wa ăl ʾarḍa wa mā bayna humā wa tuʾminu bi ʿīsà bni maryama wa bi kitābi hi 
 <lb n="26"/>wa tuẓhiru ăl ʿadla la hum wa ăl ʿamala bi ăl ḥaqqi wa ʿamalu kum fī mā bayna nā 
 <lb n="27"/>wa bayna kum muḫālif:un li mā tuẓhiru fa qad ʾatā kum tāǧir:un min tuǧǧāri ʾahli 
 <lb n="28"/>baladi nā yuqālu la hu saʿd:un qad ḏahaba bi ʾamwāl:in kaṯīraẗ:in zāʾiġ:an 
 <lb n="29"/>bi hā min ʾahli hā fa ḥabastumū hu qibala kum wa ḥultum bayna hu wa bayna man yaṭlubu hu bi ḥaqq:in 
 <lb n="30"/>wa manaʿtumū hu min hu wa baʿaṯa ʾilay kum raǧul:un min ʾahli ʾaswāna yuqālu la hu 
 <lb n="31"/>muḥammadu bnu zayd:in tāǧir:an la hu fī tiǧārati hi wa ṭalaba ḥuqūq la hu fa ĭḥtabastumū hu 
 <lb n="32"/>wa mā kāna maʿa hu mina ăl māli fa kataba ʾilà ʾilay ø ya ʿāmil ī 
 <lb n="33"/>ʿalà ʾaswāna yaḏkuru ʾanna hu kataba ʾilà ḫalīfati ka 
 <lb n="34"/>fī hi fa kataba ʾilay hi ḫalīfatu ka yasalu hu ʾan yabʿuṯa ʾilay hi muḥammada 
 <lb n="35"/>bna zayd:in ṣāḥiba ḏālika ăt tāǧiri li yastaḫlifa hu ʿalà mā kāna maʿa hu mina 
 <lb n="36"/>ăl māli fa baʿaṯa hu ʾilay hi fī rahṭ:in mina ăl muslimīna fa ḍaraba hu ḍarb:an 
 <lb n="37"/>sayyiʾ:an wa kasara yada hu wa ḥabasa hu ṯalāṯa layāl:in ʿinda hu ḥattà ẓanna ʾanna hu qātilu hu 
 <lb n="38"/>ṯumma ḫallà sabīla hu fa daʿā hu salmu bnu sulaymāna ʿāmil ī ʿalà ʾaswāna bi ăl bayyinaẗi 
 <lb n="39"/>ʿalà wuṣūli tāǧiri hi ʾilay kum wa ʿalà mā ṣanaʿa bi hi ḫalīfatu ka 
 <lb n="40"/>fa ʾatā hu bi rahṭ:in mina ăl muslimīna ʿudūl:in min sukkāni ʾaswāna fa šahidū 
 <lb n="41"/>la hu bi mā ḏakara min ʾamri hi wa ʾamri tāǧiri hi wa kataba ʾilay ya bi ḏālika kulli hi 
 <lb n="42"/>wa baʿaṯa ʾilay ya muḥammada bna zayd:in ṣāḥiba ḏālika ăt tāǧiri fa wāfà 
 <lb n="43"/>qudūma baṭraẗa rasūli ka ʾilay nā fa ǧamaʿtu bayna humā wa maʿa baṭraẗa 
 <lb n="44"/>rahṭ:un min ʾahli millati ka fa ḏakarū ʾanna hum 
 <lb n="45"/>ẓannū ḥīna ʾaḫaḏū hu ʾanna hu mimman kāna yuġīru ʿalay him mina ăl buǧaẗa 
 <lb n="46"/>fa ʾamartu ġawṯa ʿawna bna sulaymāna qāḍī ʾahli miṣra ʾan yanẓura fī ʾamri him 
 <lb n="47"/>ṯumma taḥammaltum ʿalà miṯli mā taḥammala ʿalay hi ăn nāsu mina ăl ḥaqqi wa ăl ʿadli 
 <lb n="48"/>fa qaḍà ʿalà baṭraẗa ʾan yarudda ḏālika ăt tāǧira wa mā kāna maʿa hu mina 
 <lb n="49"/>ăl māli ʾin kāna ḥayy:an wa ʾin kāna qad qutila fa ʿalay kum diyatu hu 
 <lb n="50"/>ʾalfu dīnār:in 
 <lb n="51"/>wa baʿaṯa ʾilay kum salm:un rasūl:an la hu munḏu tisʿaẗi ʾašhur:in wa rasūl:an munḏu ʾarbaʿaẗi 
 <lb n="52"/>ʾašhur:in fa ḥabastumū hum maʿa mā ʿinda kum mina ʾariqqāʾi ʾahli ăl ʾislāmi 
 <lb n="53"/>wa ʾahli ḏimmati nā wa mā ʿalay kum mina ăl baqṭi fa ʾinna hu qad ḏakara 
 <lb n="54"/>l ī ʾanna ʿalay kum baqṭa sinīna lam tuʾaddū hu wa mā baʿaṯtum bi hi mina ăl baqṭi 
 <lb n="55"/>baʿaṯtum bi mā lā ḫayra fī hi bayna ʾaʿwara ʾaw ʾaʿraǧa ʾaw kabīr:in ḍaʿīf:in 
 <lb n="56"/>ʾaw ṣabiyy:in ṣaġīr:in 
 <lb n="57"/>fa ŭnẓur fī mā katabtu ʾilay ka bi hi wa ʿaǧǧil 
 <lb n="58"/>ăl baʿṯaẗa ʾilay nā bi mā baqiya ʿalay kum mina ăl baqṭi li s sinīna ăllatī 
 <lb n="59"/>qibala kum wa lā tabʿuṯ bi mā lā ḫayra fī hi fa lā naqbalu hu wa ŭbʿuṯ 
 <lb n="60"/>ʾilay nā bi tāǧiri muḥammadi bni zayd:in wa bi mā kāna maʿa hu mina ăl māli ʾillā ʾin 
 <lb n="61"/>yakūna qad qutila fa tabʿuṯa bi ʾalfi dīnār:in diyata hu wa bi mā kāna maʿa hu 
 <lb n="62"/>min māl:in wa ŭbʿuṯ ʾilay nā saʿd:ana ăt tāǧira ăllaḏī qibala kum wa lā tuʾaḫḫir 
 <lb n="63"/>min ḏālika šayʾ:an ʾin kuntum tuḥibbūna ʾan nafiya la kum bi ʿahdi nā 
 <lb n="64"/>wa nakūna ʿalà mā kunnā ʿalay hi mina ăli ĭstiqāmaẗi la kum wa ʿaǧǧil 
 <lb n="65"/>ḏālika wa lā tuʾaḫḫir hu wa ʾin ʾanta lam tamtaṯil raʾaytu fī mā 
 <lb n="66"/>bayn ī wa bayna kum raʾy ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu fa ʾin nī qad ʾaḥbabtu ʾan ʾaʿḏira 
 <lb n="67"/>ʾilay kum wa ʾattaḫiḏa ăl ḥuǧǧaẗa ʿalay kum wa ăs salāmu ʿalà ʾawliyāʾi 
 <lb n="68"/>ăl lāhi wa ʾahli ṭāʿati hi wa kataba maymūn:un yawma ăl ʾaḥadi 
 <lb n="69"/>li ĭṯnatay ʿašraẗa laylaẗ:an baqiyat min raǧabi sanaẗi ʾiḥdà wa ʾarbaʿīna wa miʾaẗ:in 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the Compassionate, the Merciful
			<lb n="2"/>
		From Mūsa b. K[aʿb to] ... ... master (ṣāḥib) of Muqurr[a] and Nubia. Peace be upon
		From Mūsā b. K[aʿb to] ... ... master of Muqurr&lt;a&gt; and Nubia. Peace be upon
			<lb n="3"/>
		the friends (awliyāʾ) of God and those who obey him... To them do I praise God,
		the friends of God and those who obey Him.... To them do I praise God,
			<lb n="4"/>
		other than whom there is no God.
			<lb n="5"/>
		To continue. You (sing.) know about which an agreement was made with you and the fulfilment of it
		To continue. You (sing.) know that on the basis of which a peace agreement was made with you and that which you took
			<lb n="6"/>
		upon yourselves to fulfil, so preserving your blood and property if
		which you took upon yourselves, so preserving your blood and property if
			<lb n="7"/>
		you fulfil [it]. God, blessed and exalted is He, says in His book &#034;Fulfil
			<lb n="8"/>
		the compact of God when you make a compact, and do not break the oath after
			<lb n="9"/>
		it has been affirmed and you have made God your guarantor; verily God
			<lb n="10"/>
		knows what you do.&#034; And He said &#034;Fulfil my compact and I shall fulfil your compact;
		knows what you do.&#034; And He said &#034;Fulfil my compact and I shall fulfil your compact and mine;
			<lb n="11"/>
		so fear me.&#034; We have fulfilled for you that which we took upon ourselves for you in
			<lb n="12"/>
		desisting from your blood and your property and you (sing.) know your security in our land
		turning away from your blood and your property and you (sing.) know your security in our land
			<lb n="13"/>
		and your dwelling wherever you wish in it and the repairing of your merchants to us, no oppression
			<lb n="14"/>
		or harm comes to them from us; no one of you who is among us is attacked by us
		or wrong comes to them from us; no one of you who is among us is attacked by us
			<lb n="15"/>
		nor is he denied his right; no obstacle is placed between your merchants and what they want - [they are] safe
			<lb n="16"/>
		and at ease wherever they go in our land, [this being] in fulfillment of our compact, in truth to our word
		and contented wherever they go in our land, [this being] in fulfillment of our compact, in truth to our word
			<lb n="17"/>
		in belief in our Lord and in trust in our Prophet.
		in belief in our Lord and in verification of our Prophet.
			<lb n="18"/>
		You however, in that which lies between us, behave otherwise. You do not bring to us
		You however, in that which lies between us, behave otherwise. You do not hand over to us
			<lb n="19"/>
		that to which you are liable according to the baqṭ on the basis of which / about which agreement was made with you; nor do you return those of our
		what you owe of the baqṭ about which a peace agreement was made with you; nor do you return those of our
			<lb n="20"/>
		slaves who run away to you; nor are our merchants safe among you; nor do you hasten to permit
		slaves who run away to you; nor are our merchants safe among you; nor do you hasten to send
			<lb n="21"/>
		our emissaries [back] to us. You know that the people of all religions
		our messengers [to return] to us. You know that the people of all religions
			<lb n="22"/>
		and the confessions which neither know a lord, nor believe in a resurrection, nor hope for recompense,
		and the persuasions (milal) which neither know a lord, nor believe in a resurrection, nor hope for recompense,
			<lb n="23"/>
		nor fear punishment, [even these] do not attack a merchant or detain a messenger.
		nor fear punishment, [even these] do not attack a merchant or detain an emissary.
			<lb n="24"/>
		You (sing.) make manifest to the people of your confession belief in Him who created
		You (sing.) make manifest to the people of your persuasion belief in Him who created
			<lb n="25"/>
		the heavens and the earth and what is between them, you (sing.) believe in Jesus the son of Mary and his book,
			<lb n="26"/>
		and you (sing.) make manifest to them justice and the doing of what is right, while what you do in that which is between you
		and you (sing.) make manifest to them justice and the doing of what is right, while what you do in that which lies between you
			<lb n="27"/>
		and us is contrary to that which you make manifest. One of the merchants of the people
			<lb n="28"/>
		of our country, Saʿd by name, came to you with much wealth, having made off
			<lb n="29"/>
		with it from its owners, and you detained him among you, stood between him and the one who rightly pursued him
			<lb n="30"/>
		and protected him from him. [Secondly] a man of the people of Aswān, named
			<lb n="31"/>
		Muḥammad b. Zayd, sent to you a merchant of his, on his business and seeking rights for him.
			<lb n="32"/>
		You detained him and the wealth that he had with him, and my governor over Aswān
			<lb n="33"/>
		wrote to me, mentioning that he had written to your deputy
			<lb n="34"/>
		concerning him and that your deputy had written to him, asking him to send to him Muḥammad
			<lb n="35"/>
		b. Zayd, the master of that merchant, so that he might make over to him with the wealth which he (the merchant) had
			<lb n="36"/>
		with him. So he (the governor) sent him (Muḥammad) to him (the deputy) with a group of Muslims, and he (the deputy) gave him (Muḥammad) a bad
			<lb n="37"/>
		beating and broke his hand and detained him for three nights until he (Muḥammad) thought that he would kill him.
			<lb n="38"/>
		Then he (the deputy) let him go, and my governor over Aswān, Salm b. Sulaymān, asked him (Muḥammad) for evidence
			<lb n="39"/>
		of the arrival of his merchant to you and of that which your deputy had done to him.
			<lb n="40"/>
		He (Muḥammad) then brought to him a group of Muslims, persons of good morals from the inhabitants of Aswān, and they bore witness
		He (Muḥammad) then brought to him a group of Muslims, witnesses of probity (ʿudūl), from the inhabitants of Aswān, and they bore witness
			<lb n="41"/>
		for him of what he had mentioned in the matter of himself and the matter of his merchant. He (Salm) then wrote to me about all of this
		to him (Salm) of what he (Muḥammad) had mentioned in the matter of himself and the matter of his merchant. He (Salm) then wrote to me about all of this
			<lb n="42"/>
		and sent to me Muḥammad b. Zayd, the master of that merchant. He came at the time of the
			<lb n="43"/>
		arrival of BṬRH (Peter), your emissary to me, so I brought them together. With Peter
		arrival of BṬRH (Peter), your messenger to me, so I brought them together. With Peter
			<lb n="44"/>
		[was] a group of your confession and they mentioned
		[was] a group of your persuasion, and they mentioned
			<lb n="45"/>
		that they thought, when they took him (the merchant), that he was one of the Beǧa who make attacks on them.
		that they thought, when they took him (the merchant), that he was one of the Beja who make attacks on them.
			<lb n="46"/>
		I then instructed ʿAwn b. Sulaymān, qāḍī of the people of Miṣr, to look into their affair;
		I then instructed Ğawṯ b. Sulaymān, qāḍī of the people of Miṣr, to look into their affair;
			<lb n="47"/>
		then were you made to bear the like of the right and justice which the people (al-nās, i.e. Muslims?) are made to bear,
		then were you made to bear the like of the right and justice which the people (scil. of Egypt) are made to bear.
			<lb n="48"/>
		for he judged that Peter should return that merchant, together with the wealth that is
		He judged that Peter should return that merchant, together with the wealth that is
			<lb n="49"/>
		with him, if he is alive, and if he has been killed you are liable to blood money of
		with him, if he is alive, and if is dead, you are liable to blood money of
			<lb n="50"/>
		one thousand dinars.
			<lb n="51"/>
		Salm sent to you a messenger of his nine months ago, and a messenger four months
		Salm sent to you an emissary of his nine months ago, and an emissary four months
			<lb n="52"/>
		ago, and you detained them, together with those slaves of the people of Islam and of the people
			<lb n="53"/>
		protected by us who are with you, and that of the baqṭ to which you are liable. For he (Salm) mentioned to me
		protected by us who are with you, as well [being liable to] that to which you are liable in the baqṭ. It has been mentioned to me / He (Salm) mentioned to me
			<lb n="54"/>
		that you are liable to the baqṭ of [outstanding] years, which you have not made over ; [that, in respect of] such of the baqṭ as you have sent,
		that you are liable to the baqṭ of [several] years, which you have not fulfilled; as for that which you have sent in accordance with the baqṭ,
			<lb n="55"/>
		you have sent that in which there is no good - the one-eyed, or the lame, or the weak old man,
			<lb n="56"/>
		or the young boy.
			<lb n="57"/>
		So look (sing.) into that about which I have written to you (sing.) and hasten (sing.)
			<lb n="58"/>
		the dispatching to us of that of the baqṭ for which you are still liable for the [outstanding] years, which is
		the dispatching to us of your remaining liability according to the baqṭ for the years for which
			<lb n="59"/>
		with you, and to not send (sing.) that in which there is no good, for we do not accept it; and send (sing.)
		you owe and to not send (sing.) that in which there is no good, for we do not accept it; and send (sing.)
			<lb n="60"/>
		to us the merchant of Muḥammad b. Zayd and the wealth which was with him, unless
			<lb n="61"/>
		he has been killed, in which case send (sing.) the thousand dinars, his blood money, together with
			<lb n="62"/>
		the wealth which was with him; and send (sing.) to us Saʿd the merchant who is among you and be not tardy (sing.)
			<lb n="63"/>
		in that in any respect if you wish us to fulfil for you our compact
			<lb n="64"/>
		and to continue as we did in dealing correctly with you. Hasten (sing.)
			<lb n="65"/>
		that and to not delay (sing.) it. If you (sing.) do not obey, I shall have
			<lb n="66"/>
		my view concerning what is between you and me, God willing. I have wanted to eceed the usual bounds in exhorting you
			<lb n="67"/>
		and to take proof against you. Peace be upon the friends of
			<lb n="68"/>
		God and those who obey him. Written by Maymūn on Sunday,
			<lb n="69"/>
		the twelfth night remaining in Rajab in the year 141.
		twelve nights remaining of Raǧab in the year 141.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
