<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1213" xml:id="Khan_Khurasan_10" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khurasan 10</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khurasan_10</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169051</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا كتاب من شعيب بن علون عامل الأمير عمر بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">غارم </lem><rdg resp="APD">عازم </rdg><rdg resp="APD">غارم</rdg></app> على مدر ورزم براه لمير بن بيك 
<lb n="3"/>  إنّك أدّيت إلي ممّا صار عليك من خراج سنة إحدى وخمسين ومئة وقسمة 
<lb n="4"/>  خراج سنة خمسين ومئة درهم وأربعة دوانيق قبضت ذلك منك 
<lb n="5"/>  پرپپ إلي منها وكتب في ذو القعدة سنة اثنين وخمسين ومئة 
<lb n="seal 1"/>  شعيب 
<lb n="seal 2"/>  بن علوان 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā kitāb:un min šuʿaybi bni ʿalwāna ʿāmili ăl ʾamīri ʿumara bni ʿārim:in ʿāzim:in ġārim:in ʿalà madra wa rizma barāʾaẗ:un li mīri bni bayk:in 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾinna ka ʾaddayta ʾilay ya mimmā ṣāra ʿalay ka min ḫarāǧi sanaẗi ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in wa qismaẗi 
 <lb n="4"/>ḫarāǧi sanaẗi ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in dirham wa ʾarbaʿaẗa dawānīqa qabaḍtu ḏālika min ka 
 <lb n="5"/>wa bariʾta ʾilay ya min hā wa kutiba fī ḏū ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗa ĭṯnayni wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="6"/>šuʿaybu 
 <lb n="7"/>bnu ʿalwāna 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful and Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is a document from Shuʿayb ibn ʿAlwān, the financial administrator of the governor ʿUmar ibn ʿĀrim, (whose jurisdiction is) over Madr and Rizm, a quittance for Mīr ibn Bēk.
			<lb n="3"/>
		You have delivered to me what you owe with regard to the kharāj for the year one hundred and fifty-one and the portion
			<lb n="4"/>
		of the kharāj for the year one hundred and fifty, one dirham and four dānaqs. I have received that from you and
			<lb n="5"/>
		you have been released from (the obligation to pay) them to me. It has been written in Dhū al-Qaʿda of the year one hundred and fifty-two.
			<lb n="6"/>
		Shuʿayb
			<lb n="7"/>
		ibn ʿAlwān
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
