<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1500" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_21" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 21 (= P.Khalili II 38)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_21</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169276</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ابن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أمّ</rdg></app> محمّد إلى آمنة سلم عليّك ورحمته أمّا بعد عافاك اللّه 
 <lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأبـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـقـ</supplied>ـاك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وإيّاك</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وإنّك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فإنّك</rdg></app> أرسلت إلي بأربعة أوصال كتّان جليل ومائة درهم 
 <lb n="4"/>  ورق وأكون إن أخّرني رحيل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الضّاجعة </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الملحفة</rdg></app> وما فضل فاشتري لي 
 <lb n="5"/>  به كتّان وإن النّسّاج لم يستطيع يبقى ينسجها بثمانية أذرع إلّا 
 <lb n="6"/>  بثلثة پصف وإن أحببت عطيتها إيّاك وإن لا فاكتبي 
 <lb n="7"/>  إلي برأيك المحكم وذكري وانظري <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">فيه</unclear> كان 
 <lb n="8"/>  لي على ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> توكّل فأمرته <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">سرّرته</unclear> حتّا حبك مرّتين وإن كان 
 <lb n="9"/>  النّسج الجلّة تصل معه فلترسلي بها وأقري منّي على <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">فليخيم</unclear> 
 <lb n="10"/>  وأبو حـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـسـ</supplied>ـن السّلم وعلى أبو قريل وأهله السّلم 
 <lb n="verso"/>  من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ابن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أمّ</rdg></app> محمّد إلى آمنة ابنت أسد 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>mina ĭbni ʾummi muḥammad:in ʾilà ʾāminaẗa salām:un ʿalay ki wa raḥmatu hu ʾammā baʿdu ʿāfā ki ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ʾabqā ʾiyyā ki wa fa ʾinna ki ʾarsalti ʾilay ya bi ʾarbaʿaẗi ʾawṣāli kattān:in ǧalīl:in wa miʾaẗi dirhami 
 <lb n="4"/>waraq:in wa ʾakūnu ʾin ʾaḫḫara nī raḥīlu ăḍ ăl ḍāǧiʿaẗi milḥafaẗ wa mā faḍala fa ĭštarī l ī 
 <lb n="5"/>bi hi kattān wa ʾinna ăn nassāǧa lam yastaṭīʿ yabqà yansuǧu hā bi ṯamāniyaẗi ʾaḏruʿ:in ʾillā 
 <lb n="6"/>bi ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa niṣf:in wa ʾin ʾaḥbabti ʿāṭaytu hā ʾiyyā ki wa ʾin lā fa ŭktubī 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾilay ya bi raʾyi ki ăl muḥkami wa ḏkurī wa ŭnẓurī fī hi kāna 
 <lb n="8"/>l ī ʿalà ăl lāhi tawakkul:un fa ʾamartu hu sarrartu hu ḥattā ḥabaka marratayni wa ʾin kāna 
 <lb n="9"/>ăn nusuǧu ăl ǧallaẗu taṣilu maʿa hu fa la tursilī bi hā wa ʾaqrī minn ī ʿalà falayḫayma 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ʾabū ḥasan:in ăs salāma wa ʿalà ʾabū qirīla wa ʾahli hi ăs salāmu 
 <lb n="11"/>mina ĭbni ʾummi muḥammad:in ʾilà ʾāminaẗa ø ĭbnati ʾasad:in 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  From Ibn Muḥammad to ʾĀmina. Peace be upon you and his (i.e. God&#039;s) mercy. As for what follows, may God grant you health
 	  From Ibn Muhammad to Aminah. Peace be upon you and His mercy. As for what follows, may God grant you health
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  and preserve you. You have sent me four lengths of thick flax and a 100 waraq
 	  and preserve you, you have sent me four lengths of thick flax and a hundred waraq
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  dirhams. If I am delayed by the conveyance of the sheep, buy some flax for me from what remains.
 	  dirhams. If I am delayed by the conveyance of the sheep, buy some linen for me from what remains.
 	  ... und wenn etwas davon (sc. vom Geld) übrigbleibt, dann kaufe für mich damit
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  The weaver cannot continue weaving in eight cubit (lengths) but (only)
 	  The weaver cannot continue weaving them in eight cubit (lengths) but (only)
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  in (lengths) of three and a half (cubits). If you like I shall give them to you, if not write
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  to me (to let me know) your considered veiw and make a point of looking into the matter.
 	  to me  your considered veiw and make a point of looking into the matter.
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  God was my support and I persuaded him to weave double. If
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  the large textiles arrive with him send them. Give my best wishes to Palēḵēm
 	  the large textiles arrive with him send them. Give my best wishes to Palekhem
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  and to ʾAbū Ḥasan and ʾAbū Qirīl and his family.
 	  and to Abu Hasan and Abu Qiril and his family.
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  From Ibn Muḥammad to ʾĀmina, daughter of ʾAsad.
 	  From Ibn Muhammad to Aminah bint Asad
 	  ... ʾUmm Muḥammad...
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
