<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1540" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_33" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 33 (= P.Khalili II 65)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_33</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169311</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أطال اللّه بقاكما وأدام عزّكما وكرامتكما وأتم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أنعمه </lem><rdg resp="Diem">نعمته</rdg></app> عليكم وزاد <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إحسانه</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  إليكم في الدّنيا والآخرة برحمة أعلمكم أنّي لم أقرأ لكم كتاب من أيّام فغمّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـني</supplied> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـم </lem><rdg resp="Khan textual notes">ذلك</rdg></app> 
<lb n="4"/>  فأسل اللّه أن يجمع بيننا وبينكم في عافية إنّه على ذلك قدير وبعد أكرمكم اللّه إنّما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أبطـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـلت</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أبطأت</rdg></app> 
<lb n="5"/>  كتابي عنكم من كثـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـر</supplied>ة الشّغل <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">فـ</supplied>ـأسل <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ا</supplied>للّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الرّجوع </lem><rdg resp="Diem">العود</rdg></app> في عافية فأحب أن تكتبي إلي بخبرك 
<lb n="6"/>  وخبر راصة أبقاه اللّه وخبر أمّك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأخبرو </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأخيك</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">خبر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وخبر</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أمين </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أمّي</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="bāʾ with two dots below, maybe representing kasra “Khan textual notes” 	">وأخبرو </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأخي</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">خبر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وخبر</rdg></app> عبّاس أبقاه 
<lb n="7"/>  اللّه وقد اشتريت لكم منديل واحد ولم أصب إلّا واحد واكتبي إلي بخبرك وحالك 
<lb n="8"/>  فإنّي أسر بذلك إن شا اللّه وإنّما أغيب عنكم مقدار شهر وهو آخر طوبة فـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـأسل</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> 
<lb n="9"/>  أن يجمع بيننا وبينكم في عافية إن شا اللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حضر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">خصّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ثوبكم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">نفسك</rdg></app> بالسّلام وعلى راصة أبقاه 
<lb n="10"/>  اللّه السّلام وعلى أمّك وأختك وعبّاس السّلام كثيرا واكتبي إلي بخبر صاحب البيت اليهود<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يّ</supplied> 
<lb n="address verso 1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">المصري </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الصّيرف</rdg></app> إلى منزله يدفع إلى أبوا خير من بقام الملّاح 
<lb n="address verso 2"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> يدفع إلى <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> الحسن بلّغ رحمك اللّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa kumā wa ʾadāma ʿizza kumā wa karāmata kumā wa ʾatamma ʾanʿuma niʿmaẗa hu ʿalay kum wa zāda fī ʾiḥsāni hi 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾilay kum fī ăd dunyā wa ăl ʾāḫiraẗi bi raḥmaẗ:in ʾuʿlimu kum ʾan nī lam ʾaqraʾ la kum kitāb min ʾayyām:in fa ġamma nī *** ḏālika **m ġamm 
 <lb n="4"/>fa ʾasalu ăl lāha ʾan yaǧmaʿa bayna nā wa bayna kum fī ʿāfiyaẗ:in ʾinna hu ʿalà ḏālika qadīr:un wa baʿdu ʾakrama kumu ăl lāhu ʾinnamā ʾabṭaltu ʾabṭaʾtu 
 <lb n="5"/>kitāb ī ʿan kum min kaṯraẗi ăš šuġli fa ʾasalu ăl lāha ăr ruǧūʿa ʿawda fī ʿāfiyaẗ:in fa ʾuḥibbu ʾan taktubī ʾilay ya bi ḫabari ki 
 <lb n="6"/>wa ḫabari rāṣaẗa ʾabqā hu ăl lāhu wa ḫabari ʾummi ki wa ʾaḫbirū ʾaḫī ø ki ø wa ḫabara ḫabari ʾamīn:in ʾumm ø ī wa ʾaḫbirū ʾaḫ ø ī ø wa ḫabara ḫabari ʿabbās:in ʾabqā hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl lāhu wa qadi ĭštaraytu la kum mindīl wāḥid wa lam ʾuṣib ʾillā wāḥid wa ŭktubī ʾilay ya bi ḫabari ki wa ḥāli ki 
 <lb n="8"/>fa ʾin nī ʾusarru bi ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu wa ʾinnamā ʾaġību ʿan kum miqdāra šahr:in wa huwa ʾāḫiru ṭūbaẗa fa ʾasalu ăl lāha 
 <lb n="9"/>ʾan yaǧmaʿa bayna nā wa bayna kum fī ʿāfiyaẗ:in ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu ḥaḍara ḫuṣṣa ṯawbu nafsa kum ka bi ăs salāmi wa ʿalà rāṣaẗa ʾabqā hu 
 <lb n="10"/>ăl lāhu ăs salāmu wa ʿalà ʾummi ki wa ʾuḫti ki wa ʿabbās:in ăs salāmu kaṯīr:an wa ŭktubī ʾilay ya bi ḫabari ṣāḥibi ăl bayti ăl yahūdiyyi 
 <lb n="11"/>*** ăl miṣriyyi ṣayraf ʾilà manzili hi yudfaʿu ʾilà ʾabū ḫayr:in min baqama ăl mallāḥi 
 <lb n="12"/>*** *** yudfaʿu ʾilà *** ăl ḥasani balliġ raḥima ka ăl lāhu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		May God prolong your life, preserve your strength and nobility, give a full measure of his bounty and increase his goodness
			<lb n="3"/>
		to you in this world and the next, with mercy! (I am writing to) let you know that I have not read a letter of yours for days and... worried me,
		to you in this world and the next, with mercy. (I am writing to) let you know that I have not read a letter of yours for days and [...] worried me,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and I pray to God that he will bring us together in good health. He has the power to do that. As for what follows - may God show you kindness - I ceased
		and I pray to God that he will bring us together in good health. He has the power to do that. As for what follows - may God show you kindness! - I ceased
			<lb n="5"/>
		writing to you due to my many preoccupations. I pray to God that (I shall) return in good health. I should like you to write to me (and tell me) your news,
			<lb n="6"/>
		the news of Rāṣe - may God preserve him - and the news of your mother. Give ma also news of ʾAmīn and ʿAbbās - may God preserve him.
		the news of Raseh - may God preserve him! - and the news of your mother. Give ma also news of Amin and ʿAbbas - may God preserve him!
			<lb n="7"/>
		I have bought a kerchief for you. I acquired only one. Write to me (to tell me) your news and how you are,
		I have bought for you one kerchief. I acquired only one. Write to me (to tell me) your news and how you are
			<lb n="8"/>
		for I shall be given pleasure by that, God willing. I shall only be away from you for a month, that is (to) the end of Tubah. [I pray to God]
		for I shall be given pleasure by that, God willing. I shall only be away from you for a month, that is (to) the end of Ṭūba. [I pray to God]
			<lb n="9"/>
		... Laß Dich ganz speziell grüßen!...
		that he will bring us together in health. God willing, your garment will have arrived safely. Give my best wishes to Rāṣe - may God preserve him -
		that He will bring us together in health. God willing, your garment will have arrived safely. Give my best wishes to Raseh - may God preserve him! -
			<lb n="10"/>
		and my very best wishes to your mother, your sister and ʿAbbas. Write to me (and tell me) the news of the Jewish landlord.
		and my very best wishes to your mother, your sister and ʿAbbās. Write to me (and tell me) the news of the Jewish landlord.
			<lb n="11"/>
		[...] the Egyptian to his house, let it be delivered to ʾAbū Khayr from Baqām the sailor.
		... to Abu Khayr from Baqam the Sailor...
			<lb n="12"/>
		[...] let it be delivered to... al-Ḥasan, convey the message &#039;may God have mercy upon you.&#039;
		... Liefere (den Brief beim Empfänger) ab - Gott erbarme sich Deiner!
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
