<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1533" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_29" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 29 (= P.Khalili II 72)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_29</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169304</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  صبّحك اللّه يأخي بعافية وكرامة قد فهمت 
<lb n="3"/>  كتابك وما ذكرت من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أمر</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الخمار </lem><rdg resp="Khan÷ variant reading of the personal name, Diem÷ donkey">الحمار </rdg><rdg resp="APD">الخمّار </rdg><rdg resp="APD">الخمار</rdg></app> وأنت من أعذر النّاس 
<lb n="4"/>  عندي وأنا أعلم أن لو قام لك سبيل تسبق رسولي 
<lb n="5"/>  وأمّا قولك في أن أم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">شعيث </lem><rdg resp="APD">شعيث</rdg></app> ذهبت إلى الفاسقة 
<lb n="6"/>  ولا ذكرته لي ولا علمت حتّا أتاني كتابك 
<lb n="7"/>  فزعمت لي أنّها ذهبت إلى منزل بنت أختي فلمّا 
<lb n="8"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وصّت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">رجعت</rdg></app> رأت بنتها على قارعة الطّريق فقالت 
<lb n="9"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">هـ</supplied>ـا هو <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ذا</unclear> منزلكم قالت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فقد </lem><rdg resp="Diem ≤tooth, loop visible above a hole±">نعم</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">حلّت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فدخلت</rdg></app> بقلب 
<lb n="10"/>  الّبيت حتّا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تقلّب </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تقلّب</rdg></app> ابنتها ولم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تذكر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تذكر</rdg></app> لي <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">شي</unclear> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حتّـ</supplied>ـا أتاـني 
<lb n="11"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كتـ</supplied>ـابك وذكرت <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> ولا من خبر 
<lb n="12"/>  وأنا إذا رجـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـعـ</supplied>ـت لبيتك مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>ك 
<lb n="13"/>  وذكرت لي وشرحت أن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">أكري</unclear> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="14"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> وكتابك 
<lb n="15"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> و<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> فأنا أرجو أن يصنع اللّه نعمته بك منه 
<lb n="16"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> قدوم أخي فأنا أرجع من السّاحل وأنزل 
<lb n="17"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ṣabbaḥa ka ăl lāhu yā ʾaḫ ī bi ʿāfiyaẗ:in wa karāmaẗ:in qad fahimtu 
 <lb n="3"/>kitāba ka wa mā ḏakarta min ʾummi ʾamri ăl ḥammāri ḫammāri ḥimāri ḫimāri wa ʾanta min ʾaʿḏari ăn nāsi 
 <lb n="4"/>ʿind ī wa ʾanā ʾaʿlamu ʾan law qāma la ka sabīl:un tasbiqu rasūl ī 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ʾammā qawlu ka fī ʾanna ʾumma šuʿayb:in šuʿayṯ:in ḏahabat ʾilà ăl fāsiqaẗi 
 <lb n="6"/>wa lā ḏakarat ḏakarta hu l ī wa lā ʿalimtu ḥattā ʾatā nī kitābu ka 
 <lb n="7"/>fa zaʿamat zaʿamta l ī ʾanna hā ḏahabat ʾilà manzili binti ʾuḫt ī fa lammā 
 <lb n="8"/>waṣṣat raǧaʿat raʾat binta hā ʿalà qāriʿaẗi ăṭ ṭarīqi fa qālat 
 <lb n="9"/>hā huwa ḏā manzilu kum qālat fa naʿam qad ø ø fa ḥallat daḫalat bi qalbi 
 <lb n="10"/>ăl bayti ḥattā naqalati tuqalliba ĭbnata ĭbnatu hā wa lam taḏkur yuḏkar l ī sāyʾ šayʾ:un ḥattā ʾatā nī 
 <lb n="11"/>kitābu ka wa ḏakarta *** *** wa lā min ḫabar:in 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ʾanā ʾiḏā raǧaʿtu li bayti ka m***k 
 <lb n="13"/>wa ḏakarta l ī wa šaraḥta ʾan ʾukriya *** 
 <lb n="14"/>*** *** wa kitāb ka 
 <lb n="15"/>*** *** wa *** fa ʾanā ʾarǧū ʾan yaṣnaʿa ăl lāhu niʿmata hu bi ka min hu 
 <lb n="16"/>*** *** qudūm ʾaḫ ī fa ʾanā ʾarǧiʿu min ăs sāḥili wa ʾanzilu 
 <lb n="17"/>*** 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		... Ich habe
		May God grant you good health and show you kindness this morning! I have taken note of
		May God grant you good health and show you kindness this morning. I have taken note of
			<lb n="3"/>
		Deinen Brief und die Sache mit dem Esel, die du erwähnst, gelesen. Du bist jemand, den ich am allerehesten entschuldige.
		your letter and what you said concerning ʾUmm al-Ḥammār. You are one of my most supportive companions.
		your letter and what you said concerning Umm al-Hammar. You are one of my most supportive companions.
			<lb n="4"/>
		... Denn ich weiß ja, daß Du, wenn es Dir möglich wäre, meinem Boten noch zuvorkämst.
		I know that if you had the opportunity you would outstrip my messenger.
		I know that if you had the opportunity, you would outstrip my messenger.
			<lb n="5"/>
		As for your telling me that Umm Shuʿayb has gone to the sinful woman
		As for your telling me that ʾUmm Šuʿayb has gone to the sinful woman
		Was Deinen Hinweis betrifft, daß ʾUmm Šuʿayb zu dem sündhaften Weib gegangen sei
			<lb n="6"/>
		- sie hatte es mir nicht mitgeteilt und ich wusste es nicht, bis mich Dein Brief erreichte - ,
		- you did not mention it (previously) and I did not know about it until I received your letter
		- you had not mentioned it (previously)، and I did not know about it until I received your letter،
			<lb n="7"/>
		and you told me that she had gone to the house of the daughter of my sister. When
		so hat sie mir gegenüber (auf meine Frage hin) erklärt, sie sei...
			<lb n="8"/>
		she looked she saw her daughter in the middle of the road. She said
		she looked, she saw her daughter in the middle of the road. She said,
		she returned, she (accidentally) saw her daughter in the middle of the road, and she (the mother?) said 
			<lb n="9"/>
		&#034;Here is your home.&#034; She said (this), and she lived in
		Here is your home. She said (this) and she lived in
		So, this is your home (now)? She (the daughter?) said yes, and then (the mother) entered into
			<lb n="10"/>
		the house in order to examine (the state of) her daughter. And she did not tell me anything until your letter reached me.
		the house until her daughter moved. None of this was mentioned to me until your letter came
			<lb n="11"/>
		and you mentioned [...] nor any news.
		and you mentioned ... nor any (other) news.
			<lb n="12"/>
		When I return to your house. [...].
			<lb n="13"/>
		you related and explained to me that... [...]
			<lb n="14"/>
		[...] and your letter
			<lb n="15"/>
		[...] ... and I hope that God will bestow his bounty upon you
			<lb n="16"/>
		[...] ... the arrival of my brother and I shall return from the coast and alight
			<lb n="17"/>
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
