<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1289" xml:id="Khan_Development_1" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.KhanPetitions 1</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Development_1</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169112</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أصلح اللّه الأمير وأطال بقاه 
<lb n="3"/>  ومد لي في عمره 
<lb n="4"/>  أعلم الأمير أبقاه اللّه بقا في 
<lb n="5"/>  عافية إنّي من مولي الشّيخ رحمت 
<lb n="6"/>  اللّه عليه منذ يوم عتّقني عتّقه 
<lb n="7"/>  اللّه من النّار عرض علي في الوكالة 
<lb n="8"/>  وغير ذاك فـأبنت عليه 
<lb n="9"/>  فـإن را الأمير أبقاه اللّه أن يصلني بما 
<lb n="10"/>  يوجّه به إلي مغلّة وأجنّب <sic n="superfluous">پڤصه</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">نقيصة</supplied> عند 
<lb n="11"/>  عيالي فـإن علي خمسة من العيال فـإن 
<lb n="12"/>  را الأمير أبقاه اللّه أن يصلني بما 
<lb n="13"/>  يثيبه اللّه به الجنّة فليفعل فإنّي أدعوا 
<lb n="14"/>  لك عند القبر والمنبر وعند البيت 
<lb n="15"/>  بالبقا لك لرغبة فإنّي حاج على قدمي 
<lb n="16"/>  وقد خرجت على قدمي مرّتين فذالك 
<lb n="17"/>  من اللّه ومن أبيك رحمت اللّه عليه 
<lb n="18"/>  أبقا اللّه الأمير ومد في عمره 
<lb n="19"/>  ولا أخلا مكانه وكـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـبـ</supplied>ـت أعداه 
<lb n="20"/>  وجمع له خير الدّنيا والآخرة برحمته 
<lb n="21"/>  ولوّحه اللّه من جور القبر فإنّي نازل 
<lb n="22"/>  عند ذالك العبّاس فهو مأنك 
<lb n="23"/>  سمپى وقاد النّوى فـإن كل ما 
<lb n="24"/>  دخل عندك رجل مكسه فإنّك 
<lb n="25"/>  تضعه في موضع آخر 
<lb n="26"/>  أبقا اللّه الأمير <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـرحمته 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaṣlaḥa ăl lāhu ăl ʾamīra wa ʾaṭāla baqāʾa hu 
 <lb n="3"/>wa madda l ī fī ʿumri hi 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾuʿlimu ăl ʾamīra ʾabqā hu ăl lāhu baqāʾ:an fī 
 <lb n="5"/>ʿāfiyaẗ:in ʾin nī min mawālī ăš šayḫi raḥmatu 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl lāhi ʿalay hi munḏu yawmi ʿattaqa nī ʿattaqa hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl lāhu mina ăn nāri ʿaraḍa ʿalay ya fī ăl wakālaẗi 
 <lb n="8"/>wa ġayri ḏāka fa ʾabantu ʿalay hi 
 <lb n="9"/>fa ʾin rā ăl ʾamīru ʾabqā hu ăl lāhu ʾan yaṣila nī bi mā 
 <lb n="10"/>yuwaǧǧihu bi hi ʾilay ya muġallaẗ:an wa ʾuǧanniba naqīṣaẗ:an ʿinda 
 <lb n="11"/>ʿiyāl ī fa ʾinna ʿalay ya ḫamsaẗ:un mina ăl ʿiyāli fa ʾin 
 <lb n="12"/>rā ăl ʾamīru ʾabqā hu ăl lāhu ʾan yaṣila nī bi mā 
 <lb n="13"/>yuṯību hu ăl lāhu bi hi ăl ǧannaẗa fa li yafʿal fa ʾin nī ʾadʿū 
 <lb n="14"/>la ka ʿinda ăl qabri wa ăl minbari wa ʿinda ăl bayti 
 <lb n="15"/>bi ăl baqāʾi la ka li raġbaẗ:in fa ʾin nī ḥāǧǧ:un ʿalà qadam ī 
 <lb n="16"/>wa qad ḫaraǧtu ʿalà qadam ī marratayni fa ḏālika 
 <lb n="17"/>mina ăl lāhi wa min ʾabī ka raḥmatu ăl lāhi ʿalay hi 
 <lb n="18"/>ʾabqā ăl lāhu ăl ʾamīra wa madda fī ʿumri hi 
 <lb n="19"/>wa lā ʾaḫlā makāna hu wa kabata ʾaʿdāʾa hu 
 <lb n="20"/>wa ǧamaʿa la hu ḫayra ăd dunyā wa ăl ʾāḫiraẗi bi raḥmati hi 
 <lb n="21"/>wa lawwaḥa hu ăl lāhu min ǧawri ăl qabri fa ʾin nī nāzil:un 
 <lb n="22"/>ʿinda ḏālika ăl ʿabbāsi fa huwa maʾʾānu ka 
 <lb n="23"/>sāma nī wiqāda ăn nawà fa ʾinna kulla mā 
 <lb n="24"/>daḫala ʿinda ka raǧul:un makasa hu fa ʾinna ka 
 <lb n="25"/>taḍaʿu hu fī mawḍiʿ:in ʾāḫara 
 <lb n="26"/>ʾabqā ăl lāhu ăl ʾamīra bi raḥmati hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		May God cause the amīr to prosper, prolong his existence
			<lb n="3"/>
		and extend his life for me.
			<lb n="4"/>
		I (hereby) inform the amīr, may God preserve him in
			<lb n="5"/>
		health, that I am a freedman of the shaykh, the mercy
			<lb n="6"/>
		of God be upon him. Since the day he freed me - may God
			<lb n="7"/>
		free him from Hell Fire - he was opposed to me regarding my being his representative
			<lb n="8"/>
		and regarding other matters and I testified against him.
			<lb n="9"/>
		If the amīr, may God preserve him, should resolve to give me
			<lb n="10"/>
		some produce and send it to me so that I may avoid a shortage in
			<lb n="11"/>
		my family, for I have five children who depend on me - if
			<lb n="12"/>
		the amīr should resolve to give me something
			<lb n="13"/>
		for which God will reward him with Paradise, then let him do so. For I shall pray
			<lb n="14"/>
		and supplicate for your preservation at the Tomb and the Minbar and at the Kaʿba,
			<lb n="15"/>
		since I am making the pilgrimage on foot.
			<lb n="16"/>
		I have set out on foot (to make the pilgrimage) twice,
			<lb n="17"/>
		for God and for your father, the mercy of God be upon him.
			<lb n="18"/>
		May God preserve the amīr, extend his life,
			<lb n="19"/>
		not leave his place empty, crush his enemies,
			<lb n="20"/>
		and join for him the good of this life with that of the Hereafter in His mercy,
			<lb n="21"/>
		and may God guard him from the injustice of the grave. When I alighted
			<lb n="22"/>
		at the place of that ʿAbbās, your purveyor, he
			<lb n="23"/>
		asked from me an excessive price for the fuel of date stones. Every time
			<lb n="24"/>
		a man goes to him he cheats him in a sale. You
			<lb n="25"/>
		should move him to another place.
			<lb n="26"/>
		May God preserve the amīr in his mercy.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
