<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1221" xml:id="Khan_Khurasan_18" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khurasan 18</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khurasan_18</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169059</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذه براه من نصر بن سليم عامل الأمير النّصر بن 
<lb n="3"/>  سليم أكرمه اللّه على <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">وسبا</unclear> ومدر ورزم 
<lb n="4"/>  للقاروال بن مير إنّك أدّيت إلي ممّا صار 
<lb n="5"/>  عليك في قصر نهر يسكن وغندر من خراج 
<lb n="6"/>  سنة أربعة وخمسين ومائة درهمين ودانقين 
<lb n="7"/>  ومن القسم خمسة دونيق ونصف وقبضت 
<lb n="8"/>  ذلك منك وبرئت إلي منها وكتب في 
<lb n="9"/>  ذو الحجّة سنة خمس وخمسين ومائة 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏihi barāʾaẗ:un min naṣri bni salīm:in ʿāmili ăl ʾamīri ăn naṣri bni 
 <lb n="3"/>salīm:in ʾakrama hu ăl lāhu ʿalà wasbā wa madra wa rizma 
 <lb n="4"/>li ăl qārwāla bni mīr:in ʾinna ka ʾaddayta ʾilay ya mimmā ṣāra 
 <lb n="5"/>ʿalay ka fī qaṣri nahri yaskina wa ġandara min ḫarāǧi 
 <lb n="6"/>sanaẗi ʾarbaʿaẗ:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in dirhamayni wa dānaqayni 
 <lb n="7"/>wa mina ăl qisami ḫamsaẗa dawānīqa wa niṣf wa qabaḍtu 
 <lb n="8"/>ḏālika min ka wa bariʾta ʾilay ya min hā wa kutiba fī 
 <lb n="9"/>ḏū ăl ḥiǧǧaẗi sanaẗa ḫams:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful and Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is a quittance from Naṣr ibn Salīm, the financial administrator of the governor al-Naṣr ibn
			<lb n="3"/>
		Salīm, may God grant him honour, (whose jurisdiction is) over Wasbā (?), Madr and Rizm,
			<lb n="4"/>
		for al-Qārwāl ibn Mīr. You have delivered to me what you
			<lb n="5"/>
		owe in the citadel of the river of Yaskin and Ġandar with regard to the kharāj
			<lb n="6"/>
		for the year one hundred and fifty-four, two dirhams and two dānaqs,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and with regard to the portions, five and a half dānaqs. I have received
			<lb n="8"/>
		that from you and you have been released from (the obligation to pay) them to me. It has been written in
			<lb n="9"/>
		Dhū al-Ḥijja of the year one hundred and fifty-five.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
