<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1214" xml:id="Khan_Khurasan_11" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khurasan 11</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khurasan_11</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169052</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذه براه من بشر بن عمر 
<lb n="3"/>  عامل الأمير غالب أصلحه اللّه على رزم ومدر 
<lb n="4"/>  لمير بن بيك إنّك أدّيت إلي ممّا صار عليك في قصر 
<lb n="5"/>  يسكن وغندر من خراج سنة إحدى وخمسين 
<lb n="6"/>  ومائة خمسة درهم وثلثة دونيق ومن القسمة معها 
<lb n="7"/>  درهم وأربعة دونيق ونصف قبضت 
<lb n="8"/>  ذلك منك وبرئت إلي منها 
<lb n="9"/>  وكتب في رمضان سنة أربع وخمسين ومائة 
<lb n="seal"/>  حسبي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏihi barāʾaẗ:un min bišri bni ʿumara 
 <lb n="3"/>ʿāmili ăl ʾamīri ġālib:in ʾaṣlaḥa hu ăl lāhu ʿalà rizma wa madra 
 <lb n="4"/>li mīri bni bayk:in ʾinna ka ʾaddayta ʾilay ya mimmā ṣāra ʿalay ka fī qaṣri 
 <lb n="5"/>yaskina wa ġandara min ḫarāǧi sanaẗi ʾiḥdà wa ḫamsīna 
 <lb n="6"/>wa miʾaẗ:in ḫamsaẗa darāhima dirham wa ṯalāṯaẗa dawānīqa wa mina ăl qismaẗi maʿa hā 
 <lb n="7"/>dirham wa ʾarbaʿaẗa dawānīqa wa niṣf qabaḍtu 
 <lb n="8"/>ḏālika min ka wa bariʾta ʾilay ya min hā 
 <lb n="9"/>wa kutiba fī ramaḍāna sanaẗa ʾarbaʿ:in wa ḫamsīna wa miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="10"/>ḥasb iya ăl lāhu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful and Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is a quittance from Bishr ibn ʿUmar,
			<lb n="3"/>
		the financial administrator of the governor Ġālib, may God grant him prosperity, (whose jurisdiction is) over Rizm and Madr,
			<lb n="4"/>
		for Mīr ib Bēk. You have delivered to me what you owe in the citadel
			<lb n="5"/>
		of Yaskin and Ġandar with regard to the kharāj for the year one hundred and fifty-one,
			<lb n="6"/>
		five dirhams and three dānaqs, and the portion (administered) with them,
			<lb n="7"/>
		one dirham and four dānaqs and a half. I have received
			<lb n="8"/>
		that from you and you have been released (from the obligation) to pay them to me.
			<lb n="9"/>
		It has been written in Ramaḍān of the year one hundred and fifty-four.
			<lb n="10"/>
		My sufficiency [is God]
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
