<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1499" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_20" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 20 recto (= P.Khalili II 73 recto)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_20</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169275</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">والـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">والسّكنكبين</rdg></app> والورد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">المردا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">المربّا</rdg></app> وذكرت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أمر</rdg></app> الكباش وأن ليس فيها 
 <lb n="2"/>  شي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكيف </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فكيف</rdg></app> تجد الكباش تأكّل ومعها ألف رأس تعتلف 
 <lb n="3"/>  لا أهل القرية وغيرهم فكيف تجدوا فيها خروف سمين والتّبّان 
 <lb n="4"/>  فقد اشترا من أهل القرية أربع مراكب تبن ولا تطلق له منهم شي إلّا 
 <lb n="5"/>  بأ<sic n="superfluous">ا</sic>مري وبـكتابي وقد سألني ذالك وقال قد خرج عمل التّبن وما عندي منه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">خبر </lem><rdg resp="APD">خير</rdg></app> 
 <lb n="6"/>  وقد عرّفتك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وعلّمتك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأعلمتك</rdg></app> أن القمح نافق بأربعين ولو <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تركونا</rdg></app> يكون <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">البغشا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لبعنا</rdg></app> بخمسة 
 <lb n="7"/>  وأربعين <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">والجلبان </lem><rdg resp="APD">والجلبان</rdg></app> بسبعة وعشرين <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ولم</unclear> تعرّفني ما بقي من الأرض 
 <lb n="8"/>  نقيت ولا ما نقي وأنا أعلم أنّك غير مقصّر وقد وصل الجدي 
 <lb n="9"/>  ولم تذكر لي أن الكباش ولدت أم لا قرأت عليكم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أمّي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">منّي</rdg></app> أكثر السّلم 
 <lb n="10"/>  وقد خرج الرّجل إلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">بغداد</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ادفع</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فغمّنا</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">منه</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">شا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">شأنه</rdg></app> اللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أطال</rdg></app> اللّه 
 <lb n="margin"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> بقيراط ونصف وكرهت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أخبر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أن</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أكلّم </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أحبس</rdg></app> الحارس <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">مجرا </lem><rdg resp="Diem÷ assuming if the scribe wrote one alif to much at the next word">عن</rdg></app> النّقل وأنا أوخّه إليكم 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>wa ăl ăs *** sikankabīn wa ăl ward wurd ăl mardāʾ murabbā wa ḏakarta *** ʾamra ăl kibāš kibāši wa ʾan laysa fī hā 
 <lb n="2"/>šayʾ:un wa fa kayfa taǧidu ăl kibāšu taʾakkul wa maʿa hā ʾalfu raʾs:in taʿtalifu 
 <lb n="3"/>lā ʾahlu ăl qaryaẗi wa ġayru hum fa kayfa taǧidū fī hā ḫarūf samīn wa ăt tabbānu 
 <lb n="4"/>fa qad ĭštarā min ʾahli ăl qaryaẗi ʾarbaʿa marākibi tibn:in wa lā tuṭliqa la hu min hum šayʾ ʾillā 
 <lb n="5"/>bi ʾamr ī wa bi kitāb ī wa qad saʾala nī ḏālika wa qāla qad ḫaraǧa ʿamalu ăt tibni wa mā ʿind ī min hu ḫabara ḫayra 
 <lb n="6"/>wa qad ʿarraftu ka wa ʾaʿlamtu ʿallamtu ka ʾanna ăl qamḥa nāfiq:un bi ʾarbaʿīna wa law lam tarakū ø nā yakūn ăl la baġšā biʿnā bi ḫamsaẗ:in 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ʾarbaʿīna wa ăl ǧilbānu ǧilibbānu ǧulabānu ǧulbānu ǧulubbānu bi sabʿaẗ:in wa ʿišrīna wa lam tuʿarrif nī mā baqiya mina ăl ʾarḍi 
 <lb n="8"/>naqiyat wa lā mā naqiya wa ʾanā ʾaʿlamu ʾanna ka ġayru muqaṣṣir:in wa qad waṣala ăl ǧadyu 
 <lb n="9"/>wa lam taḏkur l ī ʾanna ăl kibāša waladat ʾam lā qaraʾat qaraʾtu ʿalay kum ʾumm minn ī ʾakṯara ăs salāmi 
 <lb n="10"/>wa qad ḫaraǧa ăr raǧulu ʾilà *** baġdāda ĭdfaʿ fa ø ġamma ø nā min ø hu ø ʾin ø šāʾa šaʾna ø hu ăl lāhu *** ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="11"/>*** bi qīrāṭ:in wa niṣf:in wa karihtu ʾuḫbiru ʾan ʾukallimu ʾaḥbisa ăl ḥārisa maǧrā ʿani ăn naqli wa ʾanā ʾuwaǧǧihu ʾilay kum 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  ... bays without fetlocks. You mentioned ... the sheep and that there is not a good one among them.
 	  ... the horses without fetlocks. You mentioned... the sheep and that there is not a good one among them.
 	  und das Oxymel (Sauerhonig) und die Rosenkonfitüre...
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  How can the sheep find food when there are thousand of them requiring fodder.
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  The people, both of the village and from outside (cannot find food), so how do you expect to find a fat lamb among them. The straw dealer
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  has bought four boat loads of straw from the people of the village. Do not permit him to buy anything from them except
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  with my written authority. He asked me about this and said that the account for the straw had been sent, but we have no knowledge of it.
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  und wenn man uns gelassen hätte, hätten wir (ihn) für 45 verkaufen können.
 	  We have informed you that the wheat is selling at forty (waybas per dīnār) and if it were not for the rain (it would have sold) at forty five.
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  Vetch (is selling) at twenty seven (waybas per dīnār). You have not let me know what land remains
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  neither the (land which is) cultivable nor (that which is) uncultivable. I know that you are not remiss. The kid has arrived.
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  You did not mention to me whether the sheep have given birth or not. My mother sends you her best wishes.
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  Der (bewußte) Mann ist nach Baġdād abgereist; die Sache mit ihm tat uns leid - Gott [schütze ihn]
 	  The courier has gone out to... God willing...
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  [   ] for a qīrāṭ and a half. I do not wish to speak to the guard informing him about the way of transport. I will send to you...
 	  [   ] for a qīrāṭ and a half. I do not wish to speak to the guard informing him of the course to be taken. I will send to you...
 	  ... Ich wollte den Wächter nicht aufhalten...
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
