<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1291" xml:id="Khan_Development_2" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.KhanPetitions 2</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Development_2</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169114</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحيم</supplied> 
<lb n="2"/>  أطال اللّه بقا الأمير وأدام عزّه و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أثـ</supplied>ـنـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نـ</supplied>ـعمتـه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وجعلني</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">من</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كلّ</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">سو</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  ومكروه فداه أعلم الأمير أعزّپه اللّه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إنّـ</supplied>ـي رجل <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="4"/>  في رجل يقال له الحسن ابن تربي البستباني و<gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> في <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="5"/>  حق كرى سنتين في كل سنة بثمانية الدّنانير وجعل لي غاية <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="6"/>  وهو يدفعني عن حقّي يوم بعد يوم إلى هذا الوقت و<gap reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="7"/>  ولي بذلك البيّنة بهذا الحق الّذي أطالب به فـإن را الأ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مير</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ينظر</supplied> 
<lb n="8"/>  في أمري فإنّه في ذلك مأجور مثابا 
<lb n="9"/>  أطال اللّه <sic n="superfluous">پڤاك</sic> بقا الأمير وأعزّه وأثنا النّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـعمـ</supplied>ـة عـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـليه</supplied> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ăl ʾamīri wa ʾadāma ʿizza hu wa ʾaṯnà niʿmata hu wa ǧaʿala nī min kulli sūʾ:in 
 <lb n="3"/>wa makrūh:in fidāʾa hu ʾuʿlimu ăl ʾamīra ʾaʿazza hu ăl lāhu ʾin nī raǧul:un *** *** 
 <lb n="4"/>fī raǧul:in yuqālu la hu ăl ḥasana ĭbna turabiyy:in ăl bustabāniyya wa **** fī **** 
 <lb n="5"/>ḥaqq kirà sanatayni fī kulli sanaẗ:in bi ṯamāniyaẗi ăd danānīra wa ǧaʿala l ī ġāyaẗ:an *** 
 <lb n="6"/>wa huwa yadfaʿu nī ʿan ḥaqq ī yawm baʿda yawm ʾilà hāḏā ăl waqti wa ***** 
 <lb n="7"/>wa l ī bi ḏālika ăl bayyinaẗu bi hāḏā ăl ḥaqqi ăllaḏī ʾuṭālibu bi hi fa ʾin rā ăl ʾamīru ʾan yanẓura 
 <lb n="8"/>fī ʾamr ī fa ʾinna hu fī ḏālika maʾǧūr:un muṯāb:an 
 <lb n="9"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ăl ʾamīri wa ʾaʿazza hu wa ʾaṯnā ăn niʿmaẗa ʿalay hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		May God prolong the life of the amīr, cause his power to endure, double his bounties and make me his ransom for all evil
			<lb n="3"/>
		and adversity. I (hereby) inform the amīr, may God make him mighty, that I am a man .... [...]
			<lb n="4"/>
		regarding a man called al-Ḥasan ibn Turabī al-Bustabānī and ... [...]
			<lb n="5"/>
		the right of two years rent, at eight dīnārs each year. He fixed a term for me [...]
			<lb n="6"/>
		and he would pay me my due day after day until this time and ... [...]
			<lb n="7"/>
		furthermore I have proof of this due which I am claiming. If the ʾamīr should resolve [to look]
			<lb n="8"/>
		into my case, he will be rewarded and recompensed for it.
			<lb n="9"/>
		May God prolong the life of the amīr, make him mighty and double the bounties (granted) to him.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
