<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1547" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_35" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 35 (= P.Khalili II 87 = P.DiemKhalili 3)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_35</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169318</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أطال اللّه بقاك وأعزّك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وجعلت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وجعلني</rdg></app> فداك 
<lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أعلمني </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أعلمتني</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أنا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أبا</rdg></app> صلح <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فعله </lem><rdg resp="Diem">بعلّة</rdg></app> الصّبي أودع اللّه فيه 
<lb n="4"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ففهمت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فغمّني</rdg></app> ذلك ولا واللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">كپپپ </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ما</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="written above the line">ڤاعلمپ </lem><rdg resp="Diem">كنت</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكپپ </lem><rdg resp="Diem">علمت</rdg></app> على المصى 
<lb n="5"/>  إليك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وشغلني </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فشغلني</rdg></app> حضور جماعة وأنا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أرجـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـوا</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أحبّ</rdg></app> 
<lb n="6"/>  أعزّك اللّه أن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تحضرني </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تعرّفني</rdg></app> خبره وحاله <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فأربعة </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فإن</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مـ</supplied>ـن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تفرّق</rdg></app> 
<lb n="7"/>  أصحابنا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">جرت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">صرت</rdg></app> إليك وقد وجّهت إليك 
<lb n="8"/>  كتاب من بنت لميطس جاريتك 
<lb n="9"/>  فاقرأه إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="10"/>  أطال اللّه بقاك وأعزّك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وجعلت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وجعلني</rdg></app> فداك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾaʿazza ka wa ǧuʿiltu ǧaʿala ø nī fidāʾa ka 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾaʿlama ʾaʿlamta nī ʾabā ʾanā ṣalaḥa ṣāliḥ:in fiʿlu bi hu ʿillaẗi ăṣ ṣabiyyi ṣabiyyu ʾawdaʿa ʾūdiʿu ăl lāha lāhu fī hi 
 <lb n="4"/>fa fahimtu ġamma ø nī ḏālika wa lā wa ăl lāhi ø mā katabta kuntu fa ø ʾaʿlamta ʿalimtu wa kuntu ʿalà ăl muḍiyyi maṣīri 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾilay ka wa fa šaġala nī ḥuḍūru ǧamāʿaẗ:in wa ʾanā ʾarǧū ʾuḥibbu 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾaʿazza ka ăl lāhu ʾan tuḥḍira tuʿarrifa nī ḫabara hu wa ḥāla hu fa ʾarbaʿaẗ:un ʾin min tafarraqa 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾaṣḥābi ʾaṣḥābu nā ǧarat ṣirtu ʾilay ka wa qad waǧǧahtu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="8"/>kitāb min binti lamīṭasa lamiyaṭisa ǧāriyati ka 
 <lb n="9"/>fa ĭqraʾ hu ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾaʿazza ka wa ǧuʿiltu ǧaʿala ø nī fidāʾa ka 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		Im Namen Gottes, des Barmherzigen und Gnädigen!
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		In the name of God، the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		Gott lasse Dich lange leben, stärke Dich und möge mich als Dein Lösegeld geben!
		May God prolong your life and give you strength, and may I be made your ransom!
		May God prolong your life and give you strength, and may I be made your ransom.
			<lb n="3"/>
		Du hast mir mitgeteilt, o Abū Ṣāliḥ, daß der Knabe krank ist - Gott nehme ihn in seine Obhut -
		The youth has informed me - his deed was good, I commend him to God&#039;s (protection) -
		The youth has informed me - I commend him to God&#039;s (protection) for his good deed (literally: the youth informed me - his deed was good, I entrust him to God)
			<lb n="4"/>
		and I noted (literally: understood) that. By God, you did not write to inform (me). I was about to come
		dies hat mir sehr leid getan. Ich hatte (es), bei Gott, (vorher) nicht gewußt. Ich war dabei, (deswegen) zu Dir zu kommen,
			<lb n="5"/>
		als mich das Eintreffen einer Schar (von Freunden) in Beschlag genommen hat. Ich hätte gern -
		to you but was detained (literally: preoccupied, distracted) by the arrival of a group. I hope
			<lb n="6"/>
		Gott stärke Dich - daß Du mich über ihn und seinen Zustand auf dem Laufenden hältst. Sollten unsere Freunde auseinandergehen,
		- may God give you strength - that you will send me his news and (tell me) how he is. Four of
		- May God give you strength! - that you will send me his news and (tell me) how he is. Four of
			<lb n="7"/>
		komme ich bei Dir (noch) vorbei. Außerdem übersende ich Dir (beiliegend)
		our companions have betaken themselves to you. I have sent you
			<lb n="8"/>
		a letter from Bint Lamīṭas, your maid-servant,
		einen Brief von Bint Lamiyaṭis, Deinem Dienstmädchen.
			<lb n="9"/>
		for you to read, God willing.
		Lies ihn, so Gott will!
			<lb n="10"/>
		Gott lasse Dich lange leben, stärke Dich und möge mich als Dein Lösegeld geben!
		May God prolong your life and give you strength, and may I be made your ransom!
		May God prolong your life and give you strength, and may I be made your ransom.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
