<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1483" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_17" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 17 (= P.Khalili II 74)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_17</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169263</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  جعلت فداك يأختي وأطال اللّه بقاك وجعلني من كل سو فداك ولا عنيت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بسماع </lem><rdg resp="APD">لسماع</rdg></app> المكروه فيك 
 <lb n="3"/>  برحمته كتابي إليك يأختي وأنا وأم ابنها وجماعتنا على أفضل ما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بخير </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تحبّي</rdg></app> واللّه محمود لا شريك له 
 <lb n="4"/>  وصلّى اللّه على محمّد النّبي وسلّم كثيرا أعلمك يا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أختي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">يأختي</rdg></app> أن قدم أبو القسم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأخبرني </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فأخبرني</rdg></app> بسلامتك فسرّني ذلك 
 <lb n="5"/>  وحمدت اللّه على ذلك كثيرا ووصل إلي القفّة التّفّاح وأربع تلاليس قمح <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وكلناه </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فكلناه</rdg></app> فوجدنا فيها 
 <lb n="6"/>  أربع أرادب وثلاث ويبات بالقفيز الكبير وقد ولله يأختي غمّني حبسك بالقرية وإن كان 
 <lb n="7"/>  إنّما حبسك في سبب القمح فدعيه في الدّار وعجّلي علينا بقدومك فقد واللّه أسبقنا إليك 
 <lb n="8"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> بسبب محبسـك من القرية وقد وجّهت إليك خمس تلاليس وأبزار العنّاب وهي بخمسة 
 <lb n="9"/>  قراطيس <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">واعلم </lem><rdg resp="Diem “reconstructed”">واعلمي</rdg></app> كذلك أنّا لم نكتب إليك مع غلام وزيد فواللّه يأختي ما علمت به خير خرج 
 <lb n="10"/>  ولا جا إلي و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أمّ</supplied> ابنها تقرئك السّلم كثيرا وتقولك يا سيّتّي ما أشد شوقي إليك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأسل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فأسل</rdg></app> اللّه 
 <lb n="11"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem “reconstructed”">قلبي</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ابنتك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">برفقتك</rdg></app> قبل الموت فعند ذا يا ستّي عرفت لپس پحپپن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عتدما </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تحبّيني</rdg></app> قعدنى وهدا 
 <lb n="12"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>ك </lem><rdg resp="Diem “first three letters reconstructed”">فعجّلي</rdg></app> علي بالقدوم ولا تقعدي أكثر من ذلك واقري أم أحمد وأم سليمن السّلم كثيرا وعلى صفرة 
 <lb n="13"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـسّلم كثيرا وعلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ذباب </lem><rdg resp="APD">ذباب </rdg><rdg resp="APD">ذبّاب</rdg></app> وغزال وجميع الصّبيان السّلم كثيرا والكاتبة تقرأ عليكم السّلم 
 <lb n="14"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>لسّلم عليكم ورحمت اللّه وبركاته وصلّى اللّه على محمّد النّبي وسلّم 
 <lb n="Verso, address"/>  من رجحان مولات أبو <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">المزاحم </lem><rdg resp="APD">المزاحم</rdg></app> إلى صندل الخادم 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ǧuʿiltu fidāʾa ki yā ʾuḫt ī wa ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ki wa ǧaʿala nī min kulli sūʾ:in fidāʾa ki wa lā ʿunītu bi li samāʿi ăl makrūhi fī ki 
 <lb n="3"/>bi raḥmati hi kitāb ī ʾilay ki yā ʾuḫt ī wa ʾanā wa ʾummu ĭbni hā wa ǧamāʿatu nā ʿalà ʾafḍali mā bi ø ḫayr:in tuḥibbī wa ăl lāhu maḥmūd:un lā šarīka la hu 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa sallama kaṯīr:an ʾuʿlimu ki yā ø yā ʾuḫt ī ʾan qadima ʾabū ăl qāsimi wa fa ʾaḫbara nī bi salāmati ki fa sarra nī ḏālika 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ḥamidtu ăl lāha ʿalà ḏālika kaṯīr:an wa waṣala ʾilay ya ăl quffaẗu ăt tuffāḥi wa ʾarbaʿu talālīsi qamḥ:in wa fa kilnā hu fa waǧadnā fī hā 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾarbaʿa ʾarādiba wa ṯalāṯa waybāt:in bi ăl qafīzi ăl kabīri wa qad wa ăl lāhi yā ʾuḫt ī ġamma nī ḥabsu ki bi ăl qaryaẗi wa ʾin kāna 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾinnamā ḥabsu ki fī sababi ăl qamḥi fa daʿī hi fī ăd dāri ʿaǧǧilī ʿalay nā bi qudūmi ki fa qad wa ăl lāhi ʾasbaqnā ʾilay ki 
 <lb n="8"/>*** bi sababi maḥbasi ki mina ăl qaryaẗi wa qad waǧǧahtu ʾilay ki ḫamsa talālīsa wa ʾabzāra ăl ʿunnābi wa hiya bi ḫamsaẗi 
 <lb n="9"/>qarāṭīsa wa ĭʿlam ĭʿlamī kaḏālika ʾan nā lam naktub ʾilay ki maʿa ġulām:in wa zayd:un fa wa ăl lāhi yā ʾuḫt ī mā ʿalimtu bi hi ḫayr ḫaraǧa 
 <lb n="10"/>wa lā ǧāʾa ʾilay ya wa ʾummu ĭbni hā tuqriʾu ki ăs salāma kaṯīr:an wa taqūlu ki yā sayyitt ī mā ʾašadda šawq ī ʾilay ki wa fa ʾasalu ăl lāha 
 <lb n="11"/>*** *** ī qalb ø ø bi ĭbnat rifqati ki qabla ăl mawti fa ʿinda ḏā yā sitt ī ʿaraftu ʾanna ki laysa tuḥibbīna tuḥibbī ø nī ʿinda mā qaʿadtī wa hāḏā 
 <lb n="12"/>*** fa ki ʿaǧǧilī ʿalay ya bi ăl qudūmi wa lā taqʿudī ʾakṯara min ḏālika wa ĭqrī ʾumma ʾaḥmada wa ʾumma sulaymāna ăs salāma kaṯīr:an wa ʿalà ṣufraẗa 
 <lb n="13"/>*** ăs salāma kaṯīr:an wa ʿalà ḏabbāb:in dabbāb:in ḏubāba wa ġazāla wa ǧamīʿi ăṣ ṣibyāni ăs salāma kaṯīr:an wa ăl kātibaẗu taqraʾu ʿalay kumu ăs salāma 
 <lb n="14"/>*** ăs salāmu ʿalay kum wa raḥmatu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa sallama 
 <lb n="15"/>min ruǧḥāna mawlāti ʾabū ăl murāḥimi muzāḥimi ʾilà ṣandala ăl ḫādimi 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  May I be made your ransom, my sister, and may God prolong your life and make me your ransom from every evil. May I never be afflicted with the hearing of bad news about you,
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  by His mercy. I am writing to you, my sister, while I, ʾUmm ʾIbnihā (literally &#039;the mother of her son&#039;) and our community are well. God be praised, He has no partner,
 	  ... so ausgezeichnet geht, wie Du es (nur) wünschen kannst. ...
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  and may God give many blessings to Muḥammad the prophet and save him. I am letting you know, my sister, that ʾAbū al-Qāsīm has come and informed me of your good health. That pleased me
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  and I gave much praise to God for that. I have received the basket of apples and the four baskets of wheat. We measured it and found in them
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  four ʾardabs and three waybāt according to the large qāfiz. By God, my sister, your being detained in the village distressed me. If
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  you are being detained on account of the wheat, leave it in the house an hasten to us for we have sent to you already
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  [   ] on account of your detention in the village. We have sent to you five baskets and jujube seeds, (wrapped) in five sheets of
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  papyrus. You should know also that we did not send this letter to you with a servant boy for Zayd - by God, my sister, we know no good in him, he went out
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  and did not come back to me. ʾUmm ʾIbnihā sends you her very best wishes and says to you: My lady, how great is my longing for you and I ask God
 	  [ʾUmm Ibnihā lässt Dir Grüsse ausrichten und sagt Dir: &#034; ...] So bitte ich denn Gott,
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  [er möge] mein Herz vor meinem Tode durch Deine Gesellschaft [erfreuen].&#034; Da (sc. als [ʾUmm Ibnihā] ihre Sehnsucht nach der Adressatin ausdrückte) wußte ich, daß Du mich, wenn Du (so) lange (dort) verweilst, nicht liebst.
 	  [...] your daughter before death. Then I knew, my lady, that you do not like it when you are away...
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  [   ] come to me and do not stay away more than this. Give ʾUmm ʾAḥmad and ʾUmm Sulaymān our best wishes. Also to Ṣufra
 	  Komme also schleunigst zu mir! ...
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  [give our] best wishes. To Dabbāb and Ġazāl and all the boys give our best wishes. The woman scribe sends you her best wishes.
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  [        ] best wishes to you and the mercy of God and his blessings. May God bless Muḥammad the prophet and save (him).
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  From Rujḥān the freedwoman of ʾAbū Murāḥim to Ṣandal the eunuch.
 	  ... to Ṣandal the (female) servant.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
