<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1471" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_14" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 14 (= P.Khalili II 34)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_14</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169253</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـسم اللّه الرّ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حمن</supplied> الــ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـرّحيم</supplied> 
 <lb n="2"/>  لأبي يعفر عافاه اللّه من مكيس بن صمون سلم عليك فإنّي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أحمد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عليك</supplied> 
 <lb n="3"/>  اللّه الّذي لا إله إلّا هو <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">تعالى</supplied> 
 <lb n="4"/>  أمّا بعد أصلحك وحفظك وأتم عليك في الأمور كلّها 
 <lb n="5"/>  نعمته كتبت إليك عافاك اللّه وما قبلنا مـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـن</supplied> ضيعتك على ما 
 <lb n="6"/>  يسرّك واللّه محمود بلغـني كتابك أطال اللّه بقاك فسرّني سلامتك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وأ</supplied>سل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فأسل</rdg></app> اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="7"/>  أن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يسقيك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">يبقيك</rdg></app> و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>ن يرينا فيك العافية ولا يريـنا فيك شاي نكرهه أبدا فإن 
 <lb n="8"/>  بقاك لنا بقا 
 <lb n="9"/>  وكتـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـبـ</supplied>ـت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إليـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـنـ</supplied>ـا </lem><rdg resp="APD">إليّا</rdg></app> أنّك لا تدري ما منعني من البعثة بما <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كـ</supplied>ـنت أوصيتني 
 <lb n="10"/>  من المتاع وإنّه أوّل ما قدمت القرية قدم زياد <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>لعزيز على 
 <lb n="11"/>  الّذي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">والي </lem><rdg resp="LS">والى</rdg></app> على بو كبير <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فأسعاني </lem><rdg resp="APD">فأشغلني</rdg></app> في الغرم والـسّجن <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> لي وألقاني 
 <lb n="12"/>  بإيد صلح بن البنا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">نيّ</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> عر<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ابن</unclear> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> دينر واحـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـژ</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أسـ</supplied>ـعاني بعت 
 <lb n="13"/>  فيها كل شاي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أ</supplied>ملكه لي أو لأهلي ثم أنّه لم يمنعني من <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ذ</unclear><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لك</supplied> 
 <lb n="14"/>  أن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أنسا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أنسا </rdg><rdg resp="Diem">أنسأ</rdg></app> شاي ممّا وكّلتني به إلّا أنّي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أردت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لبثب</rdg></app> أن أدب في <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أسـ</supplied>ـقيتنا الكبيرة 
 <lb n="15"/>  لأنّهم أحفض لمـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـسـ</supplied>ـقا من غيرهم 
 <lb n="16"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> الّتي بعثت <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بها </lem><rdg resp="APD">بما</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">عمـپى</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="Diem"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/></rdg></app> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>ه واما 
 <lb n="verso"/>  لأبي يعفر عافاه اللّه من مكيس بن صـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمو</supplied>ن 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>li ʾabī yaʿfura ʿāfā hu ăl lāhu min mikīsa bni ṣamūna salām:un ʿalay ka fa ʾin nī ʾaḥmadu ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl lāha ăllaḏī lā ʾilāha ʾillā huwa taʿālà 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾammā baʿdu ʾaṣlaḥa ka wa ḥafiẓa ka wa ʾatamma ʿalay ka fī ăl ʾumūri kulli hā 
 <lb n="5"/>niʿmata hu katabtu ʾilay ka ʿāfā ka ăl lāhu wa mā qibala nā min ḍayʿati ka ʿalà mā 
 <lb n="6"/>yasurru ka wa ăl lāhu maḥmūd:un balaġa nī kitābu ka ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka fa sarra nī salāmatu ka wa fa ʾasalu ăl lāha ăr raḥmāna ăr raḥīma 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾan yasqiya yubqiya ka wa ʾan yuriya nā fī ka ăl ʿāfiyaẗa wa lā yuriya nā fī ka šāy nakrahu hu ʾabad:an fa ʾinna 
 <lb n="8"/>baqāʾa ka la nā baqāʾ:un 
 <lb n="9"/>wa katabta ʾilay nā yā ʾanna ka lā tadrī mā manaʿa nī mina ăl baʿṯaẗi bi mā kunta ʾawṣayta nī 
 <lb n="10"/>mina ăl matāʿi wa ʾinna hu ʾawwala mā qadimtu ăl qaryaẗa qadima ziyādu *** ăl ʿazīzu ʿalà 
 <lb n="11"/>ăllaḏī wālà wālī ʿalà bū kabīr:in fa ʾasʿā ʾašġala nī fī ăl ġurmi wa ăs siǧni *** l ī wa ʾalqā nī 
 <lb n="12"/>bi ʾīdi ṣāliḥi bni ăl bunāniyyi *** ʿr*** ĭbni *** dīnār wāḥ* ʾasʿā nī biʿtu 
 <lb n="13"/>fī hā kulla šāy:in ʾamliku hu l ī ʾaw li ʾahl ī ṯumma ʾanna hu lam yamnaʿ nī min ḏālika 
 <lb n="14"/>ʾan ʾansā ʾansaʾa ʾnšʾ šāy mim mā wakkalta nī bi hi ʾillā ʾan nī ʾaradtu labiṯtu ʾan ʾadaba fī ʾasqiyati nā ăl kabīraẗi 
 <lb n="15"/>liʾanna hum ʾaḥfaḍu li misqā min ġayri him 
 <lb n="16"/>*** ăllatī baʿaṯtu bi bi hā mā ø *** ġamma nī ***ẗ wa ʾammā 
 <lb n="17"/>li ʾabī yaʿfura ʿāfā hu ăl lāhu min mikīsa bni ṣamūna 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  To ʾAbū Yaʿfur, may God give him health, from Mikis ibn Samūn. Peace be upon you. I praise for your sake God,
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  other than Whom there is no other god, He is exalted.
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  As for what follows, may He grant you well being, preserve you and give you your full measure of his favours in all matters,
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  I am writing to you, may God grant you health, while your estate here is as you
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  ... [So] bitte ich denn Gott...
 	  wish, God be praised. Your letter reached me, may God prolong your life, and I was pleased (to hear of) your good health. I ask God, the merciful and compassionate,
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  dich weiter am Leben zu erhalten... , denn
 	  to send down rain to you and to cause us to see you in health and never to see you in a state which displeases us, for
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  daß Du weiterlebst bedeutet (auch) für uns Weiterleben.
 	  your life is our life.
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  You wrote to me that you do not know what prevented me from sending the goods which you had commissioned me with.
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  As soon as I reached the village Ziyād [   ] al-ʿAzīz went to
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  the head of Bū Kabīr and he imposed upon me a fine and a prison sentence [   ] and threw me
 	  to the one who protects Bū Kabīr...
 	  ... und er ließ mich meinen Lebensunterhalt wegen der Strafe und des Gefängnisses verdienen. / ... und er bewirkte, daß ich mit der Geldstrafe und dem Gefängnis voll in Anspruch genommen war.
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  into the hands of Ṣāliḥ ibn al-Bunā[nī   ]...[  ]...[  ]dīnār and...[   ]... and I sold
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  for it (i.e. the fine (?)) every thing which I and my family own. Then none of this prevented me from
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  addressing anything which you commissioned me with, except that I wanted to pursue the journey with our large water-skins
 	  etwas von den mir von Dir erteilten Aufträgen zu vergessen (bzw. aufzuschieben); vielmehr zögerte ich, ...
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  since they are more retentive of water than the others
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  [....] which I sent, troubles me [   ] and as for...
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  To ʾAbū Yaʿfur, may God grant him health, from Mikis ibn Samūn.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
