<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1293" xml:id="Khan_Development_4" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.KhanPetitions 4</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Development_4</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169116</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">صلوات</supplied> اللّه وبركاته ونوامي زكواته وأفضل سلامته وتحيّاته 
<lb n="3"/>  على مولانا وسيّدنا الأمام الحافظ لدين اللّه أمير المومپپن 
<lb n="4"/>  وعلى آبائه الطّاهرين وأبنائه الأكرمين صلاة باقية إلى يوم الدّين 
<lb n="5"/>  المملوك يقبّل الأرض أمام المجلس العالي الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـمـ</supplied>ـعظّم المنصور السّيّدي 
<lb n="6"/>  الأجلّي الأفضلي الجيوشي السّيفي النّاصري الكافل لقضاة 
<lb n="7"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">المسلمين</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">والهادي</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لدعاة</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">المومپپن</supplied> خلّد اللّه ملك مالكه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ṣalawātu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu wa nawāmī zakawāti hi wa ʾafḍalu salāmati hi wa taḥīyāti hi 
 <lb n="3"/>ʿalà mawlā nā wa sayyidi nā ăl ʾimāmi ăl ḥāfiẓi li dīni ăl lāhi ʾamīri ăl muʾminīna 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ʿalà ʾābāʾi hi ăṭ ṭāhirīna wa ʾabnāʾi hi ăl ʾakramīna ṣalāẗ:un bāqiyaẗ:un ʾilà yawmi ăd dīni 
 <lb n="5"/>ăl mamlūku yuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa ʾamāma ăl maǧlisi ăl ʿālī ăl muʿaẓẓami ăl manṣūri ăs sayyidiyyi 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl ʾaǧalliyyi ăl ʾafḍaliyyi ăl ǧuyūšiyyi ăs sayfiyyi ăn nāṣiriyyi ăl kāfili li quḍāẗi 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl muslimīna wa ăl hādī li duʿāẗi ăl muʾminīna ḫallada ăl lāhu mulka māliki hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		The blessings and benedictions of God, and his increasing benefactions and most excellent salutation and greetings
			<lb n="3"/>
		upon our lord and master the Imām al-Ḥāfiẓ li-Dīn illāh, Commander of the Faithful
			<lb n="4"/>
		and upon his pure ancestors and his most noble sons, with a blessing enduring until the day of judgement.
			<lb n="5"/>
		The slave kisses the ground before the lofty, mighty and glorious seat of the
			<lb n="6"/>
		most exalted lord, al-ʾAfḍal, commander of the armies, sword of Islam, the defender, the protector of the judges
			<lb n="7"/>
		[of the Muslims and guide of the dāʿīs of the believers], may God perpetuate the dominion of him who holds it.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
