<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1462" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_5" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 05 (= P.Khalili II 09 recto)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_5</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169246</idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> دينر قبضت من ذلك <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="2"/>  مبلغ كرى دار الخربة دينرين وثلثي دينر وقيراط وثلث قبضت من ذلك نصف وربع دينر و<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="3"/>  مبلغ كرى دار أم مكّي ثلثة دنانير ونصف وقراط قبضت من ذلك دينر ونصف دينر و<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="4"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مبلـ</supplied>ـغ كـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـر</supplied>ى معمر <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">مخروب </lem><rdg resp="Diem">معيوب</rdg></app> دينرين وثلثي دينر قبضت <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">من</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ذلك</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="5"/>  مبلغ كرى دار رفّا وطرّف دينرين قبضت من ذلك دينر 
 <lb n="6"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مبلـ</supplied>ـغ كر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ى</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">حو</supplied>انيت المغازلي دينرين وسدس دينر قبضت من ذلك نصف وثمن دينر <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="7"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مبلـ</supplied>ـغ كرى دار السّمنّودي ثلثة <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">دنانير</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وثـ</supplied>ـلث وقيراطين قبضت من ذلك نصف وثلث <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">دينر</supplied> 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** dīnār:un qabaḍtu min ḏālika *** 
 <lb n="2"/>mablaġu kirà dāri ăl ḫirbaẗi dīnārayni wa ṯulṯay dīnār:in wa qīrāṭ:un wa ṯulṯ:un qabaḍtu min ḏālika niṣfa wa rubʿa dīnār:in wa *** 
 <lb n="3"/>mablaġu kirà dāri ʾummi makkiyy:in ṯalāṯaẗu danānīra wa niṣf:un wa qirāṭ:un qabaḍtu min ḏālika dīnār wa niṣfa dīnār:in wa *** 
 <lb n="4"/>mablaġu kirà maʿmari maʿmar:in maḫrūb:in maʿyūb:in dīnārayni wa ṯulṯay dīnār:in qabaḍtu min ḏālika *** 
 <lb n="5"/>mablaġu kirà dāri raffāʾ:in wa ṭarrāf:in dīnārayni qabaḍtu min ḏālika dīnār 
 <lb n="6"/>mablaġu kirà ḥawānīti ăl maġāziliyyi dīnārayni wa sudsu dīnār:in qabaḍtu min ḏālika niṣfa wa ṯumna dīnār:in *** 
 <lb n="7"/>mablaġu kirà dāri ăs samannūdiyyi ṯalāṯaẗu danānīra wa ṯulṯ:un wa qīrāṭayni qabaḍtu min ḏālika niṣfa wa ṯulṯa dīnār:in 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  [   ...]dīnār. I have received of that[   ]
 	  [   ...]dīnār. Of that I have received [   ]
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  The amount of rent from the house of the ruin - two dīnārs, two thirds of a dīnār, a qīrāṭ and a third. Of that I have received a half and a quarter of a dīnār and [  ]
 	  The amount of the rent of the house of the ruin - two dīnārs, two thirds of a dīnār, a qīrāṭ and a third. I have received of that a half and a quarter of a dīnār and [  ]
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  The amount of rent from the house of Umm Makki - three dīnārs and a half and a qīrāṭ. Of that I have received one dīnār and a half dīnār and [  ]
 	  The amount of the rent of the house of ʾUmm Makkī - three dīnārs and a half and a qīrāṭ. I have received of that one dīnār and a half dīnār and [  ]
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  The amount of rent from a ruined dwelling - two dīnārs and two thirds of a dīnār. Of that I have received...
 	  [The amount] of the rent of a ruined dwelling - two dīnārs and two thirds of a dīnār. I have received [of that...]
 	  [The amount] of the rent of the dwelling(?) of Maʿyūb
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  The amount of rent from the house of a darner and a cobbler - two dīnārs. Of that I have received one dīnār.
 	  The amount of the rent of the house of a darner and a cobbler - two dīnārs. I have received of that one dīnār.
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  The amount of rent from the shops of the spindle-maker - two dīnār and a sixth of a dīnār. Of that I have received a half and an eighth of a dīnār [   ]
 	  [The amount] of the rent of the shops of the spindle-maker - two dīnār and a sixth of a dīnār. I have received of that a half and an eighth of a dīnār [   ]
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  The amount of rent from the house of al-Samannudi - three [dīnārs and] a third and two qīrāṭs. Of that I have received a half and a third [dīnār].
 	  [The amount] of the rent of the house of al-Samannūdī - three [dīnārs and] a third and two qīrāṭs. I have received of that a half and a third [dīnār].
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
