<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1551" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_36" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 36 (= P.Khalili II 93)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_36</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169319</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  أطال اللّه بقاك وأدام عزّك وكرامتك وتأييدك وسعادتك وأتم نعمه علـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـيك</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  وزاد في إحسانه إليك في الدّنيا والآخرة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">من </lem><rdg resp="Diem">برحمته</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">خير </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">صـ</supplied>ـلّى اللّه على محمّد النّبي وعليه السّلم 
<lb n="4"/>  أعلمك أكرمـك اللّه أنّي قد كتبت إليك من الكتب ما لا أحصيها أذكر لك 
<lb n="5"/>  فيها أمر محمّد ولدي وما نزل <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">في </lem><rdg resp="Diem">بي</rdg></app> من مصيبة ولم أرا لك كتاب 
<lb n="6"/>  ولا خبر ولقد غمّني أمرك وبعد فلا أدري يصل كتـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـابي</supplied> والدّنانير فأسل ا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> 
<lb n="7"/>  أن لا يريك في من أحببت مكروه أحب تعلم أعزّك <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>للّه أنّه غمّني أمر خبرك 
<lb n="8"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إ</supplied>ذا لم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يأتني </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تأتي</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">متخبّر </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فتخبر</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـليـ</supplied>ـك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فواللّه</rdg></app> يا أخي إلّا ممّا عجّلت عـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـليه</supplied> بجواب كتابي هذا حليـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـت</supplied> 
<lb n="9"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">به</supplied> نفسي وقد <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">اتضا<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يقـ</supplied>ـت </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أبصرت</rdg></app> أنّك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عليك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">عليل</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لأي </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فغمّني</rdg></app> ذلك فأسـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـأل</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ا</supplied>للّه أن لا <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يـ</supplied>ـري فيك مكر<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وه</supplied> 
<lb n="10"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> أنّه <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يـ</supplied>ـتمتّع الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> الإجابة وقد <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> ويسـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> كتابي <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="11"/>  وبها نـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـسـ</supplied>ـتعيذ فإن شا اللّه <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> عـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="12"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> خبره أحسن اللّه <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">عزاك</unclear> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وأخلد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وأخلف</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عزّك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">عليك</rdg></app> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> في فهو الـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="13"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ألّا </lem><rdg resp="APD">إلّا</rdg></app> سـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> أحد <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـها الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">أعلمه</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="APD">اعلمه</rdg></app> الـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="14"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>ـك كنت أحب ألّا <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تدفع </lem><rdg resp="Diem">تدع</rdg></app> الكتاب <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">بخبرك</rdg></app> وحالك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وجوابـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـك</supplied> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وحوائجك</rdg></app> 
<lb n="15"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem">فإنّي</rdg></app> أسر بذلك عليك منّي أفضل السّلم وأطيـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـبـ</supplied>ـه وعلى جميع من قبلك 
<lb n="16"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">السّلـ</supplied>ـم كثيرا أطال الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـلّه</supplied> بقاك وأدام عزّك وكرامتك وتأييدك وسعادتك 
<lb n="17"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وصلّى</supplied> اللّه على محمّد النّبي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وسـ</supplied>ـلّم تسليم حسبنا اللّه ونعم الوكيل 
<lb n="18"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> لأبي عثمان أدام اللّه عزّه وكرامته من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أحمد </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أخيه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">بن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أبي</rdg></app> الأسود تدفع <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> بلّغ إليه 
<lb n="19"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><supplied reason="lost" cert="high">أسعـ</supplied>ـدك </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وليّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عند </lem><rdg resp="Diem">عبد</rdg></app> اللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وحسبنا </lem><rdg resp="Diem">وسعادته</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">اللّه </lem><rdg resp="Diem">ø</rdg></app> 
<lb n="20"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> المرة أن تخرج إليكم في <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> السّلم 
<lb n="21"/>   <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> واسعدها عپد وولدها 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾadāma ʿizza ka wa karāmata ka wa taʾyīda ka wa saʿādata ka wa ʾatamma niʿama hu ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="3"/>wa zāda fī ʾiḥsāni hi ʾilay ka fī ăd dunyā wa ăl ʾāḫiraẗi min bi ø raḥmati ø hi ḫayr:in ø wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa ʿalay hi ăs salāmu 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾuʿlimu ka ʾakrama ka ăl lāhu ʾan nī qad katabtu ʾilay ka mina ăl kutubi mā lā ʾuḥṣī hā ʾaḏkuru la ka 
 <lb n="5"/>fī hā ʾamra muḥammad:in walad ī wa mā nazala fī b ya ī min muṣībaẗ:in wa lam ʾarā la ka kitāb 
 <lb n="6"/>wa lā ḫabara wa la qad ġamma nī ʾamru ka wa baʿdu fa lā ʾadrī yaṣilu kitāb ī wa ăd danānīru fa ʾasalu ăl lāha 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾan lā yuriya ka fī man ʾaḥbabta makrūh ʾuḥibbu taʿlamu ʾaʿazza ka ăl lāhu ʾanna hu ġamma nī ʾamru ḫabari ka 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾiḏā lam yaʾti taʾtī nī ø ø fa mutaḫabbir:un tuḫbir ʿalay fa ka wa ø ăl ø lāhi yā ʾaḫ ī ʾillā mimmā ʿaǧǧalta ʿalay hi bi ǧawābi kitāb ī hāḏā ḥaliyat 
 <lb n="9"/>bi hi nafs ī wa qad ĭtḍāyaqtu ʾabṣartu ʾanna ka ʿalay ʿalīl:un ka ø laʾy:un fa ø ġamma ø nī ḏālika fa ʾasʾalu ăl lāha ʾan lā yuriya fī ka makrūh 
 <lb n="10"/>*** *** ʾanna hu yatamattaʿu ʾl*** *** *** ăl ʾiǧābaẗ wa qad *** wa ys*** kitāb ī *** 
 <lb n="11"/>wa bi hā nastaʿīḏu fa ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu *** *** *** ʿ** 
 <lb n="12"/>*** *** ḫabar h ʾaḥsana ăl lāhu ʿazāʾa ka wa ʾaḫlada ʾaḫlafa ʿizza ʿalay ka *** fī fa huwa ăl *** 
 <lb n="13"/>*** ʾallā ʾillā s*** ʾaḥad *** *** hā ʾl*** *** ʾaʿlamu ʾaʿlim ĭʿlam ʾuʿlimu hu ăl *** *** *** 
 <lb n="14"/>*** ka kuntu ʾuḥibbu ʾallā tadfaʿa tadaʿa ăl kitāba *** ḫabari bi *** *** ka wa ḥāli ka wa ǧawābi ḥawāʾiǧi ka 
 <lb n="15"/>*** *** fa *** ʾin *** nī ʾusarru bi ḏālika ʿalay ka minn ī ʾafḍalu ăs salāmi wa ʾaṭyabu hu wa ʿalà ǧamīʿi man qibala ka 
 <lb n="16"/>ăs salāmu kaṯīr:an ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾadāma ʿizza ka wa karāmata ka wa taʾyīda ka wa saʿādata ka 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa sallama taslīm ḥasbu nā ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
 <lb n="18"/>*** li ʾabī ʿuṯmāna ʾadāma ăl lāhu ʿizza hu wa karāmata hu min ʾaḥmada ʾaḫī ø hi bni ʾabī ăl ʾaswadi tadfaʿ *** balliġ ʾilay hi 
 <lb n="19"/>ʾasʿada waliyy ka ø ʿabdi ʿinda ăl lāhi wa ḥasbu saʿādata nā hu ăl ø lāhu ø 
 <lb n="20"/>*** *** ăl maraẗ ʾan taḫruǧa ʾilay kum fī *** ăs salām 
 <lb n="21"/>*** wa ʾasʿada hā ʿinda wa walada hā muḥammad 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
		In the name of God, the merciful، and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		May God prolong your life, may he preserve your strength, your honour, your support and your happiness, may he bestow upon you a full measure of his bounty
		May God prolong your life! May he preserve your strength, your honour, your support and your happiness! May he bestow upon you a full measure of his bounty
			<lb n="3"/>
		and increase His goodness to you in this world and the next! God bless Muhammad the prophet and upon him be peace!
		and may he increase his goodness to you in this world and the next. God bless Muḥammad the prophet and upon him be peace.
			<lb n="4"/>
		(I am writing to) let you know - may God show you kindness - that I have written to you innumerable letters, in which I told you about
		(I am writing to) let you know - May God show you kindness! - that I have written to you innumerable letters, in which I told you about
			<lb n="5"/>
		the affair of Muḥammad, my boy, and the affliction which has befallen me. I have not seen any letter of yours
		the affair of Muhammad, my boy, and the affliction which has befallen me. I have not seen any letter of yours,
			<lb n="6"/>
		nor (have I heard) any news and I am concerned about you. Now, I do not know whether my letter and the dīnārs will arrive. I pray to God
			<lb n="7"/>
		that he will not cause you to see anything unpleasant afflict those whom you love. I should like you to know - may God give you strength - that I am worried about you.
		that He will not cause you to see anything unpleasant afflict those whom you love. I should like you to know - May God give you strength! - that I am worried about you.
			<lb n="8"/>
		If we hear no more news from you than what you hasten to write in reply to this letter of min I shall be pleased.
		If we hear no more news from you than what you quickly write in reply to this letter of min I shall be pleased.
		Wenn Du nicht kommst, dann gib (doch wenigstens) Nachricht.
			<lb n="9"/>
		... ich habe (jetzt) deutlich erkannt, daß Du krank bist (sc. weil Du nicht schreibst); dies hat mich betrübt. ...
		It distresses me that you find this a burden. I pray to God that he does not cause me to see anything unpleasant concerning you.
			<lb n="10"/>
		[...] he enjoys [...] ... reply [...] ... my letter...
			<lb n="11"/>
		... God willing...
			<lb n="12"/>
		... Gott gebe Dir guten Trost und gewähre Dir Ersatz. ...
		[...] his news [...] may God give you good consolation and preserve your strength [...] ... he...
			<lb n="13"/>
			<lb n="14"/>
		... ich hätte gern, daß Du es nicht unterläßt, zu schreiben, wie es mit Dir steht, wie es Dir geht und welche Anliegen Du hast.
		... I should like you not to hand the letter [to ... tell me your news] and how you are, and your reply
			<lb n="15"/>
		denn ich würde mich darüber freuen. ...
		[so that] I should have pleasure in that. The very best wishes from me to you, and also the very best wishes to every one who is with you.
		[so that] I should have pleasure in that. The very best wishes from me to you, and also to every one who is with you
			<lb n="16"/>
		May God prolong your life, and may He preserve your strength, honour, support and happiness!
		the very best wishes. May God prolong your life and may he preserve your strength, honour, support and happiness.
			<lb n="17"/>
		God [bless] Muḥammad, the prophet, and save him. Our sufficiency is in God and in him we like to trust.
		God [bless] Muhammad the Prophet and save him! Our sufficiency is God, and in Him we like to trust.
			<lb n="18"/>
		To ʾAbū ʿUṯmān, may God preserve his strength and honour, from ʾAḥmad ibn al-ʾAswad, deliver [...] convey to him the message:
		To Abu ʿUthman - May God preserve his strength and honour! - from Ahmad ibn al-Aswad.
			<lb n="19"/>
		&#039;May God [help] you in it&#039;. Our sufficiency is God.
			<lb n="20"/>
		[...] the woman to go to you...
			<lb n="21"/>
		and (God) help her and her son Muḥammad in it.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
