<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1514" xml:id="Khan_Khalili_I_24" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khalili I 24 (= P.Khalili II 31)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khalili_I_24</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169285</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  صبّحـك اللّه بعافيته ومسّاك بكرامته 
<lb n="3"/>  أعلمك فديتك أن أتاني كتاب من بنت 
<lb n="4"/>  عمّك تذكر <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أن </lem><rdg resp="Diem">أنّ</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">رجل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">رجل</rdg></app> من قرابة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">مرة </lem><rdg resp="Diem">مرة</rdg></app> أبو الخير 
<lb n="5"/>  وقع بي في <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">قرية </lem><rdg resp="Diem">القرية</rdg></app> وكنت تعلم أن ليس لي 
<lb n="6"/>  خلق إلّا اللّه وأنت وقد وجّهت إليك 
<lb n="7"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بـ</supplied>ـكتاب لتقبـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـض وتشير علي برأيك 
<lb n="8"/>  أبعثك إلى <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">الـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـرّ</supplied>جل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">الرّجل</rdg></app> بـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـ</supplied>ـالبكرة أو أمسك 
<lb n="9"/>  عنه أو ترى أن يقسّـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـط</supplied> وضع وضعوه 
<lb n="10"/>  فينكر فيحتج علي <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لجزل </lem><rdg resp="Diem">لحال</rdg></app> النّفقة فأنّه لا 
<lb n="11"/>  يخاف اللّه والحمد للّه الّذي عشت 
<lb n="12"/>  عمري ما ذكرني إنسان إلّا إلى وجه 
<lb n="13"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">المشومة </lem><rdg resp="Diem">المشوم</rdg></app> وانتظرتك فديتك لتصير 
<lb n="14"/>  إلي فأشكوا إليك همّي فأسل اللّه بك البقا 
<lb n="15"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وا</supplied><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">لدك</unclear> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Diem “suggestion”">بمنّه</rdg></app> أطال اللّه بقاك وأعزّك وأكرمك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ṣabbaḥa ka ăl lāhu bi ʿāfiyati hi wa massā ka bi karāmati hi 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾuʿlimu ka fadaytu ka ʾan ʾatā nī kitāb:un min binti 
 <lb n="4"/>ʿammi ka taḏkuru ʾan ʾanna raḥala raǧul min qarābaẗi qurābaẗi maraẗi marraẗ:in ʾabū ăl ḫayri 
 <lb n="5"/>waqaʿa b ī fī ø ăl qaryaẗ:in qaryaẗi wa kunta taʿlamu ʾan laysa l ī 
 <lb n="6"/>ḫalq:un ʾillā ăl lāhu wa ʾanta wa qad waǧǧahtu ʾilay ka 
 <lb n="7"/>bi kitāb:in li taqbuḍa wa tušīra ʿalay ya bi raʾyi ka 
 <lb n="8"/>ʾabʿaṯu ka ʾilà ăr raḥli raǧuli bi ăl bukraẗi ʾaw ʾumsiku 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿan hu ʾaw tarà ʾan yuqassaṭa waḍʿ:un waḍaʿū hu 
 <lb n="10"/>fa yunkiru fa yaḥtaǧǧu ʿalay ya li ǧazli ḥāli ăn nafaqaẗi fa ʾanna hu lā 
 <lb n="11"/>yaḫāfu ăl lāha wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ăllaḏī ʿištu 
 <lb n="12"/>ʿumr ī mā ḏakara nī ʾinsān:un ʾillā ʾilà waǧhi 
 <lb n="13"/>ăl mašūmaẗi mašūmi wa ĭntaẓartu ka fadaytu ka li taṣīra 
 <lb n="14"/>ʾilay ya fa ʾaškū ʾilay ka hamm ī fa ʾasalu ăl lāha bi ka ăl baqāʾa 
 <lb n="15"/>wʾldk *** bi ø manni ø hi ʾaṭāla ăl lāhu baqāʾa ka wa ʾaʿazza ka wa ʾakrama ka 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God the merciful and compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		May God give you health in the morning and show you kindness in the evening (i. e. may he always give you health and show you kindness).
			<lb n="3"/>
		... (daß) ich einen Brief von der Tochter
		(I am writing to) let you know - may I be made your ransom - that a letter has come to me from the daughter
		(I am writing to) let you know - May I be made your ransom! - that a letter has come to me from the daughter
			<lb n="4"/>
		Deines Onkels väterlicherseits erhalten habe des Inhalts, daß ein Mann von der Verwandtschaft der Frau von ʾAbū l-Ḫayr
		of your uncle. She says that ʾAbū al-Ḵayr has recently left.
		of your uncle. She says that Abu &#039;l-Khayr has recently left.
			<lb n="5"/>
		im Dorf über mich hergezogen ist. ... daß ich
		I was afflicted by (this news) whilst I was in the village. You know I have
		I was afflicted by this news whilst I was in the village. You know I have
			<lb n="6"/>
		gar niemanden außer Gott und Dir habe. ...
		nobody except God. I have sent
			<lb n="7"/>
		a letter to you. When you receive it, indicate to me whether in your view
			<lb n="8"/>
		I should send you to the journey stage tomorrow or whether I shoud refrain
		... Mann...
			<lb n="9"/>
		from this, or do you think that they should pay a deposit in instalments (literally: a deposit which they make should be paid in instalments),
			<lb n="10"/>
		although he would disapprove of this and claim that I was spending excessively? He does not
		although he would disapprove of this and claim that I was spending excessively. He does not
		... wegen der Ausgaben...
			<lb n="11"/>
		fear God. God be praised that throughout
		Preis sei Gott, daß mich während meines bisherigen
			<lb n="12"/>
		Lebens noch jeder in unglücklicher
		my life people have always thought me to be
		my life people have always thought that I was
			<lb n="13"/>
		Erinnerung behalten hat. ...
		ill-fated (literally: people have not mentioned axcept in the manner (of speaking about) something illfated). I have been waiting for you to come
		ll-fated! I have been waiting for you to come
			<lb n="14"/>
		to me so that I can relate my predicament to you. I ask God to preserve you.
			<lb n="15"/>
		... may God prolong your life, give you strength and show you kindness!
		[...] ...[...] may God prolong your life, give you strength and show you kindness.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
