<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="1263" xml:id="Khan_Khurasan_28" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Khurasan 28</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Khan_Khurasan_28</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">169090</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم هذا 
<lb n="2"/>  ما شهد عليه يحيى بن حبّة والعذافر بن صفون 
<lb n="3"/>  وعبد اللّه مولى حرث ومحمّد بن سعيد 
<lb n="4"/>  وعبد اللّه بن سليمن وخاقان بن فرودى 
<lb n="5"/>  وخالد بن شيبان وشهدوا على أن هذه 
<lb n="6"/>  الجارية حمرة ابنت مير أوصت عيسى 
<lb n="7"/>  بن سالم وقبض مهرها خمس مئة درهم 
<lb n="8"/>  وما كان لها من قليل أو كثير من مهر أو غيره 
<lb n="9"/>  على خيب بن نشبود وأن وصي خيب 
<lb n="10"/>  خلّا لها سبيلها فليس له عليها 
<lb n="11"/>  دعوى ولا خصومة وقد برٮئ منه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi hāḏā 
 <lb n="2"/>mā šahida ʿalay hi yaḥyà bnu ḥabbaẗa wa ăl ʿuḏāfiru bnu ṣafwāna 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi mawlà ḥāriṯ:in wa muḥammadu bnu saʿīd:in 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu sulaymāna wa ḫāqānu bnu firūdà 
 <lb n="5"/>wa ḫālidu bnu šaybāna wa šahidū ʿalà ʾanna hāḏihi 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl ǧāriyaẗa ḥamraẗa ĭbnata mīr:in ʾawṣat ʿīsà 
 <lb n="7"/>bna sālim:in wa qabaḍa mahra hā ḫamsa miʾaẗi dirham:in 
 <lb n="8"/>wa mā kāna la hā min qalīl:in ʾaw kaṯīr:in min mahr:in ʾaw ġayri hi 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿalà ḫībi bni našbūda wa ʾanna waṣiyya ḫīb:in 
 <lb n="10"/>ḫallā la hā sabīla hā fa laysa la hu ʿalay hā 
 <lb n="11"/>daʿw:an wa lā ḫuṣūmaẗ:un wa qad bariʾat min hu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful and Compassionate. This is
			<lb n="2"/>
		what was testified by Yaḥyā ibn Ḥabba, al-ʿUdhāfir ibn Ṣafwān,
			<lb n="3"/>
		ʿAbd Allāh the client of Ḥārith, Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd,
			<lb n="4"/>
		ʿAbd Allāh ibn Sulaymān, Khāqān ibn Frōdā (?)
			<lb n="5"/>
		and Khālid ibn Shaybān. They testified to the fact that this
			<lb n="6"/>
		girl Ḥamra, the daughter of Mīr, has appointed ʿĪsā
			<lb n="7"/>
		ibn Sālim as her legatee and he has received her dowry, five hundred dirhams,
			<lb n="8"/>
		and what she is owed, of any amount, with regard to dowry and anything else
			<lb n="9"/>
		by Khīb ibn Nashbūd, and that the legatee of Khīb
			<lb n="10"/>
		has granted her freedom of action and has no
			<lb n="11"/>
		claim or contention over her and she has been released from him.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
