<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2501" xml:id="Little_FivePetitions_010" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleFivePetitions 25 recto</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_FivePetitions_010</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="right margin 1"/>  المماليك 
 <lb n="right margin 2"/>  بنو <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">السّلم</unclear> من نابلس 
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  يقبّلون الأرض وينهون أن على المماليك وقفا 
 <lb n="3"/>  من سلفهم شرط الواقف فيه أن يكون على ذكور ذريّته 
 <lb n="4"/>  دون إناثهم وللمماليك مدّة طويلة يتناولوا ريعه 
 <lb n="5"/>  الذّكور منهم دون الإناث وبأيديهم <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">أجاير</unclear> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أيضا </lem><rdg resp="APD">أجائز</rdg></app> متوافرة 
 <lb n="6"/>  ومحضر شرعي مثبوت على الحكّام يشهد لهم بصحّة ذلك 
 <lb n="7"/>  ثم أن شخصا في هذا الوقت نازع المماليك 
 <lb n="8"/>  وادّعى أن الوقف على الذّكور والإناث وليس معه ما 
 <lb n="9"/>  يدل على صحّة دعواه ولكن أشاع ذلك فيمن لا يثبت 
 <lb n="10"/>  بقوله شي وسوال المماليك من الصّدقات العميمة مولانا 
 <lb n="11"/>  وسيّدنا قاضي القضاة وخطيب خطبا المسلمين منحهم اللّه ببقائه 
 <lb n="12"/>  مرسوما كريما إلى الحاكم بالنّاحية بالتّروّي في ذلك 
 <lb n="13"/>  وتحرير قضيّتهم صدقة عليهم وإحسانا إليهم 
 <lb n="14"/>  أنهوا المماليك والحمد للّه وحده 
 <lb n="15"/>  وصلّى اللّه على سيّدنا محمّد وآله وسلّم 
 <lb n="16"/>  تم 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl mamālīku 
 <lb n="2"/>banū ăs slm min nābulusa 
 <lb n="3"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="4"/>yuqabbilūna ăl ʾarḍa wa yunhūna ʾanna ʿalà ăl mamālīki waqf:an 
 <lb n="5"/>min salafi him šaraṭa ăl wāqifu fī hi ʾan yakūna ʿalà ḏukūri ḏurriyyaẗi hi 
 <lb n="6"/>dūna ʾināṯi him wa li l mamālīki muddaẗ:un ṭawīlaẗ:un yatanāwalū rayʿa hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ăḏ ḏukūru min hum dūna ăl ʾināṯi wa bi ʾaydī him ʾayḍ:an ʾaǧāʾiru ʾaǧāʾizu mutawāfiraẗ:un 
 <lb n="8"/>wa maḥḍar:un šarʿiyy:un maṯbūt:un ʿalà ăl ḥukkāmi yašhadu la hum bi ṣiḥḥaẗi ḏālika 
 <lb n="9"/>ṯumma ʾanna šaḫṣ:an fī hāḏā ăl waqti nāzaʿa ăl mamālīka 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ĭddaʿà ʾanna ăl waqfa ʿalà ăḏ ḏukūri wa ăl ʾināṯi wa laysa maʿa hu mā 
 <lb n="11"/>yadullu ʿalà ṣiḥḥaẗi daʿwā hu wa lākin ʾašāʿa ḏālika fī man lā yaṯbutu 
 <lb n="12"/>bi qawli hi šayʾ:un wa suʾālu ăl mamālīki mina ăṣ ṣadaqāti ăl ʿamīmaẗi mawlā nā 
 <lb n="13"/>wa sayyida nā qāḍiya ăl quḍāẗi wa ḫaṭība ḫuṭabāʾi ăl muslimīna manaḥa humu ăl lāhu bi baqāʾi hi 
 <lb n="14"/>marsūm:an karīm:an ʾilà ăl ḥākimi bi ăn nāḥiyaẗi bi ăt tarawwī fī ḏālika 
 <lb n="15"/>wa taḥrīra qaḍiyyaẗi him ṣadaqaẗ:an ʿalay him wa ʾiḥsān:an ʾilay him 
 <lb n="16"/>ʾanhaw ăl mamālīku wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥdi hi 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in wa ʾāli hi wa sallama 
 <lb n="18"/>tamma 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  The slaves
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  the Banū al-S-l-m from Nablus
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  In the name of God the Compassionate the Merciful
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  kiss the ground and report that they have an endowment
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  in their favor from their ancestors, in which the endower stipulated that it be in favor of his male progeny,
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  excluding their females. For a long time the slaves have received the income,
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  the males among them, excluding the females. In their possession are also
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  cumulative authorizations (?) and a legal court record binding on magistrates, attesting to them the validity of that.
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  Subsequently a person has currently been disputing (the claim of) the slaves,
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  claiming that the endowment is in favor of the males and the females, but he has nothing
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  to prove the validity of his claim. Rather he has circulated that among people who cannot corroborate
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  his word in any way. The slaves request from the all-embracing bounties of Our Lord
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  and Master, Chief Judge and Chief Preacher of the Muslims, may God grant them his preservation,
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  a gracious decree to the magistrate in the district, to reflect on that
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  and to clarify this case as an act of charity and kindness to them.
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  The slaves reported (that). Praise be to God alone.
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  May God bless our Master Muḥammad and his family and give them peace.
		 <lb n="18"/>
 	  The End.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
