<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2425" xml:id="Little_TwoPetitions_02" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleTwoPetitions 2</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_TwoPetitions_02</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n=" upper right corner 1"/>  الحمد للّه 
 <lb n="upper right corner 2"/>  المملوك 
 <lb n="upper right corner 3"/>  محمّد بن أحمد الصّفدي 
 <lb n="upper right margin 1"/>  يقبّل الأرض وينهي أن المملوك أودع تحت يد محمّد بن نجيب الحصري قفّة ضمّنها تسعة أرطال وربع فلوس وقد توفّي المذكور وللمملوك بيّنة شهد بذلك وسواله إذنا كريما 
 <lb n="upper right margin 2"/>  بكتابة محضر شرعي وسماع بيّنته أشهد بذلك الحمد للّه وحده 
 <lb n="upper left corner 1"/>  ليكتب 
 <lb n="1 left"/>  الحمد للّٰهِ وَأسأله التّوفيق 
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّٰه الرّحْمٰن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  شهد من يضع خطّه آخره ومن يكتب عنه بإذنه <sic n="superfluous">ساهدپهم</sic> <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">شهادتهم</supplied> بها عالمون ولها محقّقون ولا يشكّون فيها ولا يرتابون بل ثواب اللّه تعالى <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يقصدون</supplied> 
 <lb n="3"/>  أنهم يعرفون الأخ محمّد بن المرحوم نجيب الحصري المتوفّى إلى رحمة اللّه تعالى قبل تأريخه المعرفة الشّرعيّة ويشهدون مع ذلك أنّه قبل وفاته 
 <lb n="4"/>  استودع لمحمّد بن أحمد الصّفدي المقيم يومئذ بالقدس الشّريف قفّة ضمّنها فلوس دراهم بلا فضّة تسعة أرطال وربع فلوس برطل الوزن <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
 <lb n="5"/>  وأنّه تسلّم ذلك ووضعه بحانوته بالقدس الشّريف وأن محمّد المذكور يستحق تسليم ذلك وقبضه علم شهوده ذلك وحقّقوه وبذلك وضعوا خطوطهم 
 <lb n="6"/>  مسولپن في العشر الآخر من شهر صفر سنة سبع وتسعين وسبعماية وسطّر ذلك حسب الإذن الكريم العالي المولوي القضائي الشّرفي 
 <lb n="7"/>  الأنصاري الشّافعي الحاكم بالقدس الشّريف وأعمالها أيّده اللّه تعالى وأسبغ ظلاله وختم بالصّالحات أعماله وحسبي اللّه ونعم الوكيل 
 <lb n="8 a"/>  شهد بمضمونه أحمد بن 
 <lb n="9 a"/>  علي بن عمر العلمي وكتب عنه 
 <lb n="10 a"/>  بإذنه وحضوره 
 <lb n="11 a"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="8 b"/>  شهد بمضمونه الحاج 
 <lb n="9 b"/>  علي ابن عبد اللّه بن عبد الدّائم 
 <lb n="11 b"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="8 c"/>  شهد بمضمونه 
 <lb n="9 c"/>  وكتب عن إذنه 
 <lb n="10 c"/>  وهو أبو <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">بكر</unclear> 
 <lb n="11 c"/>  ابن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ناهض</unclear> الشّريف 
 <lb n="12 c"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="8 d"/>  أشهد بمضمونه 
 <lb n="9 d"/>  كتب حسب إذنه قاسم 
 <lb n="10 d"/>  بن محمود 
 <lb n="11 d"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="8 e"/>  شهد بمضمونه أبو بكر بن أحمد 
 <lb n="9 e"/>  منتصر وكتب عنه بإذنه 
 <lb n="10 e"/>  وحضوره 
 <lb n="11 e"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="right margin 1"/>  ليشهد بثبوته واللّه المستعان المولى الشّيخ جمال الدّين المالكي نفع اللّه به ليحلف 
 <lb n="lower margin 1"/>  الحمد للّه 
 <lb n="lower margin 2"/>  حلف محمّد بن أحمد الصّفدي أنّه أودع محمّد بن نجيب المذكور القفّة الفلوس المذكورة أعلاه وفيها تسعة أرطال فلوس وربع رطل وأن الفلوس 
 <lb n="lower margin 3"/>  المذكورة باقية على ملكه ويستحق قبضها من موجده في ثالث شهر ربيع الأوّل سنة سبع وتسعين وسبعمائة والحمد للّه وحده وصلّى اللّه على محمّد وآله وصحبه 
 <lb n="lower margin 4 right"/>  حضره وشهد بجريانه 
 <lb n="lower margin 5 right"/>  عبد اللّه بن سليمان المالكي 
 <lb n="lower margin 6 right"/>  شهد عندي بذلك 
 <lb n="lower margin 4 left"/>  حضره وشهد بجريانه 
 <lb n="lower margin 5 left"/>  كتبه أحمد بن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">شوهيم</unclear> 
 <lb n="lower margin 6 left"/>  شهد عندي 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi 
 <lb n="2"/>ăl mamlūku 
 <lb n="3"/>muḥammadu bnu ʾaḥmada ăṣ ṣafadiyyu 
 <lb n="4"/>yuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa wa yunhī ʾanna ăl mamlūka ʾawdaʿa taḥta yadi muḥammadi bni naǧīb:ini ăl ḥuṣriyyi quffaẗ:an ḍimna hā tisʿaẗu ʾarṭāl:in wa rubʿ:un fulūs:in wa qad tuwuffiya ăl maḏkūru wa li l mamlūki bayyinaẗ:un šuhida bi ḏālika wa suʾālu hu ʾiḏn:an karīm:an 
 <lb n="5"/>bi kitābaẗi maḥḍar:in šarʿiyy:in wa samāʿi bayyinati hi ʾašhada bi ḏālika ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu 
 <lb n="6"/>li yuktab 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa ʾasʾalu hu ăt tawfīqa 
 <lb n="8"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="9"/>šahida man yaḍaʿu ḫaṭṭa hu ʾāḫira hu wa man yuktabu ʿan hu bi ʾiḏni hi šahādata hum bi hā ʿālimūna wa la hā muḥaqqaqūna wa lā yašukkūna fī hā wa lā yartābūna bal ṯawābu ăl lāhi taʿālà yaqṣidūna 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾanna hum yaʿrifūna ăl ʾaḫa muḥammada bna ăl marḥūmi naǧīb:ini ăl ḥuṣriyyi ăl mutawaffà ʾilà raḥmaẗi ăl lāhi taʿālà qabla taʾrīḫi hi ăl maʿrifaẗa ăš šarʿiyyaẗa wa yašhadūna maʿa ḏālika ʾanna hu qabla wafāti hi 
 <lb n="11"/>ĭstawdaʿa li muḥammadi bni ʾaḥmada ăṣ ṣafadiyyi ăl muqīmi yawmaʾiḏ:in bi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi quffaẗ:an ḍimna hā fulūsu darāhima bi lā fiḍḍaẗ:in tisʿaẗu ʾarṭāl:in wa rubʿ:un fulūs:in bi raṭli ăl wazni *** *** 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ʾanna hu tasallama ḏālika wa waḍaʿa hu bi ḥānūti hi bi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi wa ʾanna muḥammad ăl maḏkūra yastaḥiqqu taslīma ḏālika wa qabḍa hu ʿalima šuhūdu hu ḏālika wa ḥaqqaqū hu wa bi ḏālika waḍaʿū ḫuṭūṭa hum 
 <lb n="13"/>masʾūlīna fī ăl ʿušri ăl ʾāḫiri min šahri ṣafar:in sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa tisʿīna wa sabʿi miʾaẗ:in wa suṭṭira ḏālika ḥasaba ăl ʾiḏni ăl karīmi ăl ʿāliyyi ăl mawlawiyyi ăl qaḍāʾiyyi ăš šarafiyyi 
 <lb n="14"/>ăl ʾanṣāriyyi ăš šāfiʿiyyi ăl ḥākimi bi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi wa ʾaʿmāli hā ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu taʿālà wa ʾasbaġa ẓilāla hu wa ḫatama bi ăṣ ṣāliḥāti ʾaʿmāla hu wa ḥasb iya ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
 <lb n="15"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi ʾaḥmadu bnu 
 <lb n="16"/>ʿaliyyi bni ʿumara ăl ʿalamiyyu wa kutiba ʿan hu 
 <lb n="17"/>bi ʾiḏni hi wa ḥuḍūri hi 
 <lb n="18"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi ăl ḥāǧǧu 
 <lb n="20"/>ʿaliyyu ĭbnu ʿabdi ăl lāhi bni ʿabdi ăd dāʾimi 
 <lb n="21"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi 
 <lb n="23"/>wa kutiba ʿan ʾiḏni hi 
 <lb n="24"/>wa huwa ʾabū bakri 
 <lb n="25"/>ĭbni nāhiḍ:ini ăš šarīfi 
 <lb n="26"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="27"/>ʾašhadu bi maḍmūni hi 
 <lb n="28"/>kutiba ḥasaba ʾiḏni hi qāsimu 
 <lb n="29"/>bnu maḥmūd:in 
 <lb n="30"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="31"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi ʾabū bakri bnu ʾaḥmada 
 <lb n="32"/>muntaṣir:in wa kutiba ʿan hu bi ʾiḏni hi 
 <lb n="33"/>wa ḥuḍūri hi 
 <lb n="34"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="35"/>li yušhad bi ṯubūti hi wa ăl lāhu ăl mustaʿānu ăl mawlà ăš šayḫu ǧamālu ăd dīni ăl mālikiyyu nafaʿa ăl lāhu bi hi li yuḥlaf 
 <lb n="36"/>ăl ḥamdu li ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="37"/>ḥalafa muḥammadu bnu ʾaḥmada ăṣ ṣafadiyyu ʾanna hu ʾawdaʿa muḥammada bna naǧīb:ini ăl maḏkūra ăl quffaẗa ăl fulūsa ăl maḏkūraẗa ʾaʿlā hu wa fī hā tisʿaẗu ʾarṭāli fulūs:in wa rubʿu raṭl:in wa ʾanna ăl fulūsa 
 <lb n="38"/>ăl maḏkūraẗa bāqiyaẗ:un ʿalà milki hi wa yastaḥiqqu qabḍa hā min mawǧidi hi fī ṯāliṯi šahri rabīʿa ăl ʾawwali sanaẗa sabʿ:in wa tisʿīna wa sabʿi miʾaẗ:in wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà muḥammad:in wa ʾāli hi wa ṣaḥbi hi 
 <lb n="39"/>ḥaḍara hu wa šahida bi ǧarayāni hi 
 <lb n="40"/>ʿabdu ăl lāhi bnu sulaymāna ăl mālikiyyu 
 <lb n="41"/>šahida ʿind ī bi ḏālika 
 <lb n="42"/>ḥaḍara hu wa šahida bi ǧarayāni hi 
 <lb n="43"/>kataba hu ʾaḥmadu bnu šūhayma 
 <lb n="44"/>šahida ʿind ī 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  Praise be to God!
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  The slave
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  Muḥammad b. Aḥmad al-Ṣafadī
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  Kisses the ground and reports that he deposited a basket containing nine and 1/4 raṭls of copper coins with Muḥammad b. Najīb al-Ḥuṣrī, who died. The slave has witnesses who will testify to that. His request is gracious permission
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  that a legal court record be written and that his witnesses be heard. Praise be to God alone.
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  Let it be written
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  Praise be to God; I ask Him for success!
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  In the name of God the Compassionate, the Merciful,
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  Those who affixe their signature, or have them written with their permission, at the end, give testimony of which they are informed, competent, and without doubt or skepticism - aspiring rather to the reward of God the Exalted -
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  that they know with legal cognizance the brother Muḥammad, son of the deceased Najīb al-Ḥuṣrī, who passed into the mercy of God the Exalted before the document&#039;s date. They testify, moreover, that before his death
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  he deposited for Muḥammad b. Aḥmad al-Ṣafadī, residing at that time in Jerusalem the Noble, a basket containing copper dirhams without silver: nine and 1/4 ratls of copper, of weight (?),
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  that he received it and placed it in his shop in Jerusalem the Noble, and that the aforementioned Muḥammad is entitled to its delivery and receipt. Its witnesses being aware of that and substantiating it, affix their signatures
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  responsibly in the last decade of Ṣafar 797/16-25 December 1394. That was indited in accordance with the gracious permission of the High Master, the Qāḍī Sharaf al-Dīn
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  al-Anṣārī l-Shāfiʿī, the Magistrate in Jerusalem the Noble and its districts, may God the Exalted support him, extend his shadow, and seal his deeds with benefits! God is my sufficiency; how excellent a Keeper is He!
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  He was witness to it contents. Aḥmad b.
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  ʿAlī b. ʿUmar al-ʿAlamī. Written for
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  him with his permission and in his presence.
		 <lb n="18"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="19"/>
 	  He was witness to its contents. Al-Ḥājj
		 <lb n="20"/>
 	  ʿAlī b. ʿAbd Allāh b. ʿAbd al-Dāʾim
		 <lb n="21"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="22"/>
 	  He was witness to its contents.
		 <lb n="23"/>
 	  written with his permission,
		 <lb n="24"/>
 	  he being Abū Bakr (?)
		 <lb n="25"/>
 	  ibn Nāhiḍ (?) al-Sharīf
		 <lb n="26"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="27"/>
 	  I am witness to its contents.
		 <lb n="28"/>
 	  Written with his permission, Qāsim
		 <lb n="29"/>
 	  b. Maḥmūd.
		 <lb n="30"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="31"/>
 	  He was witness to its contents. Abū Bakr b. Aḥmad
		 <lb n="32"/>
 	  Muntaṣir. Written for him with his permission
		 <lb n="33"/>
 	  and in his presence
		 <lb n="34"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="35"/>
 	  Let there be witnesses to its certification. God is One Whose help is to be sought! Al-Mawlā Jamāl al-Dīn al-Mālikī, may God profit Him! Let there be an oath.
		 <lb n="36"/>
 	  Praise be to God!
		 <lb n="37"/>
 	  Muḥammad b. Aḥmad al-Ṣafadī swore that he entrusted with the mentioned Muḥammad b. Najīb the basket of copper coins mentioned above, containing nine 1/4 raṭls, that the copper
		 <lb n="38"/>
 	  mentioned remains his property, and that he is entitled to take possession of it from the place where it is located. (He took the oath) on 3 Rabīʿ I 797/27 December 1394. Praise be to God alone! May God bless Muḥammad, his family, and his companions!
		 <lb n="39"/>
 	  He attended and was witness to the administration of it (the oath).
		 <lb n="40"/>
 	  ʿAbd Allāh b. Sulaymān al-Mālikī.
		 <lb n="41"/>
 	  He was witness to that before me.
		 <lb n="42"/>
 	  He attended and was witness to the administration of it
		 <lb n="43"/>
 	  Written by Aḥmad b. Shuhaym (?)
		 <lb n="44"/>
 	  He was witness to that before me.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
