<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2573" xml:id="Little_FivePetitions_080" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleFivePetitions 305 verso</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_FivePetitions_080</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  المَلكي المنصوري 
 <lb n="3"/>  يعتمد 
 <lb n="4"/>  المرسوم بالأمْر الكريم العالي المولوي الأميري الكبيري المالكي المخدومي 
 <lb n="5"/>  البدري بن المقر المرحوم العمادي بن العسكري نايب السّلطنة وناظر الحرمين 
 <lb n="6"/>  الشّريفين بالقدس الشّريف وتربة سيّدنا الخليل عليه الصّلاة والسّلام أعز اللّه تعالى 
 <lb n="7"/>  أنصاره أن يتأمّل الإنها باطنا ويستمر رافعها المشار إليه باطنًا في الوظيفة 
 <lb n="8"/>  المذكورة باطنًا بالمعلوم المقرّر له على عادته ويستقر في الخدم 
 <lb n="9"/>  فليباشر الوظيفة المذكورة وليتناول المعلوم المذكور معتمدًا على 
 <lb n="10"/>  الخط الكريم أعلاه إن شا اللّه تعالى 
 <lb n="11"/>  كتبه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ثامن</unclear> </lem><rdg resp="APD">ثاني</rdg></app> شهر شعبان سنة أحد وثمانين وسبعمئة 
 <lb n="12"/>  حسبنا اللّه ونعم الوكيل 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ăl malikiyyu ăl manṣūriyyu 
 <lb n="3"/>yuʿtamad 
 <lb n="4"/>ăl marsūmu bi ăl ʾamri ăl karīmi ăl ʿālī ăl mawlawiyyi ăl ʾamīriyyi ăl kabīriyyi ăl mālikiyyi ăl maḫdūmiyyi 
 <lb n="5"/>ăl badriyyi bni ăl maqarri ăl marḥūmi ăl ʿimādiyyi bni ăl ʿaskariyyi nāyibi ăs salṭanaẗi wa nāẓiri ăl ḥaramayni 
 <lb n="6"/>ăš šarīfayni bi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi wa turbaẗi sayyidi nā ăl ḫalīli ʿalay hi ăṣ ṣalāẗu wa ăs salāmu ʾaʿazza ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾanṣāra hu ʾan yutaʾammala ăl ʾinhāʾu bāṭin:an wa yastamirra rāfiʿu hā ăl mušāru ʾilay hi bāṭin:an fī ăl waẓīfaẗi 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl maḏkūraẗi bāṭin:an bi ăl maʿlūmi ăl muqarrari la hu ʿalà ʿādati hi wa yastaqirra fī ăl ḫidami 
 <lb n="9"/>fa l yubāširi ăl waẓīfaẗa ăl maḏkūraẗa wa l yatanāwali ăl maʿlūma ăl maḏkūra muʿtamid:an ʿalà 
 <lb n="10"/>ăl ḫaṭṭi ăl karīmi ʾaʿlā hu ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="11"/>kataba hu ṯāmina ṯāniya šahri šaʿbāna sanaẗa ʾaḥad:in wa ṯamānīna wa sabʿi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="12"/>ḥasbu nā ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  al-Malik al-Manṣūr
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  Let it be executed.
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  (It is) the decree by the gracious and high command of the Lord, Grand Amīr, the Master and Served,
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  Badr al-Dīn ibn of the late Excellency ʿImād al-Dīn b. al-ʿAskarī, Royal Viceroy and Supervisor of the Two
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  Noble Sanctuaries in Jerusalem and at the tomb of Our Master Khalīl (prayers and peace be upon him), may God the Exalted make glorious
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  his victories, that the report on recto be given consideration and that its petitioner referred to on recto continue
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  in the position mentioned therein at the customary salary established for him and that he remain in service.
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  Let him perform the aforementioned office and receive the aforementioned salary, relying on
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  the gracious script above. God the Exalted willing.
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  Written on 8 Shaʿbān 781/19 November 1379.
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  God is our sufficiency and He ist the best keeper.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
