<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2399" xml:id="Little_TwoPetitions_01" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleTwoPetitions 1</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_TwoPetitions_01</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="recto upper right margin 1"/>  الحمد للّه 
 <lb n="recto upper right margin 2"/>  <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">المماليك</unclear> 
 <lb n="recto upper right margin 3"/>  محمّد وعبد الواحد وعلي 
 <lb n="recto upper right margin 4"/>  أولاد أحمد بن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">وهدان</unclear> بن أدهم 
 <lb n="recto upper margin 1"/>  يقبّلون الأرض وينهون أن قريبهم مخلوف بن مفرّج بن عمر بن أدهم توفّي إلى رحمة اللّه تعالى وانحصر إرثه في زوجته غزال بنت عبد اللّه عتاقة خطائي 
 <lb n="recto upper margin 2"/>  زوجة الجناب الزّيني جبرائل والمماليك ولهم بيّنة عادلة تشهد بذلك ويسألون إذنا كريما بكتابة محضر بذلك صدقة عليهم أنهوا ذلك الحمد لله وحده وصلّى اللّه على سيّدنا محمّد 
 <lb n="recto 1 left"/>  ليكتب 
 <lb n="recto 2 left"/>  المولى <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">شرف</unclear> الدّين الشّافعي 
 <lb n="recto 1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم فهو حسبي وكفي وصلواته وسلامه على سيّدنا محمّدوعلى ساپر عپاده الدپن اصطڤى 
 <lb n="recto 2"/>  شهوده يعرفون مخلوف بن مفرّج بن عمر بن أدهم المتوفّا المذكور أعلاه وأقاربه محمّد وعبد الواحد وعلي أولاد أحمد بن <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">وهدان</unclear> بن أدهم 
 <lb n="recto 3"/>  وغزال بنت عبد اللّه المذكورة أعلاه معرفة شرعيّة جامعة العين والاسم والنّسب ويشهدون مع ذلك شهادتهم بها عالمون ولها 
 <lb n="recto 4"/>  محقوقون لا يشكون في شي منها ولا يرتابون أن مخلوف المذكور توفّي إلى رحمة اللّه تعالى بمدينة القدس الشّريف وإنحصر إرثه في زوجته غزال 
 <lb n="recto 5"/>  المذكورة وأقاربه المذكورين وأنّهم يستحقّون إرثه شرعا وأنّه لا وارث له سواهم ولا يستحق إرثه إلّا هم علم شهوده ذلك 
 <lb n="recto 6"/>  وتحقّقوه وبه وضعوا خطوطـم مسئولين رغبة في قول الحق والعمل به بتأريخ ثامن عشر ذي الحجّة الحرام عام ثلاثة وتسعين وسبعمية 
 <lb n="recto 7"/>  وسطّر ذلك حسب الإذن الكريم العالي المولوي القضائي العالمي العاملي العلّامي الشّيخي العارفي الحاكمي الشّرفي الشّافعي أنقذه اللّه 
 <lb n="recto 8"/>  تعالي وسدّه في تأريخه المعيّن فيه الحمد لله رب العالمين وصلواته وسلامه على سيّدنا محمّد نبي الرّحمة وعلى آله <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">أجمعين</unclear> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">الجلل</unclear> وعلى سائر المرسلين والأنبيا <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> وسلّم 
 <lb n="recto 9 right"/>  شهد بمضمونه 
 <lb n="recto 10 right"/>  صالح بن عمر بن أحمد وكتب عنه 
 <lb n="recto 11 right"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="recto 9 left"/>  شهد بمضمونه 
 <lb n="recto 10 left"/>  أبو بكر بن عمر بن عثمان وكتب عنه 
 <lb n="recto 11 left"/>  شهد عندي 
 <lb n="verso 1"/>  ادّعي بطريقه 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi 
 <lb n="2"/>ăl mamālīku 
 <lb n="3"/>muḥammad:un wa ʿabdu ăl wāḥidi wa ʿaliyy:un 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾawlādu ʾaḥmada bni wahdāna bni ʾadhama 
 <lb n="5"/>yuqabbilūna ăl ʾarḍa wa yunhūna ʾanna qarība hum maḫlūfa bna mufarriǧi bni ʿumara bni ʾadhama tuwuffiya ʾilà raḥmaẗi ăl lāhi taʿālà wa ĭnḥaṣara ʾirṯu hu fī zawǧati hi ġazāla binti ʿabdi ăl lāhi ʿitāqaẗi ḫiṭāʾiyya 
 <lb n="6"/>zawǧaẗi ăl ǧanābi ăz zaynī ǧabrāʾila wa ăl mamālīku wa la hum bayyinaẗ:un ʿādilaẗ:un tašhadu bi ḏālika wa yasʾalūna ʾiḏn:an karīm:an bi kitābaẗi maḥḍar:in bi ḏālika ṣadaqaẗ:an ʿalay him ʾanhū ḏālika ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in 
 <lb n="7"/>li yuktab 
 <lb n="8"/>ăl mawlà šarafu ăd dīni ăš šāfiʿiyyu 
 <lb n="9"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi fa huwa ḥasb ī wa kafà wa ṣalawātu hu wa salāmu hu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in wa ʿalà sāʾiri ʿibādi hi ăllaḏīna ĭṣṭafà 
 <lb n="10"/>šuhūdu hu yaʿrifūna maḫlūfa bna mufarriǧi bni ʿumara bni ʾadhama ăl mutawaffā ăl maḏkūra ʾaʿlā hu wa ʾaqāriba hu muḥammad wa ʿabda ăl wāḥidi wa ʿaliyy ʾawlāda ʾaḥmada bni wahdāna bni ʾadhama 
 <lb n="11"/>wa ġazāla binta ʿabdi ăl lāhi ăl maḏkūraẗa ʾaʿlā hu maʿrifaẗ:an šarʿiyyaẗ:an ǧāmiʿaẗ:an ăl ʿayna wa ăli ĭsma wa ăn nasaba wa yašhadūna maʿa ḏālika šahādata hum bi hā ʿālimūna wa la hā 
 <lb n="12"/>maḥqūqūna lā yašukkūna fī šayʾ:in min hā wa lā yartābūna ʾanna maḫlūfa ăl maḏkūra tuwuffiya ʾilà raḥmaẗi ăl lāhi taʿālà bi madīnaẗi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi wa ĭnḥaṣara ʾirṯu hu fī zawǧati hi ġazāla 
 <lb n="13"/>ăl maḏkūraẗi wa ʾaqāribi hi ăl maḏkūrīna wa ʾanna hum yastaḥiqqūna ʾirṯa hu šarʿ:an wa ʾanna hu lā wāriṯa la hu siwā hum wa lā yastaḥiqqu ʾirṯa hu ʾillā hum ʿalima šuhūdu hu ḏālika 
 <lb n="14"/>wa taḥaqqaqū hu wa bi hi waḍaʿū ḫuṭūṭa hum masʾūlīna raġabaẗ:an fī qawli ăl ḥaqqi wa ăl ʿamali bi hi bi taʾrīḫi ṯāmina ʿašara ḏī ăl ḥiǧǧaẗi ăl ḥarāmi ʿāma ṯalāṯaẗ:in wa tisʿīna wa sabʿi miyaẗ:in 
 <lb n="15"/>wa suṭṭira ḏālika ḥasaba ăl ʾiḏni ăl karīmi ăl ʿālī ăl mawlawiyyi ăl qaḍāʾiyyi ăl ʿālimiyyi ăl ʿāmiliyyi ăl ʿallāmiyyi ăš šayḫiyyi ăl ʿārifiyyi ăl ḥākimiyyi ăš šarafiyyi ăš šāfiʿiyyi ʾanqaḏa hu ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="16"/>taʿālà wa sadda hu fī taʾrīḫi hi ăl muʿayyani fī hi ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi rabbi ăl ʿālamīna wa ṣalawātu hu wa salāmu hu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in nabiyyi ăr raḥmaẗi wa ʿalà ʾāli hi ʾaǧmaʿīna ăl ǧalali wa ʿalà sāʾiri ăl mursalīna wa ăl ʾanbiyāʾi *** wa sallama 
 <lb n="17"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi 
 <lb n="18"/>ṣāliḥu bnu ʿumara bni ʾaḥmada wa kutiba ʿan hu 
 <lb n="19"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="20"/>šahida bi maḍmūni hi 
 <lb n="21"/>ʾabū bakri bni ʿumara bni ʿuṯmāna wa kutiba ʿan hu 
 <lb n="22"/>šahida ʿind ī 
 <lb n="23"/>ŭdduʿiya bi ṭarīqi hi 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  Praise be to God!
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  The slaves
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  Muḥammad, ʿAbd al-Wāḥid, and ʿAlī,
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  the sons of Aḥmad b. Wahdān (?) b. Adham
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  Kiss the ground and report that their relative, Makhlūf b. Mufarrij b. Adham, passed into the mercy of God the Exalted and that his estate was restricted to his wife, Ghazāl bint ʿAbd Allāh, the freedwoman of Khiṭāʾī,
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  the wife of His Excellency Zayn al-Dīn Jibrāʾīl. The Slaves and their relative have witnesses of legal integrity who testify to that and they request gracious permission for the writing of a court record of that as a charity to them. They reported that - praise be to God alone. Blessings of God upon our Lord Muḥammad -
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  Let it be written
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  Al-Mawlā Sharaf (?) al-Dīn al-Shāfiʿī
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  In the name of God, the Compassionate and Merciful. He is my sufficiency and fulfillment. His blessings and peace upon our Lord Muḥammad and all his servants whom He has chosen.
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  Its witnesses know Makhlūf b. Mufarrij b. ʿUmar b. Adham, the above-mentioned deceased, and his relatives - Muḥammad, ʿAbd al-Wāḥid, and ʿAlī - the sons of Aḥmad b. Wahdān (?)
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  and Ghazāl bint ʿAbd Allāh mentioned above, with legal cognizance comprising the person, name and descent. In addition they give testimony about which they are knowledgeable
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  and competent, in which they have no doubt or skepticism whatsoever, that the mentioned Makhlūf passed into the mercy of God the Exalted in Jerusalem the Noble, that his estate is restricted to his above-mentioned wife Ghazāl,
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  and his above-mentioned relatives, that they are legally entitled to his estate, that he has no heir other than them, and that no one save them is entitled to his estate. Its witnesses being aware of that
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  and substantiating it, affix their signatures responsibly, desirous of speaking the truth and acting according to it, on 18 Dhū l-Ḥijja the Sacred 793/17 November 1391.
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  That was indited in accordance with the gracious permission of the High Master, the Learned, Efficacious, and Knowing qāḍī, the Sage Shaykh, the Noble Magistrate, Sharaf al-Dīn al-Shāfiʿī, may God the Exalted save him
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  and guide him, on the date therein specified. Praise be to God, Lord of the worlds! His blessings and peace upon our Lord Muḥammad, the prophet of mercy, all his revered (?) family, and all the [-?-] messengers and prophets.
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  He was witness to its contents,
		 <lb n="18"/>
 	  Ṣāliḥ b. ʿUmar b. Aḥmad. Written on his behalf.
		 <lb n="19"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="20"/>
 	  He was witness to its contents,
		 <lb n="21"/>
 	  Abū Bakr b. ʿUmar b. ʿUthmān. Written on his behalf.
		 <lb n="22"/>
 	  He was witness before me.
		 <lb n="23"/>
 	  It was claimed in its (legal) manner.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
