<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2558" xml:id="Little_FivePetitions_070" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleFivePetitions 305 recto</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_FivePetitions_070</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="right margin, opposite l. 1"/>  المملوك 
 <lb n="right margin, opposite l. 2"/>  إبراهيم النّاصري 
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  يقبّل الأرض وينهي أن للمملوك بيده ولايةٌ 
 <lb n="3"/>  شرعيّةٌ بقرآه ميعادٍ في المسجد الأقصى وله 
 <lb n="4"/>  من المعلوم في كلّ شهر عشرون درهما وسوآل 
 <lb n="5"/>  المملوك من صدقات مولانا ملك الأمرا أعز اللّه تعالى أنصاره 
 <lb n="6"/>  مرسوما كريما بإجرآ المملوك على عادَته صدقة 
 <lb n="7"/>  عنه وعن أولاده ويغتنم الآجر والدّعآ من المملوك 
 <lb n="8"/>  في الأماكن الشّريفة أنهى ذلك والحمد للّه وحده وصلّى اللّه 
 <lb n="9"/>  على سيّدنا محمّد وعلى آله وصحبه وسلّم إن شا اللّه تعالى 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl mamlūku 
 <lb n="2"/>ʾibrāhīmu ăn nāṣiriyyu 
 <lb n="3"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="4"/>yuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa wa yunhī ʾanna li l mamlūki bi yadi hi walāyaẗ:un 
 <lb n="5"/>šarʿiyyaẗ:un bi qirāʾaẗi mīʿād:in fī ăl masǧidi ăl ʾaqṣà wa la hu 
 <lb n="6"/>mina ăl maʿlūmi fī kulli šahr:in ʿišrūna dirham:an wa suʾālu 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl mamlūki min ṣadaqāti mawlā nā maliki ăl ʾumarāʾi ʾaʿazza ăl lāhu taʿālà ʾanṣāra hu 
 <lb n="8"/>marsūm:an karīm:an bi ʾiǧrāʾi ăl mamlūki ʿalà ʿādati hi ṣadaqaẗ:an 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿan hu wa ʿan ʾawlādi hi wa yaġtanimu ăl ʾaǧra wa ăd duʿāʾa mina ăl mamlūki 
 <lb n="10"/>fī ăl ʾamākini ăš šarīfaẗi ʾanhà ḏālika wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥdi hi wa ṣallà ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="11"/>ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in wa ʿalà ʾāli hi wa ṣaḥbi hi wa sallama ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  The slave
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  Ibrāhīm al-Nāṣirī
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  In the name of God the Compassionate, the Merciful
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  kisses the ground and reports that the slave has in his possession a legal appointment
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  to recite mīʿād in al-Masjid al-Aqṣā with
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  a salary of twenty dirhams every month. The request
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  of the slave from the bounties of Our Lord the King of Amīrs, may God the Exalted make his victories glorious,
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  is for a gracious decree that the slave be provided for as customary, as an act of bounty
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  from him and his children, thereby availing himself of (God&#039;s) reward and the slave&#039;s prayers
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  in the noble places. He reported that. Praise be to God alone. May God bless
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  Our Master Muḥammad, his family, and his companions and grant them peace, God willing.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
