<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2504" xml:id="Little_FivePetitions_030" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.LittleFivePetitions 215 recto</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Little_FivePetitions_030</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="right margin 1"/>  المملوكة 
 <lb n="right margin 2"/>  ستيتة زوجة موسى 
 <lb n="right margin 3"/>  القدسي 
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  تقبّل الأرض وتنهي أنّها مزوّجة بموسى القدسي المذكور 
 <lb n="3"/>  وللمملوكة منه ولد ذكر يدعى أحمد وبنت تدعى ست البنين وله مدّة 
 <lb n="4"/>  ثلاثة عشر سنة مسافرًا ببلاد اليمن وله ملك بالقدس الشّريف وللمملوكة 
 <lb n="5"/>  عليه فرض تلك المدّة ثابت على مولانا وسيّدنا أقضى القضاة شهاب 
 <lb n="6"/>  الدّين البادسي المالكي أّيّده اللّه تعالى وجملة الفرض مبلغ ثلاثة عشر ألف درهم 
 <lb n="7"/>  والمملوكة قد عجزت عن نفسها وعن ولديها وسوال المملوكة من الصّدقات 
 <lb n="8"/>  العميمة والعواطف الرّحيمة العالية الوافية من مولانا وسيّدنا قاضي القضاة 
 <lb n="9"/>  شيخ شيوخ العارفين أسبغ اللّه تعالى ظلاله وختم بالصّالحَات 
 <lb n="10"/>  أعماله مرسوم كريم إلي الحاكم بالقدس الشّريف أيّده اللّه تعالى بالتّمكّن ببيع ملك 
 <lb n="11"/>  زوج المملوكة المذكورة على حكم الفرض الثّابت بيد المملوكة لتجد 
 <lb n="12"/>  المملوكة بذلك الإعانة على فقرها وضعف حالها وأولادها 
 <lb n="13"/>  صدقة عن مولانا وسيّدنا قاضي القضاة وعن سلفه أنهت المملوكة 
 <lb n="14"/>  ذلك إنشا اللّه تعالى 
 <lb n="15"/>  الحمد للّه وحده وصلّى اللّه على سيّدنا محمّد وآله وصحبه وسلّم 
 <lb n="16"/>  تم 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl mamlūkaẗu 
 <lb n="2"/>sutaytaẗu zawǧaẗu mūsà 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl qudsiyyi 
 <lb n="4"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="5"/>tuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa wa tunhī ʾanna hā muzawwaǧaẗ:un bi mūsà ăl qudsiyyi ăl maḏkūri 
 <lb n="6"/>wa li l mamlūkaẗi min hu walad:un ḏakar:un yudʿà ʾaḥmada wa bint:un tudʿà sitta ăl banīna wa la hu muddaẗu 
 <lb n="7"/>ṯalāṯaẗa ʿašara sanaẗ:an musāfir:an bi bilādi ăl yamani wa la hu milk:un bi l qudsi ăš šarīfi wa li l mamlūkaẗi 
 <lb n="8"/>ʿalay hi farḍu tilka ăl muddaẗi ṯābit:un ʿalà mawlā nā wa sayyidi nā ʾaqḍà ăl quḍāẗi šihābi 
 <lb n="9"/>ăd dīni ăl bādisiyyi ăl mālikiyyi ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu taʿālà wa ǧumlaẗu ăl farḍi mablaġu ṯalāṯaẗa ʿašara ʾalfi dirham:in 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ăl mamlūkaẗu qad ʿaǧazat ʿan nafsi hā wa ʿan waladay hā wa suʾālu ăl mamlūkaẗi mina ăṣ ṣadaqāti 
 <lb n="11"/>ăl ʿamīmaẗi wa ăl ʿawāṭifi ăr raḥīmaẗi ăl ʿāliyaẗi ăl wāfiyaẗi min mawlā nā wa sayyidi nā qāḍī ăl quḍāẗi 
 <lb n="12"/>šayḫi šuyūḫi ăl ʿārifīna ʾasbaġa ăl lāhu taʿālà ẓilāla hu wa ḫatama bi ăṣ ṣāliḥāti 
 <lb n="13"/>ʾaʿmāla hu marsūm:un karīm:un ʾilà ăl ḥākimi bi ăl qudsi ăš šarīfi ʾayyada hu ăl lāhu taʿālà bi ăt tamakkuni bi bayʿi milki 
 <lb n="14"/>zawǧi ăl mamlūkaẗi ăl maḏkūraẗi ʿalà ḥukmi ăl farḍi ăṯ ṯābiti bi yadi ăl mamlūkaẗi li taǧida 
 <lb n="15"/>ăl mamlūkaẗu bi ḏālika ăl ʾiʿānaẗa ʿalà faqri hā wa ḍuʿfi ḥāli hā wa ʾawlādi hā 
 <lb n="16"/>ṣadaqaẗ:an ʿan mawlā nā wa sayyidi nā qāḍī ăl quḍāẗi wa ʿan salafi hi ʾanhati ăl mamlūkaẗu 
 <lb n="17"/>ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="18"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥdi hi wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in wa ʾāli hi wa ṣaḥbi hi wa sallama 
 <lb n="19"/>tamma 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  The slave
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  Sutayta, wife of Mūsā
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  al-Qudsī
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  In the name of God the Compassionate the Merciful
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  kisses the ground and reports that she is married to the aforementioned Mūsā al-Qudsī
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  and has a son by him called Aḥmad and a daughter called Sitt al-Banīn. For a period
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  of thirteen years he has been travelling in Yemen and (still) owns property in Jerusalem the Noble. The slave
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  has an entitlement to maintenance from him for that period, certified by Our Lord and Master, Aqḍā l-Quḍāt Shihāb
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  al-Dīn al-Bādisī l-Mālikī, may God the Exalted support him. The total of the maintenance is thirteen thousand dirhams.
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  Having become incapable of supporting herself and her two children, the slave petitions from the all-embracing
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  bounties and merciful benevolences, exalted and copious, of Our Lord and Master, Qāḍī l-Quḍāt,
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  Shaykh al-Shuyūkh of the Knowers, may God the Exalted lengthen his shadow and seal with good deeds
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  his acts, a gracious decree to the magistrate in Jerusalem the Noble, may God the Exalted support him, authorizing the sale of the property of
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  the aforementioned husband of the slave by virtue of the certified maintenance in the slave&#039;s possession, so that she can find
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  thereby assistance against her poverty and the weak circumstances of her children and herself
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  as a bounty from Our Lord and Master, Qāḍī l-Quḍāt, and his progeny. The slave reported
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  that. God be willing.
		 <lb n="18"/>
 	  Praise be to God alone. May God bless Our Lord Muḥammad, his family, and companions and grant them peace.
		 <lb n="19"/>
 	  The end.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
