<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="940" xml:id="Margoliouth_APRL_6_14" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Ryl.Arab. I VI 14 (= P.World p. 179)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Margoliouth_APRL_6_14</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113694</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="Grohmann 1"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بسم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحمن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحيم</supplied> 
<lb n="Margoliouth 1 = Grohmann 2"/>  حفظك اللّه يا أخي وعافاك وأبقاك كتبت إليك وأنا وما قبلي 
<lb n="Margoliouth 2 = Grohmann 3"/>  بحال عافية واللّه محمود وقد كتبت إليك غير كتاب لم أرا لك 
<lb n="Margoliouth 3 = Grohmann 4"/>  كتاب أختك في حقّي على ما فارقتني عليه وحلفت عليه في 
<lb n="Margoliouth 4 = Grohmann 5"/>  منزل أبو الحسن ثم خرجت فلم تصنع في ذلك قليل ولا كثير 
<lb n="Margoliouth 5 = Grohmann 6"/>  تعد التّملّي وتوعد مرّة بعد أخرى فلم أرا لذلك تحقيق شي 
<lb n="Margoliouth 6 = Grohmann 7"/>  فالله المستعان وما كان رأيي أكتب إليك بحرف واحد لولا 
<lb n="Margoliouth 7 = Grohmann 8"/>  خروج رسول يحيى وقد قدم غير واحد فلم أراك كتبت إلي 
<lb n="Margoliouth 8 = Grohmann 9"/>  شي وقد وجّهت إليك يحيى وهو وكيلي فيما عليك 
<lb n="Margoliouth 9 = Grohmann 10"/>  وعلى غيرك وصد<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">يقي</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> وخذ كتابك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ḥafiẓa ka ăl lāhu yā ʾaḫ ī wa ʿāfā ka wa ʾabqā ka katabtu ʾilay ka wa ʾanā wa mā qibal ī 
 <lb n="3"/>bi ḥāli ʿāfiyaẗ:in wa ăl lāhu maḥmūd:un wa qad katabtu ʾilay ka ġayra kitāb:in lam ʾarā la ka 
 <lb n="4"/>kitāba ʾuḫti ka fī ḥaqq ī ʿalà mā fāraqat nī ʿalay hi wa ḥalafat ʿalay hi fī 
 <lb n="5"/>manzili ʾabū ăl ḥasani ṯumma ḫaraǧat fa lam taṣnaʿ fī ḏālika qalīl wa lā kaṯīr 
 <lb n="6"/>taʿidu ăt tamallī wa tūʿidu marraẗ:an baʿda ʾuḫrà fa lam ʾarā li ḏālika taḥqīqa šayʾ:in 
 <lb n="7"/>fa ăl lāhu ăl mustaʿānu wa mā kāna raʾy ī ʾaktubu ʾilay ka bi ḥarf:in wāḥid:in law lā 
 <lb n="8"/>ḫurūǧu rasūli yaḥyà wa qad qadima ġayru wāḥid:in fa lam ʾarā ka katabta ʾilay ya 
 <lb n="9"/>šayʾ wa qad waǧǧahtu ʾilay ka yaḥyà wa huwa wakīl ī fī mā ʿalay ka 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ʿalà ġayri ka wa ṣadīq ī *** wa ḫuḏ kitāba ka 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		[In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!]
			<lb n="2"/>
		God guard thee, O my brother, and keep thee in health and preserve thee. I am writing to thee being with those about me
		May God protect thee, o my brother and give thee health. I am writing to thee myself and those about me being
			<lb n="3"/>
		in a state of good health, and God be praised! I have already written to thee more than one letter, but I cannot find, that thou hast written
		in good health. Thank God! I have written to you more than one letter but cannot find that you have
			<lb n="4"/>
		written to thy sister about my claim regarding the condition on which she has separated herself from me and to which she swore in the
		written to your sister about my claim in reference to the condition on which she left me and to which she swore,
			<lb n="5"/>
		dwelling-house of Abu&#039;l-Ḥasan, after which she went out and did not do in this matter little or much.
		in the house of Abu &#039;l-Ḥasan, after which she went out and did nothing in the matter small or great;
			<lb n="6"/>
		she constantly promises and threatens time after time, and of that I see no realization.
		She constantly promises and threatens time after time, but I have not yet seen any realisation at all.
			<lb n="7"/>
		God&#039;s help must be implored. It was not my idea to write to you a single letter of the alphabet had it not been
		So God&#039;s help may be implored. It was not my intention to write to thee a single letter, had it not been
			<lb n="8"/>
		that Yaḥyâ&#039;s messenger has gone out, and several have come, and I cannot find that thou hast written to me 
		that Yaḥya&#039;s messenger has gone out, and several have come, and I cannot find that you have written to me
			<lb n="9"/>
		at all. I have already sent Yaḥyâ to thee, and he is my agent for what thou owest
		at all. I have sent Yaḥya to you, and he is my agent for what is due to me from you
			<lb n="10"/>
		and others and my friend. | And take thy letter.
		and others, and [my] frie[nd ......] And take thy letter.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
