<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2339" xml:id="Margoliouth_Bodl_1" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Bodl.Arab. 1</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Margoliouth_Bodl_1</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  أبقاك اللّه وحفظك وأتم نعمه 
<lb n="2"/>  عليك وكرامته لك 
<lb n="3"/>  إنّي أبقاك اللّه لكراهتي للشّر تركت الكتاب 
<lb n="4"/>  إليك بما ظهر لي من بشر بن سعيد صاحب 
<lb n="5"/>  أبي علي ورجوت أن أصلح الأمر قبلي 
<lb n="6"/>  ولا تعلم به ولا يكون بينكم اختلاف 
<lb n="7"/>  ولم أكتب به إليك أبقاك اللّه حتّى لم أقدر على 
<lb n="8"/>  من معه وأنا يعلم اللّه من أكره النّاس 
<lb n="9"/>  لهذا وشبهه ولكنّي تقلّدت لك شيا لا 
<lb n="10"/>  أجد بدّا من القيام به 
<lb n="11"/>  ولم يزل أبقاك اللّه بشر بن سعيد منذ يوم قدمت 
<lb n="12"/>  كارها لمكاني ممالئ لإبرهيم بن حميد لما كانا 
<lb n="13"/>  فيه قبل قدومي ولما قد عملا به ممّا لو كشفا عنه 
<lb n="14"/>  افتضحا ولما كانا مجمعين عليه فيما بقي 
<lb n="15"/>  ولم يزل يدفعني من محاسبة إبرهيم ويتكلّم عنه 
<lb n="16"/>  كل ذلك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أو </lem><rdg resp="APD">أوازيه</rdg></app> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">أزيد </lem><rdg resp="APD">ø</rdg></app> وأسل إبرهيم عمّا أريد 
<lb n="17"/>  وأسل عنه غيره حتّى ورد على إبرهيم كتاب 
<lb n="18"/>  ذكر أنّه منك أعزّك اللّه يذكر فيه أنّك 
<lb n="19"/>  إنّما وجّهتني شريكا معه وأن يقيم في عمله 
<lb n="20"/>  فجرى بيني وبين إبرهيم في ذلك كلام وأعلمته أنّه 
<lb n="21"/>  لا يجوز لي العمل بكتابه إلّا أن يأتيني بكتاب 
<lb n="22"/>  منك فأنتهي إليه وأعمل به فدخل علي 
<lb n="23"/>  بشر بن سعيد في منزلي فأسمعني ما لم أكن 
<lb n="24"/>  واللّه أحتمله لصاحبه لو كان حاضر لأنّه 
<lb n="25"/>  يعرفني وأعرفه وقال لي قد كتب إلي ألّا 
<lb n="26"/>  أعامل إلّا واحد وأن إبرهيم مقر على ما 
<lb n="27"/>  كان وزعم أنّه يحول بيني وبين إبرهيم 
<lb n="28"/>  وخرج إلى حد لو لا أنّي أغضيت عليه لصرنا 
<lb n="29"/>  إلى القتال وأشر 
<lb n="30"/>  وبشر أبقاك اللّه وإبرهيم في موضع واحد 
<lb n="31"/>  في ليلهما ونهارهما ما يفترقان وهما حرصا على 
<lb n="32"/>  إفساد ما قدرا عليه إلّا أنّه ليس <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">هاهنا </lem><rdg resp="LS pure guess">هاذا</rdg></app> 
<lb n="33"/>  اليوم شي يخاف عليه إلّا هذه البقايا والقطن 
<lb n="34"/>  قد أحرز في البيوت ورسم عليه والأمر قبلنا 
<lb n="35"/>  أبقاك اللّه على ما أعلمتك ولولا كراهة 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu wa ḥafiẓa ka wa ʾatamma niʿama hu 
 <lb n="2"/>ʿalay ka wa karāmata hu la ka 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾin nī ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu li karāhat ī li š šarri taraktu ăl kitāba 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾilay ka bi mā ẓahara l ī min bišri bni saʿīd:in ṣāḥibi 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾabī ʿaliyy:in wa raǧawtu ʾan ʾuṣliḥa ăl ʾamra qibal ī 
 <lb n="6"/>wa lā taʿlamu bi hi wa lā yakūnu bayna kumu ĭḫtilāf:un 
 <lb n="7"/>wa lam ʾaktub bi hi ʾilay ka ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu ḥattà lam ʾaqdir ʿalà 
 <lb n="8"/>man maʿa hu wa ʾanā yaʿlamu ăl lāhu min ʾakrahi ăn nāsi 
 <lb n="9"/>li hāḏā wa šibhi hi wa lākin nī taqalladtu la ka šay:an lā 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾaǧidu budd:an mina ăl qiyāmi bi hi 
 <lb n="11"/>wa lam yazal ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu bišru bnu saʿīd:in munḏu yawmi qadimtu 
 <lb n="12"/>kārih:an li makān ī mumāliʾ li ʾibrāhīma bni ḥumayd:in li mā kānā 
 <lb n="13"/>fī hi qabla qudūm ī wa li mā qad ʿamilā bi hi mimmā law kašafā ʿan hu 
 <lb n="14"/>ĭftaḍaḥā wa li mā kānā muǧmiʿayni ʿalay hi fī mā baqiya 
 <lb n="15"/>wa lam yazal yadfaʿu nī min muḥāsabaẗi ʾibrāhīma wa yatakallamu ʿan hu 
 <lb n="16"/>kullu ḏālika ʾaw ʾuwāzī ø hi ʾazyadu ø wa ʾasalu ʾibrāhīma ʿammā ʾurīdu 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ʾasalu ʿan hu ġayra hu ḥattà warada ʿalà ʾibrāhīma kitāb:un 
 <lb n="18"/>ḏakara ʾanna hu min ka ʾaʿazza ka ăl lāhu yuḏkaru fī hi ʾanna ka 
 <lb n="19"/>ʾinnamā waǧǧahta nī šarīk:an maʿa hu wa ʾan yuqīma fī ʿamali hi 
 <lb n="20"/>fa ǧarà bayn ī wa bayna ʾibrāhīma fī ḏālika kalām:un wa ʾaʿlamtu hu ʾanna hu 
 <lb n="21"/>lā yaǧūzu l ī ăl ʿamalu bi kitābi hi ʾillā ʾan yaʾtiya nī bi kitāb:in 
 <lb n="22"/>min ka fa ʾantahī ʾilay hi wa ʾaʿmalu bi hi fa daḫala ʿalay ya 
 <lb n="23"/>bišru bnu saʿīd:in fī manzil ī fa ʾasmaʿa nī mā lam ʾakun 
 <lb n="24"/>wa ăl lāhi ʾaḥtamilu hu li ṣāḥibi hi law kāna ḥāḍir liʾanna hu 
 <lb n="25"/>yaʿrifu nī wa ʾaʿrifu hu wa qāla l ī qad kutiba ʾilay ya ʾallā 
 <lb n="26"/>ʾuʿāmila ʾillā wāḥid wa ʾanna ʾibrāhīma muqarr:un ʿalà mā 
 <lb n="27"/>kāna wa zaʿama ʾanna hu yaḥūlu bayn ī wa bayna ʾibrāhīma 
 <lb n="28"/>wa ḫaraǧa ʾilà ḥadd:in law lā ʾan nī ʾaġḍaytu ʿalay hi la ṣirnā 
 <lb n="29"/>ʾilà ăl qitāli wa ʾašarra 
 <lb n="30"/>wa bišr:un ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu wa ʾibrāhīmu fī mawḍiʿ:in wāḥid:in 
 <lb n="31"/>fī layli himā wa nahāri himā mā yaftariqāni wa humā ḥaraṣā ʿalà 
 <lb n="32"/>ʾifsādi mā qadarā ʿalay hi ʾillā ʾanna hu laysa hāhunā hāḏā 
 <lb n="33"/>ăl yawma šayʾ:un yuḫāfu ʿalay hi ʾillā hāḏihi ăl baqāyā wa ăl quṭnu 
 <lb n="34"/>qad ʾuḥriza fī ăl buyūti wa rusima ʿalay hi wa ăl ʾamru qibala nā 
 <lb n="35"/>ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu ʿalà mā ʾaʿlamtu ka wa law lā karāhaẗu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		God preserve you and keep you, and perfect his mercy
			<lb n="2"/>
		and his grace upon you and to you!
			<lb n="3"/>
		Owing (God preserve you) to my dislike of mischief, I forbore to write
			<lb n="4"/>
		to you concerning the behaviour of Bishr ibn Saʿīd, the friend
			<lb n="5"/>
		of Abu ʿAlī, hoping to mend matters by my own exertions,
			<lb n="6"/>
		without your knowing thereof, and without any difference arising between you.
			<lb n="7"/>
		So I did not write about it to you (God preserve you) till I was unable to deal with
			<lb n="8"/>
		with his companions. God knows that I dislike
			<lb n="9"/>
		this and all similar things as much as any man; however I have undertaken a charge for you,
			<lb n="10"/>
		which I am bound to maintain.
			<lb n="11"/>
		From the day I arrived Bishr Ibn Saʿīd (God preserve you) has not ceased
			<lb n="12"/>
		opposing me and plotting with Ibrāhīm Ibn Ḥumayd according to their
			<lb n="13"/>
		previous arrangement, made before my arrival, and conduct which, if they revealed it,
			<lb n="14"/>
		would bring both of them to disgrace; and their understanding for the future.
			<lb n="15"/>
		He did not cease to dissuade me from reckoning with Ibrāhīm, and defending him.
			<lb n="16"/>
		This, or more, went on, [footnote: Or perhaps &#039;all this I faced &#039;] and all the time I was questioning Ibrāhīm as I pleased,
			<lb n="17"/>
		and asking others about him, till a letter came to Ibrāhīm,
			<lb n="18"/>
		which he said came from you (God bless you), stating that
			<lb n="19"/>
		you had sent me merely to be his partner, while he remained in his government.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Some words passed between Ibrāhīm and me about this, and I informed him that
			<lb n="21"/>
		I could no act according to that letter, unless he produced a letter
			<lb n="22"/>
		from you, which I should obey, and according to which I should act. Thereupon
			<lb n="23"/>
		Bishr Ibn Saʿīd paid me a visit at my house, and used language which I should not
			<lb n="24"/>
		have endured from his master, by heaven, had he been present; for
			<lb n="25"/>
		knows me, and I know him. He said he had received orders
			<lb n="26"/>
		to deal only with one person, and that Ibrāhīm remained
			<lb n="27"/>
		in his post; and that he would come between me and Ibrāhīm.
			<lb n="28"/>
		Indeed, he went so far, that had I not been lenient with him, we should
			<lb n="29"/>
		have come to blows or worse.
			<lb n="30"/>
		Now Bishr (God preserve you) and Ibrāhīm are in one place
			<lb n="31"/>
		day and night, inseparable. They were anxious to do
			<lb n="32"/>
		any harm they could, only
			<lb n="33"/>
		at present there is no mischief to be feared, except for the remnants. For the cotton
			<lb n="34"/>
		is housed and sealed; but things with us are
			<lb n="35"/>
		as I have told you (God preserve you), and were it not for my dislike -
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
