<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="919" xml:id="Margoliouth_APRL_1_5" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Ryl.Arab. I I 05 (= P.World p. 171)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Margoliouth_APRL_1_5</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113678</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="2"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="3"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="4"/>  من سرورك به وموقعه منك 
<lb n="5"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تقدم </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann”">تقدّم</rdg></app> علينا وإلى ولا خبر عند كتابى 
<lb n="6"/>  فإذا وقع عندنا خبر خبر كتبت 
<lb n="7"/>  به تقدم علينا وإلى ولا خبر كتابى عند 
<lb n="8"/>  إليك فإذا وقع عندنا خبر كتبت 
<lb n="9"/>  وإن المزرعين به إليك شا سريعا 
<lb n="10"/>  في الزّرع بأسفل الأرض 
<lb n="11"/>  الكور لهم الكور قد تسجّلوا لهم وإن ابنتي 
<lb n="12"/>  زوجها دخلت على زوجها 
<lb n="13"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="14"/>  وقد كنت كتبت الكتاب قبل اليوم لأبعث به حين <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ورد</supplied> قد 
<lb n="15"/>  ولاية حوي <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/>     
<lb n="16"/>  وقد كنت كتبت الكتاب قبل اليوم لأبعث به 
<lb n="17"/>  بن ولاية حوي بن حوي على الصّلاة  والخراج   
<lb n="18"/>  العمّال بإشخاصهم من العراقين أحببت إعلامك ذلك ذلك 
<lb n="19"/>  منه على علم وإنّما قرّت ولايته يوم الأحد  
<lb n="20"/>  لثلث إلى العمّال بإشخاصهم من العراقين أحببت إعلامك ذلك   
<lb n="21"/>  وقد وقد نقلت التوابيت 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** 
 <lb n="2"/>*** 
 <lb n="3"/>*** 
 <lb n="4"/>min surūri ka bi hi wa mawqiʿi hi min ka 
 <lb n="5"/>taqaddama tqdm ʿalay nā wa ʾilay ya wa lā ḫabara ʿinda kitāb ī 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾilay ka fa ʾiḏā waqaʿa ʿinda nā ḫabar:un katabtu 
 <lb n="7"/>bi hi ʾilay ka sarīʿ:an ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu wa ăl qamḥu ʿinda nā 
 <lb n="8"/>ṯamāniyaẗu waybāt:in wa niṣf:un wa ăš šaʿīru ṯalāṯaẗu ʾarādiba 
 <lb n="9"/>wa ʾinna ăl muzriʿīna ʿinda nā qad waḍaʿū ʾaydiya hum 
 <lb n="10"/>fī ăz zarʿi bi ʾasfali ăl ʾarḍi 
 <lb n="11"/>wa ʾinna ʿummāla ăl kuwari qad tasaǧǧalū la hum wa ʾinna ĭbnat ī 
 <lb n="12"/>qad daḫalat ʿalà zawǧi hā 
 <lb n="13"/>*** 
 <lb n="14"/>wa qad kuntu katabtu ăl kitāba qabla ăl yawmi li ʾabʿaṯa bi hi ḥīna warada ʿalay nā 
 <lb n="15"/>wilāyaẗu ḥuwayyi bni ḥuwayy:in ʿalà ăṣ ṣalāẗi wa ăl ḫarāǧi 
 <lb n="16"/>wa qad waliya bnu malīḥa ăz zimāma wa ăl ḫarāǧa wa ʾabū ʿubaydaẗa 
 <lb n="17"/>bnu ʿuqbaẗa bni nāfiʿ:in ʿalà ăṣ ṣalāẗi wa ăl ḫarāǧi wa qad kataba ḥuwayy:un kitāba hu 
 <lb n="18"/>ʾilà ăl ʿummāli bi ʾišḫāṣi him mina ăl ʿirāqayni ʾaḥbabtu ʾiʿlāma ka ḏālika 
 <lb n="19"/>li takūna min hu ʿalà ʿilm:in wa ʾinnamā qarrat wilāyaẗu hu yawma ăl ʾaḥadi 
 <lb n="20"/>li ṯalāṯ:in ḫalawna min ramaḍāna wa lam yakūn ʿinda nā baʿda hu mā naktubu bi hi 
 <lb n="21"/>ʾilay ka wa qad nuqilati ăt tawābītu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
			<lb n="2"/>
			<lb n="3"/>
			<lb n="4"/>
		Thy delight in him and the place he holds with thee,
		your delight in him and the place he holds with you
			<lb n="5"/>
		| and I have no news to write
		it has come (?) to us and to me (?) while I have no news to write
			<lb n="6"/>
		to thee, and if we get any news I will write
		to you, and if we get any news I will write
			<lb n="7"/>
		it to thee speedily, if God wills. Wheat is with us
		it to you speedily, if God will. Wheat is with us
			<lb n="8"/>
		eight waibahs and a half and barley three ardebs.
		eight waibas (= 1 1/3 artaba) and a half (per dirham) and barley three artabas (per dirham)
			<lb n="9"/>
		And the cultivators have put their hands
		and the tenants have put their hands
			<lb n="10"/>
		on the crops in the Delta,
		on the crops in the lower part of the country,
			<lb n="11"/>
		and the (local) finance directors have entered (the contracts of lease) for them in the registers. And my daughter
		and the officials of the districts have registered for them. And my daughter
			<lb n="12"/>
		has already cohabited with her husband
		has cohabited with her husband
			<lb n="13"/>
			<lb n="14"/>
		I had already written the letter the day before (intending) to dispatch it, when we learned
		Now I had written the letter the day before intending to send it when we learned
			<lb n="15"/>
		that Ḥuwayy b. Ḥuwayy had been appointed minister of prayer and kharaj:
		that Ḥuwayy ibn Ḥuwayy had been appointed governor of prayer and impost
			<lb n="16"/>
		and Ibn Malîḥ has just been appointed minister of control and impost, and Abû ʿUbaida
		now Ibn Malīḥ was appointed minister of control and kharaj and Abu ʿUbaidah
			<lb n="17"/>
		b. ʿUqbah b. Nāfiʿ of prayer and kharaj. And Ḥuwayy has written his letter
		ibn ʿUqba ibn Nâfiʿ of prayer and impost. And Ḥuwayy has written his letter
			<lb n="18"/>
		to the local finance directors summoning them from the two ʿIrâqs. I should like to inform thee thereof
		to the officials bidding them be brought from the two Iraqs. I have thought proper to inform you of this
			<lb n="19"/>
		that you might be aware of it. His appointment was only confirmed on Saturday
		that you mightest be aware of it. His appointment was only confirmed on Sunday, 
			<lb n="20"/>
		the third of Ramaḍan. We have nothing more after this to write
		when three nights had passed of Ramaḍân. We have nothing more after this to write
			<lb n="21"/>
		to thee, while the water-wheels have already been transferred.
		to you. And the tabuts have been transferred
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
