<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="938" xml:id="Margoliouth_APRL_6_6" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Ryl.Arab. I VI 06 (= P.World p. 178)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Margoliouth_APRL_6_6</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113693</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann”">قد</rdg></app> فهمت كتابك وقد رددت 
<lb n="3"/>  إلـ]ـيك العشر <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">دننر </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann”">دننير</rdg></app> فادفعها 
<lb n="4"/>  إلى] أبي الحسن مع العشرين إردب 
<lb n="5"/>  قمح وقد رددت إليك القرض 
<lb n="6"/>  على حاله فإن سألك فأعلمه 
<lb n="7"/>  أن رسولك أصابني قد دفعت 
<lb n="8"/>  وأن رسول عبد الخلق جاك 
<lb n="9"/>  لتطلّقه القمح وحرّق رقعتي 
<lb n="10"/>  إذا أقرأتها إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="11"/>  فإن قبل القمح مع الدّننر وألّا 
<lb n="12"/>  فرّد القمح إلى وليّك وابعث 
<lb n="13"/>  إلى الدّننر مع أوّل من يخرج إلينا 
<lb n="14"/>  إن شا اللّه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>*** qad fahimtu kitāba ka wa qad radadtu 
 <lb n="3"/>ʾilay ka ăl ʿašra danānira danānīra fa ĭdfaʿ hā 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾilà ʾabī ăl ḥasani maʿa ăl ʿišrīna ʾirdabb 
 <lb n="5"/>qamḥ wa qad radadtu ʾilay ka ăl qarḍa 
 <lb n="6"/>ʿalà ḥāli hi fa ʾin saʾala ka fa ʾaʿlim hu 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾanna rasūla ka ʾaṣāba nī qad dafaʿtu 
 <lb n="8"/>wa ʾanna rasūla ʿabdi ăl ḫāliqi ǧāʾa ka 
 <lb n="9"/>li tuṭalliqa hu ăl qamḥa wa ḥarriq ruqʿat ī 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾiḏā ʾaqraʾta hā ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="11"/>fa ʾin qabila ăl qamḥa maʿa ăd danāniri wa ʾillā 
 <lb n="12"/>fa ruddi ăl qamḥa ʾilà waliyyi ka wa ĭbʿaṯ 
 <lb n="13"/>ʾilay ya ăd danānira maʿa ʾawwali man yaḫruǧu ʾilay nā 
 <lb n="14"/>ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the Name &amp;c.
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!
			<lb n="2"/>
		I [already] understood thy letter and I return
		I understand your letter and I return
			<lb n="3"/>
		[to] thee the ten dînârs. So hand them over
		to you the ten dinars and do you hand the over
			<lb n="4"/>
		to Abu &#039;l-Ḥasan with the twenty ardebs
		to Abu&#039;l Ḥasan with the twenty artabas
			<lb n="5"/>
		of wheat; so I have returned to thee the loan  
		of wheat; so I have returned to you the loan
			<lb n="6"/>
		in its condition; and if he asks thee, then inform him  
		in its condition; and if he asks you, then inform him
			<lb n="7"/>
		that thy messenger found me having already paid,
		that your messenger found me having already paid,
			<lb n="8"/>
		and that the messenger of ʿAbd al-Khâliq came to thee
		and that the messenger of ʿAbd al-Khaliq came to you
			<lb n="9"/>
		that thou mightest give him the wheat; and burn my letter
		that you might give him the wheat; and burn my letter
			<lb n="10"/>
		when thou hast read it, please God.
		when you have read it, please God.
			<lb n="11"/>
		And if he shall accept the wheat with the dinars - otherwise
			<lb n="12"/>
		return the wheat to thy friend and send
		return the wheat to your friend and send
			<lb n="13"/>
		the dinars to me with the first person who comes out to us,
			<lb n="14"/>
		if God wills.
		please God.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
