<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="933" xml:id="Margoliouth_APRL_6_15" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Ryl.Arab. I VI 15 (= P.World p. 175 b)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Margoliouth_APRL_6_15</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM">113690</idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بسم</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">اللّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحمن</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّحيم</supplied> 
<lb n="2"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">كتبت</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">إليك</supplied> عن سلامة والحمد للّه وأنا أرجو أن 
<lb n="4"/>  أدخل إلى يومين ولا تدع أن تشتري حوائج رمضان والحمد لـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـلّه</supplied> 
<lb n="5"/>  على سلامتك الّتي حاطتكم في عافية فلا يكون في قلوبكم 
<lb n="6"/>  غم وأبو كريم يقريكم سلام كثيرا وأنا أوجّه لكم 
<lb n="7"/>  من بيتنا إليكم ولا تدع أن <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> الجارية في بدرقة 
<lb n="8"/>  على الاجران فتنقلوا البر إلى المنزل وتصيروه في البيت 
<lb n="9"/>  الدّاخل والملبّن الدّاخل حتّى يقام لكم عند الكندوج 
<lb n="10"/>  الكعبي <expan><ex>بسم</ex> <ex>اللّه</ex> <ex>الرّحمن</ex> <ex>الرّحيم</ex></expan> أخوه مرتضى 
<lb n="11"/>  حتّى نكتري لكم من يصلحه واقروا أختكم السّلام كثيرا 
<lb n="12"/>  ونحن ندخل شا قريب اللّه شا اللّه وابعث الجارية إلى 
<lb n="13"/>  الإسكاف حتّى تروح على الخف واحفظي السّلعة 
<lb n="14"/>  مع ما معك اقبضوا منّي أفضل السّلام والمنّة <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ونسل </lem><rdg resp="“Grohmann”">ونسئل</rdg></app> 
<lb n="15"/>  يكن عندكم كثير السّلم 
<lb n="16"/>  أبقاك اللّه وحفظك 
<lb n="17"/>  وأمتع بك 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>*** 
 <lb n="3"/>katabtu ʾilay ka ʿan salāmaẗ:in wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa ʾanā ʾarǧū ʾan 
 <lb n="4"/>ʾadḫula ʾilà yawmayni wa lā tadaʿ ʾan taštariya ḥawāʾiǧa ramaḍāna wa ăl ḥamdu li ăl lāhi 
 <lb n="5"/>ʿalà salāmati ka ăllatī ḥāṭat kum fī ʿāfiyaẗ:in fa lā yakūn fī qulūbi kum 
 <lb n="6"/>ġamm:un wa ʾabū karīm:in yuqrī kum salām kaṯīr:an wa ʾanā ʾuwaǧǧihu la kum 
 <lb n="7"/>min bayti nā ʾilay kum wa lā tadaʿ ʾan *** ăl ǧāriyaẗa fī badraqaẗ:in 
 <lb n="8"/>ʿalà ăl ʾaǧrāni fa tanqulū ăl burra ʾilà ăl manzili wa tuṣīrū hu fī ăl bayti 
 <lb n="9"/>ăd dāḫili wa ăl mulabbani ăd dāḫili ḥattà yuqāma la kum ʿinda ăl kandūǧi 
 <lb n="10"/>mstḥm wa ġaṭṭū hu kaṯīr:an wa ĭbnū ḥawālay hi ḥayṭ waqt 
 <lb n="11"/>ḥattà naktarī la kum man yaṣluḥu hu wa ʾaqrū ʾuḫta kumu ăs salāma kaṯīr:an 
 <lb n="12"/>wa naḥnu nadḫulu ʾilà qarīb:in ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu wa ĭbʿaṯi ăl ǧāriyaẗa ʾilà 
 <lb n="13"/>ăl ʾiskāfi ḥattà tarūḥa ʿalà ăl ḫuffi wa ĭḥfaẓī ăs silʿaẗa 
 <lb n="14"/>maʿa mā maʿa ki ĭqbiḍū min nī ʾafḍala ăs salāmi wa ăl minnaẗa wa nasalu nasʾalu 
 <lb n="15"/>yakun ʿinda kum kaṯīru ăs salāmi 
 <lb n="16"/>ʾabqā ka ăl lāhu wa ḥafiẓa ka 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ʾamtaʿa bi ka 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		[In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful!]
			<lb n="2"/>
			<lb n="3"/>
		I am writing being, thank God, in good health, and I hope to
		[I am writing to thee] in good health, praise be to God, and I hope that
			<lb n="4"/>
		be home within two days. Do not fail to buy the articles for Ramaḍân, and praise be to God
		come home by two days. Do not fail to buy the necessities of Ramaḍan and thank God
			<lb n="5"/>
		for thy safety which has kept thee in good health. Let there not be in your hearts  
		for your safety which has kept you in good health. Let there not be in your hearts
			<lb n="6"/>
		grief. And Abû Karîm sends thee copious greetings. And I am sending 
		grief. And Abu Karim sends you copious greeting. And I am sending ...
			<lb n="7"/>
		from our house to thee. And do not fail to [send?] the slave-girl with escort to
		from our house to you. And do not fail to send the slave-girl with escort to
			<lb n="8"/>
		the threshingfloors and to remove the wheat to the dwelling and put it in the inner
		the threshingfloors and to remove the wheat to the dwellinghouse and put it in the inner  
			<lb n="9"/>
		chamber and the inner brickwork so that it may be well kept for you in the vessel holding
		chamber and the inner brickwork so that it may be well kept in the vessel which holds grain.
			<lb n="10"/>
		And cover it well and build a temporary wall round it
		grain. And cover it well and build a temporary wall round it
			<lb n="11"/>
		until we hire someone to put it right for you. And convey copious greetings to your sister.  
		until we hire some one to put it right for you. And convey copious greeting to your sister
			<lb n="12"/>
		and we shall come home soon, please God. And send the slave-girl to
		And we shall come home soon, please God. And send the slave-girl to  
			<lb n="13"/>
		the cobbler that she may go about on shoes. And take care of the goods
			<lb n="14"/>
		with what thou hast in possession. Take from me the best of greetings and thanks and we ask
		with what you have got. Take from me the best of greetings and thanks and we ask
			<lb n="15"/>
		let there be with you abundant peace.
			<lb n="16"/>
		God preserve and protect thee
		May God preserve thee and protect thee,
			<lb n="17"/>
		and cause us to profit by thee.
		and may He cause us to profit by thee!
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
