<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2381" xml:id="Richards_FatimidPetition_2a" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.RichardsFatimidPetition 2a</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Richards_FatimidPetition_2a</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  <gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="character" /> متولّي الحرب المذكور بحمل 
<lb n="2"/>  رافعيها فيما سألوه على ما جرت به عادتهم 
<lb n="3"/>  وأن يكون نزوله بحيث مستقر من تقدّم من الولاة 
<lb n="4"/>  ولا يمكّن العربان ولا غيرهم من التّعرّض إلى دياراتهم 
<lb n="5"/>  وموضع صلواتهم ورعاية ما يخصّهم 
<lb n="6"/>  وحفظهم وصونهم ومنع من يتطرّق إليهم بأذيّة 
<lb n="7"/>  وأن يعتمد ذلك كافّة الولاة والمتصرّفين و<gap reason="illegible" extent="8" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="8"/>  وأن يقر بأيديهم بعد العمل به 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>********** mutawallī ăl ḥarbi ăl maḏkūr bi ḥamli 
 <lb n="2"/>rāfiʿī hā fī mā saʾalū hu ʿalà mā ǧarat bi hi ʿādatu hum 
 <lb n="3"/>wa ʾan yakūna nuzūlu hu bi ḥayṯu mustaqarru man taqaddama mina ăl wulāẗi 
 <lb n="4"/>wa lā yumakkina ăl ʿurbāna wa lā ġayra hum mina ăt taʿarruḍi ʾilà diyārāti him 
 <lb n="5"/>wa mawḍiʿi ṣalawāti him wa riʿāyaẗi mā yaḫuṣṣu hum 
 <lb n="6"/>wa ḥifẓi him wa ṣawni him wa manʿi man yataṭarraqu ʾilay him bi ʾaḏiyyaẗ:in 
 <lb n="7"/>wa ʾan yaʿtamida ḏālika kāffaẗu ăl wulāẗi wa ăl mutaṣarrifīna wa ******** 
 <lb n="8"/>wa ʾan yaqirra bi ʾaydī him baʿda ăl ʿamali bi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		The aforementioned military governor [is ordered] to treat
			<lb n="2"/>
		the petitioners in the matter of their request according to what has been customary for them in the past
			<lb n="3"/>
		and that his residence should be where former governors have established themselves
			<lb n="4"/>
		and that he should not allow the Bedouins or others to interfere with their [the monks&#039; buildings]
			<lb n="5"/>
		or their place of worship and he should respect their property,
			<lb n="6"/>
		protect and guard them and prevent any who would bring harm to them
			<lb n="7"/>
		and [it is ordered] that all governors, officials and ...... should obey this
			<lb n="8"/>
		and that it [this document] should remain in their hands after it has been acted upon.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
