<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2488" xml:id="Richards_WrittenDocuments_04" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.RichardsWrittenDocuments 04</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Richards_WrittenDocuments_04</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  يقول علی بن محمّد بن علی طباطبا الحسنی أن علي وعندي وفی 
 <lb n="3"/>  قبلي لسيّدي وشيخي أبو الحسن الصّيرفی أدام اللّه علوّه من العين 
 <lb n="4"/>  الوازن المصری دينار واحد أدفع ذلك إليه يوم عشرين 
 <lb n="5"/>  من شهر شعبان من هذه السّنة ويلتزم علي شهد بذلك 
 <lb n="6"/>  بخطّه في شهر شعبان سنة اثنتين وثلثين وأربع مائة 
 <lb n="between lines 4 and 5"/>  ولا أحتج عليه فيه بحجّة ولا بسبب 
 <lb n="above line 1, right"/>  شهدت وللّه المپه 
 <lb n="centre"/>  شهدت والحمد للّه علی كل حال 
 <lb n="left"/>  شهدت والحمد للّه علی پعمه 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>yaqūlu ʿaliyyu bnu muḥammadi bni ʿaliyy:in ṭabāṭabā ăl ḥasaniyyu ʾanna ʿalay ya wa ʿind ī wa fī 
 <lb n="3"/>qibal ī li sayyid ī wa šayḫ ī ʾabū ăl ḥasani ăṣ ṣayrafiyyi ʾadāma ăl lāhu ʿuluwwa hu mina ăl ʿayni 
 <lb n="4"/>ăl wāzini ăl miṣriyyi dīnār:un wāḥid:un ʾadfaʿu ḏālika ʾilay hi yawma ʿišrīna 
 <lb n="5"/>min šahri šaʿbāna min hāḏihi ăs sanaẗi wa yaltazimu ʿalay ya šahida bi ḏālika 
 <lb n="6"/>bi ḫaṭṭi hi fī šahri šaʿbāna sanaẗa ĭṯnatayni wa ṯalāṯīna wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="7"/>wa lā ʾaḥtaǧǧu ʿalay hi fī hi bi ḥuǧǧaẗ:in wa lā bi sabab:in 
 <lb n="8"/>šahidtu wa li l lāhi ăl minnaẗu 
 <lb n="9"/>šahidtu wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ʿalà kulli ḥāl:in 
 <lb n="10"/>šahidtu wa ăl ḥamdu li ăl lāhi ʿalà niʿami hi 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God the Merciful, the Compassionate.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  ʿAli ibn Muhammad ibn ʿAli ibn Tabataba al-Hasani declares: I owe to, and hold in my possession for,
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  the respected master, Abu al-Hasan the money-changer (may God continue his exaltedness), in cash
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  of full-weight Egyptian currency, one dinar, which I will pay to him on the twentieth day
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  of the month of Shaʿban of this year. This is a legal undertaking. He bore witness to that
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  in his own hand [herewith] in the month of Shaʿban, in the year four hundred and thirty-two
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  and I will not have recourse to any argument or pretext against him in this matter.
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  I bore witness, and to God is the favour.
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  I bore witness, and praise be to God in every circumstance.
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  I bore witness, and praise be to God for his blessings.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
