<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2359" xml:id="Richards_FatimidPetitions_1" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.RichardsFatimidPetition 1</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Richards_FatimidPetitions_1</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="tag not numbered"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="tag i"/>  مرسوم <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> ومنع أمـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـير</supplied> <gap reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="character" /> 
<lb n="tag ii"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـعرب 
<lb n="tag iii"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="tag iv"/>  خليفتيّة <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
<lb n="1"/>  المماليك 
<lb n="2"/>  جماعة الرّهبان المقيمين بدير طور سينا 
<lb n="3"/>  بالوادي المقدّس 
<lb n="4"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="5"/>  خلّد اللّه تعالى ملك المجلس السّامي السّيّدي الأجلّي الجيوشي 
<lb n="6"/>  السّيفي النّاصري الكافلي الهادي وعضد به الدّين وأمتع بطول بقائه أمير المومپپن 
<lb n="7"/>  وأدام قدرته وأعلى كلمته المماليك يقبّلون الأرض وينهون أن <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">لهم</supplied> 
<lb n="8"/>  سجلّات شريفة كريمة مضمّنة صيانتهم وإعزاز جانبهم وتحذيرا لولاة الحرب 
<lb n="9"/>  والعربان من دخول ديرهم والاستيلا على أموالهم الّتي بها مادّة حياتهم وحياة 
<lb n="10"/>  من يطرقهم من الحجّاج والمسافرين وغيرهم ولمّا أنعم على الأمير بن الفرماوي 
<lb n="11"/>  ولاية الحصون الطّوريّة اجتمع به المولّدون من العربان العائذيّين وهم عسيكر 
<lb n="12"/>  وعالي ورحم ومريبط وحوير وبنو عمّهم وحسّنوا له الدّخول إلى الدّير والمقام فيه 
<lb n="13"/>  وإذا تم له ذلك فهو والعربان ينهبونه ويخربونه والعادة جارية بأن 
<lb n="14"/>  يقيم الوالي في موضع مستغل السّلطان أعز اللّه نصره وخلّد أيّامه وملكه 
<lb n="15"/>  وهو السّاحل ويحفظ المنقول ويحتاط عليه للسّلطان خلّد اللّه ملكه وأيّامه والمماليك 
<lb n="16"/>  قد خافت نفوسهم من موجب الضّرر عليهم وعلى الدّير المذكور ويكون ذلك سببا لنهبه وخرابه وهم 
<lb n="17"/>  يجدّدون تقبيل الأرض ويسئلون ويضرعون في الأخذ بأيديهم لوجه اللّه تعالى وخروج الأمر 
<lb n="18"/>  العالي زاده اللّه نفاذا ومضا إلى متولّي الباب العزيز الطاهر خلّد اللّه شرفه 
<lb n="19"/>  بإحضار الأمير المذكور والعربان المقدّم ذكرهم وأخذ خطوطهم مضمّنة القسامة الشّريفة أنّهم لا 
<lb n="20"/>  يتعرّضون للدّير ولا يقيمون فيه ولا يقربونه فإن الأسقف لمّا خرج من الدّير المذكور سد 
<lb n="21"/>  الرّهبان أبوابه بالحجارة ولا سبيل لهم إلى فتحه وإذا وصل الوالي يلتمس منهم فتحه ولا 
<lb n="22"/>  يمكنهم ذلك ولا يقدرون عليه فيودى الأمر إلي إحَنٍ بينهم وذحول أنهوا ذلك ليحيط العلم به 
<lb n="23"/>  وللآرا العالية فضل <gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="character" /> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">في</unclear> ذلك إن شا اللّه عز وجل الحمد للّه وحده وصلواته على محمّد وآله وسلامه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>*** 
 <lb n="2"/>marsūm *** wa manʿ ʾamīr ***** 
 <lb n="3"/>*** ăl ʿarab 
 <lb n="4"/>*** 
 <lb n="5"/>ḫalīfatiyyaẗ *** 
 <lb n="6"/>ăl mamālīku 
 <lb n="7"/>ǧamāʿaẗu ăr ruhbāni ăl muqīmīna bi dayri ṭūri sīnā 
 <lb n="8"/>bi ăl wādī ăl muqaddasi 
 <lb n="9"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="10"/>ḫallada ăl lāhu taʿālà mulka ăl maǧlisi ăs sāmī ăs sayyidiyyi ăl ʾaǧalliyyi ăl ǧuyūšiyyi 
 <lb n="11"/>ăs sayfiyyi ăn nāṣiriyyi ăl kāfiliyyi ăl hādī wa ʿaḍada bi hi ăd dīna wa ʾamtaʿa bi ṭūli baqāʾi hi ʾamīra ăl muʾminīna 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ʾadāma qudrata hu wa ʾaʿlà kalimata hu ăl mamālīku yuqabbilūna ăl ʾarḍa wa yunhūna ʾanna la hum 
 <lb n="13"/>siǧillāt:un šarīfaẗ:un karīmaẗ:un muḍamminaẗ:un ṣiyānata hum wa ʾiʿzāza ǧānibi him wa taḥḏīr:an li wulāẗi ăl ḥarbi 
 <lb n="14"/>wa ăl ʿurbāni min duḫūli dayri him wa ăli ĭstīlāʾi ʿalà ʾamwāli himi ăllatī bi hā māddaẗi ḥayāti him wa ḥayāẗi 
 <lb n="15"/>man yaṭruqu hum mina ăl ḥuǧǧāǧi wa ăl musāfirīna wa ġayri him wa lammā ʾunʿima ʿalà ăl ʾamīri bni ăl faramāwiyyi 
 <lb n="16"/>wilāyaẗa ăl ḥuṣūni ăṭ ṭūriyyaẗi ĭǧtamaʿa bi hi ăl muwalladūna mina ăl ʿurbāni ăl ʿāʾiḏiyyīna wa hum ʿusaykiru 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ʿālī wa raḥim:un wa muraybiṭu wa ḥuwayr:un wa banū ʿammi him wa ḥassanū la hu ăd duḫūla ʾilà ăd dayri wa ăl maqāma fī hi 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʾiḏā tamma la hu ḏālika fa huwa wa ăl ʿurbānu yanhabūna hu wa yuḫribūna hu wa ăl ʿādaẗu ǧāriyaẗ:un bi ʾan 
 <lb n="19"/>yuqīma ăl wālī fī mawḍiʿi mustaġalli ăs sulṭāni ʾaʿazza ăl lāhu naṣra hu wa ḫallada ʾayyāma hu wa mulka hu 
 <lb n="20"/>wa huwa ăs sāḥilu wa yaḥfaẓa ăl manqūla wa yaḥtāṭa ʿalay hi li ăs sulṭāni ḫallada ăl lāhu mulka hu wa ʾayyāma hu wa ăl mamālīku 
 <lb n="21"/>qad ḫāfat nufūsu hum min mūǧibi ăḍ ḍarari ʿalay him wa ʿalà ăd dayri ăl maḏkūri wa yakūnu ḏālika sabab:an li nahbi hi wa ḫarābi hi wa hum 
 <lb n="22"/>yuǧaddidūna taqbīla ăl ʾarḍi wa yasʾalūna wa yaḍraʿūna fī ăl ʾaḫḏi bi ʾaydī him li waǧhi ăl lāhi taʿālà wa ḫurūǧi ăl ʾamri 
 <lb n="23"/>ăl ʿālī zāda hu ăl lāhu nafāḏ:an wa maḍāʾ:an ʾilà mutawallī ăl bābi ăl ʿazīzi ăṭ ṭāhiri ḫallada ăl lāhu šarafa hu 
 <lb n="24"/>bi ʾiḥḍāri ăl ʾamīri ăl maḏkūri wa ăl ʿurbāni ăl muqaddami ḏikru hum wa ʾaḫḏi ḫuṭūṭi him muḍamminaẗi ăl qasāmaẗi ăš šarīfaẗi ʾanna hum lā 
 <lb n="25"/>yataʿarraḍūna li ăd dayri wa lā yuqīmūna fī hi wa lā yaqrubūna hu fa ʾinna ăl ʾusqufa lammā ḫaraǧa mina ăd dayri ăl maḏkūri sadda 
 <lb n="26"/>ăr ruhbānu ʾabwāba hu bi ăl ḥiǧāraẗi wa lā sabīla la hum ʾilà fatḥi hi wa ʾiḏā waṣala ăl wālī yaltamisu min hum fatḥa hu wa lā 
 <lb n="27"/>yumkinu hum ḏālika wa lā yaqdirūna ʿalay hi fa yuʾaddī ăl ʾamru ʾilà ʾiḥan:in bayna hum wa ḏuḥūl:in ʾanhaw ḏālika li yuḥīṭa ăl ʿilmu bi hi 
 <lb n="28"/>wa li l ʾārāʾi ăl ʿāliyaẗi faḍlu ********** fī ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu ʿazza wa ǧalla ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥdi hi wa ṣalawātu hu ʿalà muḥammad:in wa ʾāli hi wa salāmu hu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		&#034;There are a few Greek letters at the beginning, for which I can provide no sense&#034;
			<lb n="2"/>
		A decree ... keeping the amir of ... from ...
			<lb n="3"/>
		... the Arabs
			<lb n="4"/>
			<lb n="5"/>
		of the Caliph ...
			<lb n="6"/>
		The slaves
			<lb n="7"/>
		the community of monks who dwell in the monastery of Mount Sinai
			<lb n="8"/>
		in the Holy Valley.
			<lb n="9"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate.
			<lb n="10"/>
		May God Almighty perpetuate the dominion of the exalted seat, the most excellent Lord, Commander of the Armies,
			<lb n="11"/>
		Sword of Religion, the Defender, the Protector, the True Guide and support religion through him and grant the Commander of the Faithful enjoyment of his long life
			<lb n="12"/>
		and continue his power everlastingly and exalt his word. The slaves kiss the earth and report that they possess
			<lb n="13"/>
		noble and gracious decrees containing (orders for) their protection and respect for them and warning military governors
			<lb n="14"/>
		and the Bedouins against entering their monastery and seizing their possessions which provide their livelihood and that
			<lb n="15"/>
		of such pilgrims and travellers and so forth as come to them. When the Emir Ibn al-Faramāwī was appointed
			<lb n="16"/>
		governor of the forts at Ṭūr, the half-caste Bedouins of the ʿĀʾidh tribe, namely the ʿUsaykir
			<lb n="17"/>
		ʿĀlī, Raḥim, Muraybiṭ (?), Ḥuwayr (?), and their cousins, met with him and urged him to enter the monastery and take up residence there.
			<lb n="18"/>
		If he carries this out, then he and the Bedouins will plunder and destroy it. The usual custom is that
			<lb n="19"/>
		the Governor should live where the Sultan&#039;s sources of revenue are (May God strengthen his triumphal power and perpetuate his reign and dominion),
			<lb n="20"/>
		namely the coast, and that he should protect the produce brought in and guard it for the Sultan (May God perpetuate his dominion and reign). The slaves
			<lb n="21"/>
		fear in their hearts something that may harm them and the aforementioned monastery; that will be a cause of its being plundered and destroyed. So they
			<lb n="22"/>
		kiss the earth anew and beseech and beg him to take them by the hands for the sake of God Almighty and to issue an exalted order
			<lb n="23"/>
		(May God increase its efficacy and effectiveness) to the Officer of the Pure, Mighty Porte (May God perpetuate its honour)
			<lb n="24"/>
		to summon the aforementioned Emir and the Bedouins mentioned above and to obtain their signatures (to a document) comprising the noble sworn declaration that they will not
			<lb n="25"/>
		interfere with the monastery, nor take up residence there, nor come near it. For when the Bishop left the aforementioned monastery, the monks blocked up
			<lb n="26"/>
		its gate with stones and they have no way of opening it. If the Governor arrives requesting them to open it
			<lb n="27"/>
		and this is impossible for them to do, the affair will end in mutual malice and spite. They have reported this that full cognizance may be taken of it.
			<lb n="28"/>
		Yet to the exalted opinions belongs the superior ..... in this matter, if God wills (mighty and glorious is He!) Praise be to God alone ans His blessings be upon Muhammad and his family, and His peace.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
