<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2395" xml:id="Rustow_Woman" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.RustowWoman</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
              <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Rustow_Woman</idno>
              <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
              <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
              <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
             <p/>
          </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
 <lb n="2"/>  لمولاتنا السّيّدة الكريمة خلّد اللّه ملـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـكها</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وحرس</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عـ</supplied>ـزّها وأدام <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">عـ</supplied>ـلاها 
 <lb n="3"/>  وكبت أعداها في اصطناع المعروفِ وفعل الخير 
 <lb n="4"/>  عَوايد اللّه سبحانه ينشر لها شكرها ويذخر لها أجرها و<unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ملفوفة</unclear> 
 <lb n="5"/>  الجارية في ديوانها لا زال مأهولًا بدوام سُلطانِها مسجدُ جماعةٍ 
 <lb n="6"/>  وله أحباسٌ تصرفُ منها عشرون دينارا في كل سنة لمن يخطب ويقيم الدّعوة العالية 
 <lb n="7"/>  ويصرف فاضلها في مصالح المسجدِ وأجرة قيّمه ومُودّپه ولعبدها 
 <lb n="8"/>  خليفة علي الخطابةِ بها يعرف بموسى بن أزهر وحضر في هذا 
 <lb n="9"/>  الوقت فشكى تأخّر جاري الخطابة واستحكام طمع السّكّان في المدافعة به 
 <lb n="10"/>  وَاختلال هذا الحبس وذكر أن الباقي عند السّكّان إلى سلخ رجب سنة خمس عشرة وأربع مائة 
 <lb n="11"/>  نحو من عشرة دنانير وعبدها يسل الإنعام بمنشور من حضرتها 
 <lb n="12"/>  المحروسة إلي عامل النّاحية ومتولي حمايتها بالشّد على يد هذا المذكور 
 <lb n="13"/>  في استخراج هذه الأحباس فيما يسلّف ويستأنف وتقوية أمره ومعاضدته 
 <lb n="14"/>  وَمواررته والعناية به في جميع ما يعود بمصالح المسجدِ الجامع 
 <lb n="15"/>  والمنع من <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">إعيائه </lem><rdg resp="APD">إعيائه</rdg></app> ومدافعته أو تطرّق خلل علي هذا الحبس لتكثّر الدّعا 
 <lb n="16"/>  لَها في هذه الأيّام الشّريفة ولها الرّأي العالي في ذلك إن شا اللّه 
 <lb n="17"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وا</supplied>لحمد للّه وصلواته على محمّد النّبي وآله الطّاهرين وأبنا عترته الأئمّة المهتدين وسلّم تسليما 
 </ab></div>
          <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>li mawlāti nā ăs sayyidaẗi ăl karīmaẗi ḫallada ăl lāhu mulka hā wa ḥarasa ʿizza hā wa ʾadāma ʿalāʾa hā 
 <lb n="3"/>wa kabata ʾaʿdāʾa hā fī ĭṣṭināʿi ăl maʿrūfi wa fiʿli ăl ḫayri 
 <lb n="4"/>ʿawāyid ăl lāhi subḥāna hu yanšuru la hā šukra hā wa yaḏḫaru la hā ʾaǧra hā wa malfūfaẗ:uni 
 <lb n="5"/>ăl ǧāriyaẗu fī dīwāni hā lā zāla maʾhūl:an bi dawāmi sulṭāni hā masǧidu ǧamāʿaẗ:in 
 <lb n="6"/>wa la hu ʾaḥbās:un tuṣrafu min hā ʿišrūna dīnār:an fī kulli sanaẗ:in li man yaḫṭubu wa yuqīmu ăd daʿwaẗa ăl ʿāliyaẗa 
 <lb n="7"/>wa yuṣrafu fāḍilu hā fī maṣāliḥi ăl masǧidi wa ʾuǧraẗi qayyimi hi wa muʾaḏḏini hi wa li ʿabdi hā 
 <lb n="8"/>ḫalīfaẗ:un ʿalà ăl ḫaṭābaẗi bi hā yuʿrafu bi mūsà bni ʾazhara wa ḥaḍara fī hāḏā 
 <lb n="9"/>ăl waqti fa šakā taʾaḫḫura ǧārī ăl ḫaṭābaẗi wa ĭstiḥkāma ṭamaʿi ăs sukkāni fī ăl mudāfaʿaẗi bi hi 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ĭḫtilāli hāḏā ăl ḥubsi wa ḏakara ʾanna ăl bāqiya ʿinda ăs sukkāni ʾilà salḫi raǧabi sanaẗi ḫamsa ʿašraẗa wa ʾarbaʿi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="11"/>naḥw min ʿašaraẗi danānīra wa ʿabdu hā yasalu ăl ʾinʿāma bi manšūr:in min ḥaḍrati hā 
 <lb n="12"/>ăl maḥrūsaẗi ʾilà ʿāmili ăn nāḥiyaẗi wa mutawallī ḥimāyati hā bi ăš šaddi ʿalà yadi hāḏā ăl maḏkūri 
 <lb n="13"/>fī ĭstiḫrāǧi hāḏihi ăl ʾaḥbāsi fī mā yaslufu wa yastaʾnifu wa taqwiyaẗi ʾamri hi wa muʿāḍadati hi 
 <lb n="14"/>wa muʾāzaraẗi hi wa ăl ʿināyaẗi bi hi fī ǧamīʿi mā yaʿūdu bi maṣāliḥi ăl masǧidi ăl ǧāmiʿi 
 <lb n="15"/>wa ăl manʿi min ʾaʿyāni ʾiʿyāʾi hi wa mudāfaʿaẗi hi ʾaw taṭarruqi ḫalal:in ʿalà hāḏā ăl ḥubsi li takaṯṯuri ăd duʿāʾi 
 <lb n="16"/>la hā fī hāḏihi ăl ʾayyāmi ăš šarīfaẗi wa la hā ăr raʾyu ăl ʿālī fī ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa ṣalawātu hu ʿalà muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa ʾāli hi ăṭ ṭāhirīna wa ʾabnāʾi ʿitraẗi hi ăl ʾaʾimmaẗi ăl muhtadīna wa sallama taslīm:an 
   </ab></div>
 <div type="translation"><ab>
		 <lb n="1"/>
 	  In the name of God, the merciful, the compassionate.
		 <lb n="2"/>
 	  To our mistress, the noble lady, may God make her dominion eternal, secure her high rank, perpetuate her loftiness
		 <lb n="3"/>
 	  and crush her enemies. In (return for) the bestowal of a benefaction and the rendering of a benefit
		 <lb n="4"/>
 	  the beneficence of God, transcendence be to Him - may her thanks be disseminated for her and her reward stored up for her. Included in
		 <lb n="5"/>
 	  what is administered in her dīwān - may it continue to be filled with the perpetuity of her reign - is a communal mosque
		 <lb n="6"/>
 	  with pious foundations from which twenty dīnārs are distributed annually to the person who preaches and upholds the lofty daʿwa.
		 <lb n="7"/>
 	  Their remainder (i.e. of the income from the foundations) is distributed for the repair of the mosque and the salary of its superintendent and its muʾadhdhin. And her slave
		 <lb n="8"/>
 	  has a deputy charged with the office of preaching it (i.e. the daʿwa), known as Mūsā ibn Azhar. Recently he presented himself
		 <lb n="9"/>
 	  and complained about the delay of the income for the office of preacher and about the strong desire of the tenants to defer it
		 <lb n="10"/>
 	  and dissolve this foundation. And he mentioned that the debt owed by those living there until the end of Rajab in the year 415 is
		 <lb n="11"/>
 	  about ten dīnārs. Her slave asks for a benefaction in the form of a decree (manshūr) from her Presence,
		 <lb n="12"/>
 	  may she be preserved, to the governor of the district and the administrator of its jurisdiction, strengthening the hand of the aforementioned (preacher)
		 <lb n="13"/>
 	  in extracting (income) from these foundations according to what came before and what will resume, strengthening his affair, assisting him,
		 <lb n="14"/>
 	  aiding him, and being solicitous towards him in everything that occurs regarding the repairs of the congregational mosque,
		 <lb n="15"/>
 	  protecting its property and defending it, or in any occurence of injury to this foundation, so that prayers for her may be abundant
		 <lb n="16"/>
 	  during these days of (her) illustriouness. The exalted resolution in this matter belongs to her, if God wills.
		 <lb n="17"/>
 	  Praise be to God and His prayers be upon Muḥammad the prophet and his pure family, and the sons of the Prophet&#039;s descendants, the rightly guided imāms, and save them.
 </ab></div>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>
