<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2218" xml:id="Stern_FatimidPetitions_2" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.SternFatimidPetitions 2 (= P.GenizahCambr. 077)</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Stern_FatimidPetitions_2</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  العبد المملوك 
<lb n="2"/>  موسى بن صدقة التّاجر اليهودي 
<lb n="3"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="4"/>  صلوات اللّه وبركاته ونوامي زكواته وأفضل سلامه وتحيّاته على <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مولانا</supplied> 
<lb n="5"/>  وسيّدنا وإمام عصرنا وزماننا الإمام الآمر بأحكام اللّه أمير المومپپن وعلى 
<lb n="6"/>  آبائه الطّاهرين وأبنائه الأكرمين صلاة <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">باقية</supplied> إلى يوم الدّين المملوك يقبّل الأرض 
<lb n="7"/>  أمام المقام النّبوي الطّاهر الشّريف ضاعف اللّه أنواره وأسنى 
<lb n="8"/>  مناره ونصر جيوشه وأعلامه وأنصاره وينهي 
<lb n="9"/>  أنّه وصل من الهند واليمن بتجارة وقراض معه 
<lb n="10"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">فأعيق </lem><rdg resp="Khan">فعيق</rdg></app> بشبهة لم <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">تحق </lem><rdg resp="Khan">تجوز</rdg></app> إعاقته به وقد أثبت المملوك 
<lb n="11"/>  في مجلس القاضي جلال الملك تاج الأحكام <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">إزالة</unclear> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD"><gap reason="illegible" extent="6" unit="character" /> </lem><rdg resp="Khan">للاعتراض</rdg></app> 
<lb n="12"/>  والمملوك <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">يسئل </lem><rdg resp="Khan">يسل</rdg></app> ويضرع بالإنعام عليه والإحسان 
<lb n="13"/>  إليه بخروج التّوقيع العالي زاده اللّه <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">عزّا </lem><rdg resp="Khan">نفاذا</rdg></app> وشرفا 
<lb n="14"/>  إلى القاضي جلال الملك تاج الأحكام <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">باكـ<gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> </lem><rdg resp="Khan">بذكر</rdg></app> ما <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">ثبت </lem><rdg resp="Khan">أثبت</rdg></app> المملوك 
<lb n="15"/>  عنده ليكون ذلك سببا لإيصاله إلى حقّه رأفة 
<lb n="16"/>  له وحنوّا عليه ولمولانا سلام اللّه على ذكره 
<lb n="17"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الرّأي</supplied> الأعلا في ذلك إن شا اللّه عز وجل 
<lb n="18"/>  والحمد للّه وحده 
<lb n="19"/>  وصلوات اللّه على سيّدنا محمّد النّبي وآله وسلامه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>ăl ʿabdu ăl mamlūku 
 <lb n="2"/>mūsà bnu ṣadaqaẗa ăt tāǧiru ăl yahūdiyyu 
 <lb n="3"/>bi ĭsmi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="4"/>ṣalawātu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu wa nawāmī zakawāti hi wa ʾafḍalu salāmi hi wa taḥiyyāti hi ʿalà mawlā nā 
 <lb n="5"/>wa sayyidi nā wa ʾimāmi ʿaṣri nā wa zamāni nā ăl ʾimāmi ăl ʾāmiri bi ʾaḥkāmi ăl lāhi ʾamīri ăl muʾminīna wa ʿalà 
 <lb n="6"/>ʾābāʾi hi ăṭ ṭāhirīna wa ʾabnāʾi hi ăl ʾakramīna ṣalāẗ:an bāqiyaẗ:an ʾilà yawmi ăd dīni ăl mamlūku yuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa 
 <lb n="7"/>ʾamāma ăl maqāmi ăn nabawiyyi ăṭ ṭāhiri ăš šarīfi ḍāʿafa ăl lāhu ʾanwāra hu wa ʾasnà 
 <lb n="8"/>manāra hu wa naṣara ǧuyūša hu wa ʾaʿlāma hu wa ʾanṣāra hu wa yunhī 
 <lb n="9"/>ʾanna hu waṣala mina ăl hindi wa ăl yamani bi tiǧāraẗ:in wa qirāḍ:in maʿa hu 
 <lb n="10"/>fa ʾuʿīqa ʿīqa bi šubhaẗ:in lam taḥiqqi taǧūz ʾiʿāqatu hu bi hi wa qad ʾaṯbata ăl mamlūku 
 <lb n="11"/>fī maǧlisi ăl qāḍī ǧalāli ăl mulki tāǧi ăl ʾaḥkāmi ʾizālaẗ:an ******* li ø li ø ĭʿtirāḍi ø ʿan ø hu 
 <lb n="12"/>wa ăl mamlūku yasʾalu yasalu wa yaḍraʿu bi ăl ʾinʿāmi ʿalay hi wa ăl ʾiḥsāni 
 <lb n="13"/>ʾilay hi bi ḫurūǧi ăt tawqīʿi ăl ʿālī zāda hu ăl lāhu ʿizz:an nafāḏ:an wa šaraf:an 
 <lb n="14"/>ʾilà ăl qāḍī ǧalāli ăl mulki tāǧi ăl ʾaḥkāmi bi ʾk*** ḏikri mā ṯabbata ʾaṯbata ăl mamlūku 
 <lb n="15"/>ʿinda hu li yakūna ḏālika sabab:an li ʾīṣāli hi ʾilà ḥaqqi hi raʾfaẗ:an 
 <lb n="16"/>la hu wa ḥunuww:an ʿalay hi wa li mawlā nā salāmu ăl lāhi ʿalà ḏikri hi 
 <lb n="17"/>ăr raʾyu ăl ʾaʿlā fī ḏālika ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu ʿazza wa ǧalla 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ṣalawātu ăl lāhi ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:ini ăn nabiyyi wa ʾāli hi wa salāmu hu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		The servant and slave
		The slave,
			<lb n="2"/>
		Mūsā b. Ṣadaqa, the Jewish merchant.
			<lb n="3"/>
		In the name of God, the merciful and compassionate.
		In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate.
			<lb n="4"/>
		The benedictions of God and his blessings, his increasing benefactions and most excellent peace and blessings be upon our master
		The blessings and benedictions of God, and His increasing benefactions and most excellent blessings be upon our Lord
			<lb n="5"/>
		and lord, the ʾimām of our era and time, the ʾimām al-ʾĀmir bi-ʾAḥkām Allāh, commander of the faithful, and upon
		and Master the Imam al-Āmir bi-Aḥkām Allāh, Commander of the Faithful, and
			<lb n="6"/>
		his pure ancestors and most noble sons, enduring benedictions, which last until the day of judgment. The slave kisses the ground
		his pure ancestors and noble sons - blessings lasting till the day of judgment. The slave kisses the earth
			<lb n="7"/>
		before the pure and noble prophetical presence, may God double its light and exalt
		in front of the pure and noble prophetic presence, may God double its light and exalt
			<lb n="8"/>
		its beacon, and give victory to its armies, banners and helpers, and reports
		its torch, and give victory to its armies, banners and helpers, and reports as follows:
			<lb n="9"/>
		He has arrived from India and the Yemen bringing merchandise as well as [money, or goods, in] commenda
		that he arrived from India and Yemen with merchandise and (goods or money) in commenda
			<lb n="10"/>
		but it was detained by a pretext on which it was not lawful for it to be detained. The slave had registered (documents)
		but it was detained by a pretext which was not a proper reason for detention. The slave has established ...
			<lb n="11"/>
		in the court of the Kadi Calāl al-Mulk Tāc al-Aḥkām to ...
		in the court of the qāḍī Jalāl al-Mulk Tāj al-ʾAḥkām in order to prevent [any dispute]
			<lb n="12"/>
		The slave humbly asks for a kindness to be bestowed upon him and a benefaction granted
		The slave humbly petitions that the benefaction be bestowed upon, and the favor granted to,
			<lb n="13"/>
		him, to wit the issue of an exalted document (may God increase its glory and nobility)
		to him by the issuing of an exalted rescript, may God increase its efficacy and nobility,
			<lb n="14"/>
		ordering the Kadi Calāl al-Mulk Tāc al-Aḥkām to ... what the slave had established
		to the qāḍī Jalāl al-Mulk Tāj al-ʾAḥkām (instructing him) to indicate what the slave has registered
			<lb n="15"/>
		before him - out of mercy
		with him, in order that this be a means of restoring his right to him, out of compassion
			<lb n="16"/>
		and commiseration for him. To our lord, the peace of God be upon his name,
		for him. To our Lord (God&#039;s greeting be upon his name)
			<lb n="17"/>
		belongs the exalted opinion in this matter, if God wills. Praise be to God alone.
		belongs the exalted resolution in this, if God wills, he is mighty and glorious.
			<lb n="18"/>
		Praise be to God alone.
			<lb n="19"/>
		God&#039;s blessings and greetings be upon our Lord Muḥammad the prophet and his family.
		The blessings and peace of God be upon our lord Muḥammad the prophet and his family.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
