<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2058" xml:id="Stern_AyyubidDecrees_2" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.SternAyyubidDecrees 2</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Stern_AyyubidDecrees_2</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  خرج الأمر العالي المولوي 
<lb n="between 2 and 3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الحمد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وبه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">توفيقي</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  السُّلطَاني الملكي الأفضلي لا زَال 
<lb n="4"/>  عالي المنَار نامي المبار منصور الأنصار 
<lb n="5"/>  مسعود الإيراد والإصدَار نافذا في 
<lb n="6"/>  الأطراف والأقطَار بإجرا جَماعة 
<lb n="7"/>  الرّهبان بطور سينا المبارك سلّمهم اللّه 
<lb n="8"/>  علي عَادتهِم في حفظِهم ورعايتهم وصيَانة 
<lb n="9"/>  أحوالهِم وحمَايتهم وتيسير مطَالبهم وتَسهيل 
<lb n="10"/>  ماآربهم وأن لا يُعترضوا بأذيّة ظاهِرَة 
<lb n="11"/>  ولَا باطنة وأن تُرفَه خواطرهم لتكون 
<lb n="12"/>  المرفّهة السَّاكنة ولا يعرضوا في 
<lb n="13"/>  كرُومهم ونخيلهم وزرُوعهم بإضرَارٍ ولَا 
<lb n="14"/>  مقاسَمة ولا احتجار ولا اقتطاع 
<lb n="15"/>  شي من ذلك بوجه من وجُوه الإِجبَار 
<lb n="16"/>  وَأن لا يكرّهُوا بمُسَاكنة غَيرهم ولا يخزن 
<lb n="17"/>  غلّةٍ ولا غَيرِها في دَيرِهم ولتكف عَنهُم 
<lb n="18"/>  أسباب المسأَة العايدة بضيرهم 
<lb n="19"/>  والأمير الإسفهسلار الكبير الأخصّ 
<lb n="20"/>  الموفّق الأمين شمس الدّين عدّة المُجاهدين 
<lb n="21"/>  عمدة الملوك والسّلاطِين خاصّة أمير المومنپن 
<lb n="22"/>  أبو سعيد أسلم أدام اللّه تأييده ونعمته وتسديده 
<lb n="23"/>  ورفعته وأجزل من كل خير مَوهبته 
<lb n="24"/>  يقِفُ عند هذا الأمر وَلَا يتعدّيه وَليحذر 
<lb n="25"/>  من تجاوزه إلي ما سِوَاه ويشملهم 
<lb n="26"/>  بكل إرعإِ فإنّهم رعَايانا ورعَاياه 
<lb n="27"/>  وليُخفّف الوَطأة عَنهُم لمكان انقطاعِهم 
<lb n="28"/>  في ذلك المكان الشّريف ولا يمكّن أحدًا 
<lb n="29"/>  من أذيّتهم فما منهم إلَّا من هُوَ المسكِين 
<lb n="30"/>  الضَّعيف وليجرّهم على عوايدهم 
<lb n="31"/>  وَأحكام تواقيعهم الّتي بأيديهم وأَمرُنا 
<lb n="32"/>  هَذا لذلك مُوكد ولأثواب الإحسان 
<lb n="33"/>  إليهم مُجدّد وسَبيل كُل 
<lb n="34"/>  واقف على هَذا المثال من مقطع ووال 
<lb n="35"/>  ومتول لقلعة أيلة حرسَها اللّه الامتثال 
<lb n="36"/>  لمراسمه والوقوف عند مَعَالمِه 
<lb n="37"/>  والتّجنّب لمظَانّ الحَيف وماآثمه 
<lb n="38"/>  وليكن العمل بحسبه في اليوم والغَد 
<lb n="39"/>  وليُقر بأيديهم بعد قرآته حجّة لهم 
<lb n="40"/>  فيما بعد 
<lb n="41"/>  إن شا اللّه تعالى 
<lb n="42"/>  وكتب في خامس ذي القعدة سنة خمس وتسعين وخمسمائة 
<lb n="43"/>  بظاهر دمشق 
<lb n="44"/>  الحمد للّه وحده وصلواته على سَيّدنا محمّد نبيّه وآله 
<lb n="45"/>  وصحبه وسلامه 
<lb n="46"/>  حسبنا الله ونعم الوكيل 
<lb n="47"/>  الملك للّه 
<lb n="between 6 and 7 right [1a]"/>  لينسخ في ديوان النّظر الخاص المصري المعمور إن شا اللّه تعالى 
<lb n="between 6 and 7 right [1b]"/>  نسخ والحمد للّه عليه توكّلي 
<lb n="between 6 and 7 left [2a]"/>  لينسخ في الدّيوان إن شا اللّه 
<lb n="between 6 and 7 left [2b]"/>  نسخ والحمد للّه الواحد العدل 
<lb n="between 7 and 8 [3]"/>  نسخ الحمد للّه على نعمائه 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ḫaraǧa ăl ʾamru ăl ʿālī ăl mawlawiyyu 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa bi hi tawfīq ī 
 <lb n="4"/>ăs sulṭāniyyu ăl malikiyyu ăl ʾafḍaliyyu lā zāla 
 <lb n="5"/>ʿālī ăl manāri nāmī ăl mabārri manṣūru ăl ʾanṣāri 
 <lb n="6"/>masʿūdu ăl ʾīrādi wa ăl ʾiṣdāri nāfiḏ:an fī 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl ʾaṭrāfi wa ăl ʾaqṭāri bi ʾiǧrāʾi ǧamāʿaẗi 
 <lb n="8"/>ăr ruhbāni bi ṭūri sīnā ăl mubāraki sallama humu ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="9"/>ʿalà ʿādati him fī ḥifẓi him wa riʿāyati him wa ṣiyānaẗi 
 <lb n="10"/>ʾaḥwāli him wa ḥimāyati him wa taysīri maṭālibi him wa tashīli 
 <lb n="11"/>maʾāribi him wa ʾan lā yuʿtaraḍū bi ʾaḏiyyaẗ:in ẓāhiraẗ:in 
 <lb n="12"/>wa lā bāṭinaẗ:in wa ʾan turfaha ḫawāṭiru hum li takūna 
 <lb n="13"/>ăl muraffahaẗu ăs sākinaẗu wa lā yuʿraḍū fī 
 <lb n="14"/>kurūmi him wa naḫīli him wa zurūʿi him bi ʾiḍrār:in wa lā 
 <lb n="15"/>muqāsamaẗ:in wa lā ĭḥtiǧār:in wa lā ĭqtiṭāʿi 
 <lb n="16"/>šayʾ:in min ḏālika bi waǧh:in min wuǧūhi ăl ʾiǧbāri 
 <lb n="17"/>wa ʾan lā yukarrahū bi musākanaẗi ġayri him wa lā yuḫzanu 
 <lb n="18"/>ġallaẗ:in wa lā ġayru hā fī dayri him wa la tukaffa ʿan hum 
 <lb n="19"/>ʾasbābu ăl masāʾaẗi ăl ʿāyidaẗu bi ḍayri him 
 <lb n="20"/>wa ăl ʾamīru ăl ʾisfahsalāru ăl kabīru ăl ʾaḫaṣṣu 
 <lb n="21"/>ăl muwaffaqu ăl ʾamīnu šamsu ăd dīni ʿiddaẗu ăl muǧāhidīna 
 <lb n="22"/>ʿumdaẗu ăl mulūki wa ăs salāṭīni ḫāṣṣaẗu ʾamīri ăl muʾminīna 
 <lb n="23"/>ʾabū saʿīd:in ʾaslamu ʾadāma ăl lāhu taʾyīda hu wa niʿmata hu wa tasdīda hu 
 <lb n="24"/>wa rifʿata hu wa ʾaǧzala min kulli ḫayr:in mawhibata hu 
 <lb n="25"/>yaqif ʿinda hāḏā ăl ʾamri wa lā yataʿaddī hi wa li yaḥḏara 
 <lb n="26"/>man taǧāwaza hu ʾilà mā siwā hu wa yašmala hum 
 <lb n="27"/>bi kulli ʾirʿāʾ:in fa ʾinna hum raʿāyā nā wa hu raʿāyā 
 <lb n="28"/>wa li yuḫaffifa ăl waṭʾaẗa ʿan hum li makāni ĭnqiṭāʿi him 
 <lb n="29"/>fī ḏālika ăl makāni ăš šarīfi wa lā yumakkin ʾaḥad:an 
 <lb n="30"/>min ʾaḏiyyati him fa mā min hum ʾillā man huwa ăl miskīnu 
 <lb n="31"/>ăḍ ḍaʿīfu wa li yaǧurra hum ʿalà ʿawāyidi him 
 <lb n="32"/>wa ʾaḥkāmi tawāqīʿi himi ăllatī bi ʾaydī him wa ʾamru nā 
 <lb n="33"/>hāḏā li ḏālika muʾakkid:un wa li ʾaṯwābi ăl ʾiḥsāni 
 <lb n="34"/>ʾilay him muǧaddid:un wa sabīlu kulli 
 <lb n="35"/>wāqif:in ʿalà hāḏā ăl miṯāli min muqṭaʿ:in wa wāl:in 
 <lb n="36"/>wa mutawall:in li qalʿaẗi ʾaylaẗa ḥarasa hā ăl lāhu ăli ĭmtiṯālu 
 <lb n="37"/>li marāsimi hi wa ăl wuqūfu ʿinda maʿālimi hi 
 <lb n="38"/>wa ăt taǧannubu li maẓānni ăl ḥayfi wa māʾāṯimi hi 
 <lb n="39"/>wa la yakun ăl ʿamalu bi ḥasabi hi fī ăl yawmi wa ăl ġadi 
 <lb n="40"/>wa la yuqarr bi ʾaydī him baʿda qirāʾati hi ḥuǧǧaẗ:an la hum 
 <lb n="41"/>fī mā baʿdu 
 <lb n="42"/>ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="43"/>wa kutiba fī ḫāmisi ḏī ăl qaʿdaẗi sanaẗa ḫams:in wa tisʿīna wa ḫamsi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="44"/>bi ẓāhiri dimašqa 
 <lb n="45"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu wa ṣalāwātu hu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in nabiyyi hi wa ʾāli hi 
 <lb n="46"/>wa ṣaḥbi hi wa salāmu hu 
 <lb n="47"/>ḥasbu nā ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
 <lb n="48"/>ăl mulku li l lāhi 
 <lb n="49"/>li yunsaḫa fī dīwāni ăn naẓari ăl ḫāṣṣi ăl miṣriyyi ăl maʿmūri ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="50"/>nusiḫa wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ʿalay hi tawakkul ī 
 <lb n="51"/>li yunsaḫa fī ăd dīwāni ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu 
 <lb n="52"/>nusiḫa wa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ăl wāḥidi ăl ʿadli 
 <lb n="53"/>nusiḫa ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi ʿalà naʿmāʾi hi 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		The exalted order of the master,
			<lb n="3"/>
		Praise be to God, who is the cause of my success.
			<lb n="4"/>
		the sultan al-Malik al-Afḍal
			<lb n="5"/>
		- may its light continue to be exalted, its charities to increase, its victories to prevail,
			<lb n="6"/>
		whatever it begins and ends to be fortunate,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and to be executed in all lands and regions - was issued to treat the community
			<lb n="8"/>
		of monks in the blessed Mount Sinai (may God give them peace)
			<lb n="9"/>
		according to their custom, by guarding
			<lb n="10"/>
		and protecting them, defending their affairs, facilitating their business and making easy
			<lb n="11"/>
		their occupations. They should not be interfered with through open
			<lb n="12"/>
		or concealed harm, their minds be reassured so as to make them
			<lb n="13"/>
		confident and quiet. Their
			<lb n="14"/>
		vineyards, palm-trees, and fields should not be interfered with by damage,
			<lb n="15"/>
		sharing, enclosing, enfeoffment,
			<lb n="16"/>
		or in any way of constraint;
			<lb n="17"/>
		they should not be forced to live together with people not belonging to them, and no
			<lb n="18"/>
		grain, or other goods, should be stored in their monastery, and
			<lb n="19"/>
		all evil actions causing them harm should be prevented.
			<lb n="20"/>
		Let the amīr, the great general, our intimate courtier,
			<lb n="21"/>
		the one assisted by God, the trustworthy one, Sun of Religion [Shams al-Dīn], Armament of the Fighters for the Faith,
			<lb n="22"/>
		Support of Kings and Sultans, the Intimate Friend of the Commander of the Faithful,
			<lb n="23"/>
		Abū Saʿīd Aslam (may God prolong his help, welfare, support,
			<lb n="24"/>
		and greatness, and may He give him ample share of all benefits)
			<lb n="25"/>
		obey this order and not transgress it, and beware
			<lb n="26"/>
		from passing it by in order to do something else. Let him encompass them
			<lb n="27"/>
		by all protection, since they are our and his subjects,
			<lb n="28"/>
		and let him deal with them with a light touch on account of their having retired
			<lb n="29"/>
		to that noble place, and let him allow no one
			<lb n="30"/>
		to harm them, since all of them are poor and
			<lb n="31"/>
		weak. Let him treat them according to their customs
			<lb n="32"/>
		and the rulings contained in the decrees which are in their hands. This order of ours
			<lb n="33"/>
		confirms this and
			<lb n="34"/>
		renews the garments of benefaction towards them.
			<lb n="35"/>
		Let fief-holders, governors
			<lb n="36"/>
		and the governor of the fortress of Ayla (may God guard it), who have cognizance
			<lb n="37"/>
		of this order, obey its commands and follow its instructions,
			<lb n="38"/>
		and avoid actions smacking of oppression;
			<lb n="39"/>
		and let it be acted upon to-day and to-morrow,
			<lb n="40"/>
		and let this be deposited in their hands after it had been read, as a proof
			<lb n="41"/>
		in the future,
			<lb n="42"/>
		if God (may He be exalted) wills.
			<lb n="43"/>
		Written this fifth day of Dhu&#039;l-Qaʿda, the year Five-hundred Ninety Five,
			<lb n="44"/>
		outside Damascus.
			<lb n="45"/>
		Praise be to God alone, and His blessings and peace upon our lord Muḥammad His prophet, his family
			<lb n="46"/>
		and his companions.
			<lb n="47"/>
		God is sufficient for us; how excellent a Keeper is He!
			<lb n="48"/>
		Kingdom belongs to God.
			<lb n="49"/>
		Let it be copied in the Office of the Private Superintendance for Egypt (may it flourish), if God wills.
			<lb n="50"/>
		It has been copied; praise be to God, in Him I trust.
			<lb n="51"/>
		Let it be copied in the Office, if God wills.
			<lb n="52"/>
		It has been copied; praise be to God, the one, the just.
			<lb n="53"/>
		It has been copied; praise be to God for His bounty.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
