<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2049" xml:id="Stern_AyyubidDecrees_1" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.SternAyyubidDecrees 1</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Stern_AyyubidDecrees_1</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرَّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  منشور تقدّم بكتبه المولي الملك العادل 
<lb n="between 2 and 3"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الحمد</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">للّه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">وبه</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">توفيقي</supplied> 
<lb n="3"/>  السّيّد الأجل الكبير العالم المويد المظفَّر 
<lb n="4"/>  المنصور المرابط الهمام سيف الدّين ناصر الإسلام 
<lb n="5"/>  معين الإمام غياث الأنام جلال الدّولَة 
<lb n="6"/>  تاج الملَّة مجير الأمّة سيّد الملوك والسَّلاطين 
<lb n="7"/>  سُلطان جيوش المسلمين قامع الكفرة 
<lb n="8"/>  والمشركين أبو بكر بن أيّوب خليل أمير المومنين 
<lb n="9"/>  قرن اللّه النفاذ بنهيه وأمره وأنطق 
<lb n="10"/>  ألسن العباد بحمده وشكره ونوّر بالحسنات 
<lb n="11"/>  مواقيت ليله وساعات فجره وأحيا الآمالَ 
<lb n="12"/>  بما يمطره سحاب سيبه ويمتد به أيّام برّه 
<lb n="13"/>  وتضمينه أنّا لم نزل وللّه الحمد نذب عن الرّعَايَا 
<lb n="14"/>  الّذين فوّض اللّه تعالى أمرهم إلينا وأحالت 
<lb n="15"/>  الشّريعة الطّاهرة في حياطَتِهم عَلَينا 
<lb n="16"/>  فنكف كف الأذي عنهم ونجازي علي 
<lb n="17"/>  الإحسَان من سلك طريقَه منهُم 
<lb n="18"/>  ونُقيل عثرتهم ونكشف كربتهم وغمّتهم 
<lb n="19"/>  ونضاعف ذلك لبطاركتهم ورهبَانهم 
<lb n="20"/>  وقِسِّيْسيهم وكهّانهم وساكني 
<lb n="21"/>  الصّوامع من زهّادهم والمنقطعين بالدّيرَة 
<lb n="22"/>  من عُبَّادهم ونقدِّم عليهم من ارتضو تقديمه 
<lb n="23"/>  وتقدّمنا بأن يجروا رهبان هذا 
<lb n="24"/>  الدّير المذكور على عادتهم المستمرّة 
<lb n="25"/>  ويقرّوا على القاعدة المستتبّة المستقرّة 
<lb n="26"/>  وأن يتوخّوا بالرّعاية والحماية والحياطة 
<lb n="27"/>  والكِلَاية ويمنع من يتعرّض لأذيّتهم أو 
<lb n="28"/>  يطمع في مضرّتهم أو يتعدّى بقطع 
<lb n="29"/>  رسومهم الجاري بها مَاضي عادتهم أو 
<lb n="30"/>  يتطرّق لإخافة سبيلهم المسلُوك لزيارتهم 
<lb n="31"/>  وأن لا يفسح للعُربان وَلا لغيرهم من الموافقين 
<lb n="32"/>  والمخالفين لهم في الأديَان في اهتضامهم 
<lb n="33"/>  ولا في تكليفهم نقض ما أُقِرُّوا عَلَيه من 
<lb n="34"/>  أحكامهم ولا يعارض زوّارهم من البلاد الشّاميّة بوجه من وجوه إضرار أو أذيّة 
<lb n="35"/>  وسبيل كل واقف على هذا المثال 
<lb n="36"/>  من الأمَرا والولاة أجمعين أيّدهم اللّه والنّوّاب 
<lb n="37"/>  وكافّة المستخدمين حمل الأمر على حكمه 
<lb n="38"/>  والانتها إلى واجب رسمه والإنكار علَي 
<lb n="39"/>  من خالَفه بعد علمه عاملين 
<lb n="40"/>  بفحواه معتمدين على العلامة 
<lb n="41"/>  الشّريفة في أعلاه إن شا اللّه تعالى 
<lb n="42"/>  كتب سادس عشر المحرّم من سنة اثنتين وتسعين وخمس مائة 
<lb n="43"/>  الحمد للّه وحده وصلَّى اللّهُ علَي سيّدنا محمّد وآله الطّاهرين 
<lb n="44"/>  وسلّم تسليما كثيرا 
<lb n="45"/>  وحسبنا اللّه ونعم الوكيل 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>manšūr:un taqaddama bi katbi hi ăl mawlà ăl maliku ăl ʿādilu 
 <lb n="3"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi wa bi hi tawfīq ī 
 <lb n="4"/>ăs sayyidu ăl ʾaǧallu ăl kabīru ăl ʿālimu ăl muʾayyadu ăl muẓaffaru 
 <lb n="5"/>ăl manṣūru ăl murābiṭu ăl humāmu sayfu ăd dīni nāṣiru ăl ʾislāmi 
 <lb n="6"/>muʿīnu ăl ʾimāmi ġiyāṯu ăl ʾanāmi ǧalālu ăd dawlaẗi 
 <lb n="7"/>tāǧu ăl millaẗi muǧīru ăl ʾummaẗi sayyidu ăl mulūki wa ăs salāṭīni 
 <lb n="8"/>sulṭānu ǧuyūši ăl muslimīna qāmiʿu ăl kafaraẗi 
 <lb n="9"/>wa ăl mušrikīna ʾabū bakri bni ʾayyūba ḫalīlu ʾamīri ăl muʾminīna 
 <lb n="10"/>qarana ăl lāhu ăn nafāḏa bi nahyi hi wa ʾamri hi wa ʾanṭaqa 
 <lb n="11"/>ʾalsuna ăl ʿibādi bi ḥamdi hi wa šukri hi wa nawwara bi ăl ḥasanāti 
 <lb n="12"/>mawāqīta layli hi wa sāʿāti faǧri hi wa ʾaḥyā ăl ʾāmāla 
 <lb n="13"/>bi mā yamṭuru hu saḥābu saybi hi wa yamtaddu bi hi ʾayyāmu birri hi 
 <lb n="14"/>wa taḍmīnu hu ʾan nā lam nazal wa li l lāhi ăl ḥamdu naḏubbu ʿani ăr raʿāyā 
 <lb n="15"/>ăllaḏīna fawwaḍa ăl lāhu taʿālà ʾamra hum ʾilay nā wa ʾaḥālat 
 <lb n="16"/>ăš šarīʿaẗu ăṭ ṭāhiraẗu fī ḥiyāṭati him ʿalay nā 
 <lb n="17"/>fa nakuffu kaffa ăl ʾaḏà ʿan hum wa nuǧāzī ʿalà 
 <lb n="18"/>ăl ʾiḥsāni man salaka ṭarīqa hu min hum 
 <lb n="19"/>wa nuqīlu ʿaṯrata hum wa nakšifu kurbata hum wa ġummata hum 
 <lb n="20"/>wa nuḍāʿifu ḏālika li baṭārikati him wa ruhbāni him 
 <lb n="21"/>wa qissīsī him wa kuhhāni him wa sākinī 
 <lb n="22"/>ăṣ ṣawāmiʿi min zuhhādi him wa ăl munqaṭiʿīna bi ăd diyaraẗi 
 <lb n="23"/>min ʿubbādi him wa nuqaddimu ʿalay him mani ĭrtaḍaw taqdīma hu 
 <lb n="24"/>wa taqaddamnā bi ʾan yuǧrū ruhbāna hāḏā 
 <lb n="25"/>ăd dayri ăl maḏkūri ʿalà ʿādati himi ăl mustamirraẗi 
 <lb n="26"/>wa yuqirrū ʿalà ăl qāʿidaẗi ăl mustatabbaẗi ăl mustaqirraẗi 
 <lb n="27"/>wa ʾan yatawaḫḫaw bi ăr riʿāyaẗi wa ăl ḥimāyaẗi wa ăl ḥiyāṭaẗi 
 <lb n="28"/>wa ăl kilāyaẗi wa yamnaʿa man yataʿarraḍu li ʾaḏiyyati him ʾaw 
 <lb n="29"/>yaṭmaʿu fī maḍarrati him ʾaw yataʿaddà bi qaṭʿi 
 <lb n="30"/>rusūmi him ăl ǧārī bi hā māḍī ʿādati him ʾaw 
 <lb n="31"/>yataṭarraqu li ʾiḫāfaẗi sabīli himi ăl maslūki li ziyārati him 
 <lb n="32"/>wa ʾan lā yufsaḥa li l ʿurbāni wa lā li ġayri him mina ăl muwāfiqīna 
 <lb n="33"/>wa ăl muḫālifīna la hum fī ăl ʾadyāni fī ĭhtiḍāmi him 
 <lb n="34"/>wa lā fī taklīfi him naqḍa mā ʾuqirrū ʿalay hi min 
 <lb n="35"/>ʾaḥkāmi him wa lā yuʿāraḍa zuwwāru hum mina ăl bilādi ăš šāmiyyaẗi bi waǧh:in min wuǧūhi ʾiḍrār:in ʾaw ʾaḏiyyaẗ:in 
 <lb n="36"/>wa sabīlu kulli wāqif:in ʿalà hāḏā ăl miṯāli 
 <lb n="37"/>mina ăl ʾumarāʾi wa ăl wulāẗi ʾaǧmaʿīna ʾayyada humu ăl lāhu wa ăn nuwwābi 
 <lb n="38"/>wa kāffaẗi ăl mustaḫdamīna ḥamlu ăl ʾamri ʿalà ḥukmi hi 
 <lb n="39"/>wa ăli ĭntihāʾu ʾilà wāǧibi rasmi hi wa ăl ʾinkāru ʿalà 
 <lb n="40"/>man ḫālafa hu baʿda ʿilmi hi ʿāmilīna 
 <lb n="41"/>bi faḥwā hu muʿtamidīna ʿalà ăl ʿalāmaẗi 
 <lb n="42"/>ăš šarīfaẗi fī ʾaʿlā hu ʾin šāʾa ăl lāhu taʿālà 
 <lb n="43"/>kutiba sādisa ʿašara ăl muḥarrami min sanaẗi ĭṯnatayni wa tisʿīna wa ḫamsi miʾaẗ:in 
 <lb n="44"/>ăl ḥamdu li l lāhi waḥda hu wa ṣallà ăl lāhu ʿalà sayyidi nā muḥammad:in wa ʾāli hi ăṭ ṭāhirīna 
 <lb n="45"/>wa sallama taslīm:an kaṯīr:an 
 <lb n="46"/>wa ḥasbu nā ăl lāhu wa niʿma ăl wakīlu 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is an open decree, the order for the writing of which was given by the Master, the Victorious King [al-Malik al-ʿĀdil],
			<lb n="3"/>
		Praise be to God, who is the cause of my success.
			<lb n="4"/>
		the Most Excellent, Great, Learned, Divinely Assisted, Triumphant,
			<lb n="5"/>
		Victorious, Combating, Heroic Lord, Sword of Religion, Helper of Islam,
			<lb n="6"/>
		Assistant of the Imam, Succour of Mankind, Majesty of Empire,
			<lb n="7"/>
		Crown of the Muslim Denomination, Protector of the Community, Lord of Kings and Sultans,
			<lb n="8"/>
		Sultan of the Armies of the Muslims, Subduer of Unbelievers
			<lb n="9"/>
		and Polytheists, Abū Bakr, son of Ayyūb, Friend of the Commander of the Faithful,
			<lb n="10"/>
		may God make valid his orders and prohibitions, make the tongues
			<lb n="11"/>
		of men speak his praise and thanks, illuminate by good deeds
			<lb n="12"/>
		the times of his nights and the hours of his dawns, revive hopes
			<lb n="13"/>
		through the bounties which his clouds rain and in which his beneficient days are spent;
			<lb n="14"/>
		and [he ordered] to include in it as follows: We never cease, thank God, to protect the subjects
			<lb n="15"/>
		whose affairs were entrusted by God to us, and whose welfare was put
			<lb n="16"/>
		by the pure [religious] Law into our hands;
			<lb n="17"/>
		we remove harmful hand from them, and reward those of them
			<lb n="18"/>
		who follow the path of benevolence;
			<lb n="19"/>
		we forgive their stumbling, and avert their sorrow and misfortune.
			<lb n="20"/>
		We double this for their patriarchs and monks,
			<lb n="21"/>
		priests and clergymen, their ascetics
			<lb n="22"/>
		who inhabit cells, and religious who retreat into monasteries;
			<lb n="23"/>
		and we appoint as their superiors those whom they prefer.
			<lb n="24"/>
		We have ordered to treat the monks of the aforementioned
			<lb n="25"/>
		monastery according to their old-established custom
			<lb n="26"/>
		and to leave them to follow their long-settled and agreed rules,
			<lb n="27"/>
		and to accord to them protection, guarding, safe-keeping
			<lb n="28"/>
		and defence; to prevent people from doing them harm or
			<lb n="29"/>
		from intending damage against them, or from transgressing by changing
			<lb n="30"/>
		their current customs,
			<lb n="31"/>
		of from proceeding to render unsafe the road which is used for visits to them;
			<lb n="32"/>
		and that the Bedouins, or for that matter anyone else, whether of the same religion as they
			<lb n="33"/>
		or not, be kept from oppressing them
			<lb n="34"/>
		or forcing them to relinquish the rules according to which they have been
			<lb n="35"/>
		treated; and that visitors to them from Syria be not interfered with in any manner of harm or damage.
			<lb n="36"/>
		Let all amīrs and governors
			<lb n="37"/>
		(may God assist them), lieutenants,
			<lb n="38"/>
		and officials in general, who become aware of this ordinance, be sure to act according to its order
			<lb n="39"/>
		and follow its instruction and to disapprove of
			<lb n="40"/>
		those who knowingly contravene it - acting
			<lb n="41"/>
		in conformity with it and relying upon the noble signature
			<lb n="42"/>
		above it, if God (may He be exalted) wills.
			<lb n="43"/>
		Written this sixteenth of Muḥarram, the year Five-hundred Ninety Two.
			<lb n="44"/>
		Praise be to God alone, and may God bless our lord Muḥammad and his pure family
			<lb n="45"/>
		and give them much peace.
			<lb n="46"/>
		God is sufficient for us; how good a Keeper is He!
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
