<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2111" xml:id="SternMerchants" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.SternItalianMerchants</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">SternMerchants</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  صلوات اللّه وبركاته ونوامي زكواته وأفضل سلامه وتحيّاته على 
<lb n="3"/>  مولانا وسيّدنا الإمام الآمر بأحكام اللّه أمير المومنپن 
<lb n="4"/>  وعلى آبائه الطّاهرين وأبنائه الأكرمين صلاة دائمة باقية 
<lb n="5"/>  إلى يوم الدّين المملوك يقبّل الأرض أمام المواقف 
<lb n="6"/>  الشّريفة المعظّمة النّبويّة ضاعف اللّه أنوارها وأعلى 
<lb n="7"/>  اللّه منارها وينهي تواصل حضور تجّار الرّوم الواصلين 
<lb n="8"/>  بالأخشاب الّذين كان المملوك أنهى وصولهم وهم سرجه 
<lb n="9"/>  بن قسطنطين وسر<gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character" /> <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">نقولا </lem><rdg resp="LS">نقولا</rdg></app> بن هحلم وغرس بن <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">لبّن </lem><rdg resp="APD">لبّن</rdg></app> الملفطاني 
<lb n="10"/>  والرّواح وبون سنيون الجنوي ومن معهم من 
<lb n="11"/>  أصحابهم ذاكرين أنّهم إلى حين تسطير المملوك لم يتقرّر 
<lb n="12"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> هذه <gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="character" /> الأخشاب الّتي <gap reason="illegible" extent="5" unit="character" /> إليها ولا وصل إليهم من 
<lb n="13"/>  <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> <gap reason="illegible" precision="low" extent="3"/> 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>ṣalawātu ăl lāhi wa barakātu hu wa nawāmī zakawāti hi wa ʾafḍalu salāmi hi wa taḥiyyāti hi ʿalà 
 <lb n="3"/>mawlā nā wa sayyidi nā ăl ʾimāmi ăl ʾāmiri bi ʾaḥkāmi ăl lāhi ʾamīri ăl muʾminīna 
 <lb n="4"/>wa ʿalà ʾābāʾi hi ăṭ ṭāhirīna wa ʾabnāʾi hi ăl ʾakramīna ṣalāẗ:an dāʾimaẗ:an bāqiyaẗ:an 
 <lb n="5"/>ʾilà yawmi ăd dīni ăl mamlūku yuqabbilu ăl ʾarḍa ʾamāma ăl mawāqifi 
 <lb n="6"/>ăš šarīfaẗi ăl muʿaẓẓamaẗi ăn nabawiyyaẗi ḍāʿafa ăl lāhu ʾanwāra hā wa ʾaʿlà 
 <lb n="7"/>ăl lāhu manāra hā wa yunhī tawāṣula ḥuḍūri tuǧǧāri ăr rūmi ăl wāṣilīna 
 <lb n="8"/>bi ăl ʾaḫšābi ăllaḏīna kāna ăl mamlūku ʾanhà wuṣūla hum wa hum sarǧuhu 
 <lb n="9"/>bnu qusṭanṭīna wa sr* BFwlʾ niqūlā bnu hḥlm wa ġrassu bnu liyuna lubbina ăl malfiṭāniyyu 
 <lb n="10"/>wa ăr rwʾḥ wa būn:un snywn ăl ǧanwiyyu wa man maʿ hum min 
 <lb n="11"/>ʾaṣḥābi him ḏākirīna ʾanna hum ʾilà ḥīni tasṭīri ăl mamlūki lam yataqarrar 
 <lb n="12"/>*** hāḏihi **** ăl ʾaḫšāb ăllatī ***** ʾilay hā wa lā waṣla ʾilay him min 
 <lb n="13"/>*** *** *** 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		The benediction of God and his blessings, his increasing benefactions and most excellent peace and greetings, be upon
			<lb n="3"/>
		our Master and Lord, the Imām al-Āmir bi-Aḥkām Allāh, Commander of the Faithful,
			<lb n="4"/>
		and his pure ancestors and noble descendants - benedictions that should last and remain
			<lb n="5"/>
		till the Day of Judgement. The slave kisses the earth before the noble
			<lb n="6"/>
		and exalted prophetical presence, may God double its light and may God extoll
			<lb n="7"/>
		its beacon, and reports the continued arrival of the Rūm merchants, who came
			<lb n="8"/>
		bringing the timber and whose coming the slave had reported. They are: Sergius
			<lb n="9"/>
		the son of Constantine, ..... the son of ......, Grasso (?) the son of Leo (?) the Amalfitan,
			<lb n="10"/>
		......., and Bon .... the Genoese, and their companions
			<lb n="11"/>
		who are with them. They say that up to the time of the slave&#039;s writing it has not been established
			<lb n="12"/>
		....... the timber ..... reached them
			<lb n="13"/>
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
