<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2141" xml:id="Torrey_Abbott" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>P.Torrey</title>
</titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
             <authority>The Arabic Papyrology Database</authority>
             <idno type="filename">Torrey_Abbott</idno>
             <idno type="ddb-perseus-style"></idno>
             <idno type="ddb-hybrid"></idno>
             <idno type="HGV"></idno>
             <idno type="TM"></idno>
             <availability>
                <p>© The Arabic Papyrology Database. This work is licensed under a <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
<lb n="1"/>  بسم اللّه الرّحمن الرّحيم 
<lb n="2"/>  هذا ما اشترى أفئدة بن جرجرة الزّمردي اشترى من توسي 
<lb n="3"/>  <app type="BL"><lem resp="APD">وفقري </lem><rdg resp="APD">وقفري</rdg></app> بن أنفر اشترى منهم مصابة أنفر أبو فقري 
<lb n="4"/>  ‮الّذي كان توسي وفقري <sic n="superfluous">وروثها</sic>‪<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ورپوها</supplied>‬ من أبوهم أنفر وهو المنزل 
<lb n="5"/>  الّذي يكون في الدّار مع أباني اشترى ذلك منهم بثلثة الدّينر 
<lb n="6"/>  ‮عينا ذهبا ‪و‬فقد وصلت إلى توسي <supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">و</supplied>فقري الثّلثة الدّينر 
<lb n="7"/>  وبرئ فيها أفئدة إليهم وتوسي <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">و</supplied>فقري عندما باعوا أفئدة 
<lb n="8"/>  هذ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ه</supplied> المصابة الّتي ورثوها من أنفر في صحّة من عقلهم وجسمهم 
<lb n="9"/>  بمدخلها ومخرجها وأسفلها وأعلاها فإن ادّعا دعيا من 
<lb n="10"/>  النّاس شي بوجه من الوجوه أو بسبب من الأسباب فعلى توسي 
<lb n="11"/>  وفقري نفاذ ذلك من خالص مالهم وحد حدود هذه 
<lb n="12"/>  الّذي اشتراها أفئدة من توسي وفقري القبلي الطّريق وحدّها 
<lb n="13"/>  ‮الـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـپـ</supplied>ـحرى‬ منزل كيسان وحدّها الغربي منزل <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">الفنّ</unclear> وحدّها 
<lb n="14"/>  الشّرقي منزل يحنّس اشترا ذلك منهم بثلثة الدّينر عينا ذهبا 
<lb n="15"/>  شهد على إقرا<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ر</supplied> توسي ويعرفها نفسـ<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ـهـ</supplied>ـا واسمها جائز<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ة</supplied> 
<lb n="16"/>  أمرها تعرف ما لها وما عليها مرقس بن إسحق 
<lb n="17"/>  وكتب عنه عبد الصّمد السّرّاج شهادته بعلمه وحضرته 
<lb n="18"/>  وأبتولة بن هرون وكتب عنه عبد الصّمد شهادته بعلمه 
<lb n="19"/>  وحضرته وقزمان بن سيّد هرون وكتب عنه عبد الصّمد شهادتـ<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">ـه</supplied> 
<lb n="20"/>  بعلمه وحضرته وسهم بن هرون وكتب عنه 
<lb n="21"/>  عبد الصّمد شهادته بعلمه وحضرته 
<lb n="22"/>  وإسحاق بن إبرهيم القرشي وكتب شهادته بيده 
<lb n="23"/>  وإبرهيم بن أيّو<supplied reason="omitted" cert="high">ب</supplied> وكتب عنه عبد الصّمد شهادته بمحضرته 
<lb n="24"/>  <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">بمسـ</supplied><unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">ـجد</unclear> <unclear reason="undefined" cert="high">إسكندرية</unclear> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">في</supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="high">الـ</supplied>ـدّيوان وكتب في رمضان 
<lb n="25"/>  سنة خمس و<supplied reason="lost" cert="high">مائـ</supplied>ـتين 
</ab></div>
         <div type="edition"><ab>
 <lb n="1"/>bi smi ăl lāhi ăr raḥmāni ăr raḥīmi 
 <lb n="2"/>hāḏā mā ĭštarà ʾafʾidaẗu bnu ǧarǧaraẗa ăz zumrudiyyu ĭštarà min tūsī 
 <lb n="3"/>wa faqrī qafrī bni ʾanfara ĭštarà min hum muṣābaẗa ʾanfara ʾabū faqrī 
 <lb n="4"/>ăllaḏī kāna tūsī wa faqrī waraṯū hā‬ min ʾabū hum ʾanfara wa huwa ăl manzilu 
 <lb n="5"/>ăllaḏī yakūnu fī ăd dāri maʿa ʾabānī ĭštarà ḏālika min hum bi ṯalāṯaẗi ăd dīnāri 
 <lb n="6"/>ʿayn:an ḏahab:an wa fa qad waṣalat ʾilà tūsī wa faqrī ăṯ ṯalāṯaẗu ăd dīnāri 
 <lb n="7"/>wa bariʾa fī hā ʾafʾidaẗu ʾilay him wa tūsī wa faqrī ʿindamā bāʿū ʾafʾidaẗa 
 <lb n="8"/>hāḏihi ăl muṣābaẗa ăllatī waraṯū hā min ʾanfara fī ṣiḥḥaẗ:in min ʿaqli him wa ǧismi him 
 <lb n="9"/>bi madḫali hā wa maḫraǧi hā wa ʾasfali hā wa ʾaʿlā hā fa ʾini ĭddaʿā dāʿiy:an min 
 <lb n="10"/>ăn nāsi šayʾ bi waǧh:in mina ăl wuǧūhi ʾaw bi sabab:in mina ăl ʾasbābi fa ʿalà tūsī 
 <lb n="11"/>wa faqrī nafāḏu ḏālika min ḫāliṣi māli him wa ḥaddu ḥudūdi hāḏihi 
 <lb n="12"/>ăllaḏī ĭštarā hā ʾafʾidaẗu min tūsī wa faqrī ăl qibliyyu ăṭ ṭarīqu wa ḥaddu hā 
 <lb n="13"/>ăl baḥriyyu manzilu kaysāna wa ḥaddu hā ăl ġarbiyyu manzilu ăl fanni wa ḥaddu hā 
 <lb n="14"/>ăš šarqiyyu manzilu yuḥannisa ĭštarā ḏālika min hum bi ṯalāṯaẗi ăd dīnāri ʿayn:an ḏahab:an 
 <lb n="15"/>šahida ʿalà ʾiqrāri tūsī wa yaʿrifu hā nafsa hā wa ĭsma hā ǧāʾizaẗa 
 <lb n="16"/>ʾamri hā taʿrifu mā la hā wa mā ʿalay hā murqusu bnu ʾisḥāqa 
 <lb n="17"/>wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi ăs sarrāǧu šahādata hu bi ʿilmi hi wa ḥaḍrati hi 
 <lb n="18"/>wa ʾabtūlaẗu bnu hārūna wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi šahādata hu bi ʿilmi hi 
 <lb n="19"/>wa ḥaḍrati hi wa quzmānu bnu sayyidi hārūna wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi šahādata hu 
 <lb n="20"/>bi ʿilmi hi wa ḥaḍrati hi wa sahmu bnu hārūna wa kataba ʿan hu 
 <lb n="21"/>ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi šahādata hu bi ʿilmi hi wa ḥaḍrati hi 
 <lb n="22"/>wa ʾisḥāqu bnu ʾibrāhīma ăl qurašiyyu wa kataba šahādata hu bi yadi hi 
 <lb n="23"/>wa ʾibrāhīmu bnu ʾayyūba wa kataba ʿan hu ʿabdu ăṣ ṣamadi šahādata hu bi maḥḍarati hi 
 <lb n="24"/>bi masǧid ʾiskandariyyaẗ fī ăd dīwāni wa kutiba fī ramaḍāna 
 <lb n="25"/>sanaẗa ḫams:in wa miʾatayni 
  </ab></div>
<div type="translation"><ab>
			<lb n="1"/>
		In the name of God, the compassionate, the mercyful.
			<lb n="2"/>
		This is which Afʾida b. Jarjara al-Zumrudī purchased from Tūsī
			<lb n="3"/>
		and Faqrī, the son of Anfar. He bought from them the estate of Anfar Abū Faqrī,
			<lb n="4"/>
		which Tūsī and Faqrī had inherited from their father Anfar; and it is the dwelling house
			<lb n="5"/>
		which is in the enclosure with certain (other) buildings. He bought this from them for 3 dinars,
			<lb n="6"/>
		in gold coin. The whole amount of the dinars was delivered to Tūsī and Faqrī,
			<lb n="7"/>
		and by it (this payment) Afʾida became free of obligation to them. Tūsī and Faqrī, at the time when they sold to Afʾida
			<lb n="8"/>
		this estate which they had inherited from Anfar, were of sound mind and body.
			<lb n="9"/>
		They sold it with its entrance and its exit, and with what is below and above its surface. If a claim shall be made by anyone
			<lb n="10"/>
		in any matter whatsoever or for any reason whatsoever, then upon Tūsī
			<lb n="11"/>
		and Faqrī falls its settlement from their own property. The boundaries of this
			<lb n="12"/>
		which Afʾida has purchased from Tūsī and Faqrī: The southern boundary is the street; its boundary
			<lb n="13"/>
		on the north is the dwelling of Kaisān; its western boundary is the dwelling of al-Fann (?); and its boundary
			<lb n="14"/>
		on the east is the dwelling of Yoḥannas. He bought this from them for 3 dinars in gold coin.
			<lb n="15"/>
		(The following witnesses) testified to the acknowledgment of Tūsī, (each) knowing her in person and in name, she being capable of transacting
			<lb n="16"/>
		her (business) affairs, knowing what is due to her, and what is required of her: Marqus b. Isḥāq
			<lb n="17"/>
		and ʿAbd al-Ṣamad, the saddler, wrote his testimony for him with his knowledge and in his presence.
			<lb n="18"/>
		And Abtūla b. Hārūn, and ʿAbd al-Ṣamad wrote his testimony for him with his knowledge
			<lb n="19"/>
		and in his presence. And Quzmān b. Sayyīd Hārūn, and ʿAbd al-Ṣamad wrote his testimony for him
			<lb n="20"/>
		with his knowledge and in his presence. And Sahm b. Hārūn, and
			<lb n="21"/>
		ʿAbd al-Ṣamad wrote his testimony for him, with his knowledge and in his presence.
			<lb n="22"/>
		And Isḥāq b. Ibrāhīm al-Qurašī, and he wrote his testimony with his (own) hand.
			<lb n="23"/>
		And Ibrāhīm b. Ayyūb, and ʿAbd al-Ṣamad wrote his testimony for him with his knowledge and in his presence.
			<lb n="24"/>
		? ? in the diwān (?) of Alexandria (?). And this was writen in (the month of) Ramaḍān, 
			<lb n="25"/>
		in the year 205.
</ab></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
